<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An answer to the representer's reflections upon the state and view of the controversy with a reply to the vindicator's full answer, shewing, that the vindicator has utterly ruined the new design of expounding and representing popery.</title>
            <author>Clagett, William, 1646-1688.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 267 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 71 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A33205</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C4376</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11070</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12387058</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12387058</idno>
            <idno type="VID">60867</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A33205)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 60867)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 655:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An answer to the representer's reflections upon the state and view of the controversy with a reply to the vindicator's full answer, shewing, that the vindicator has utterly ruined the new design of expounding and representing popery.</title>
                  <author>Clagett, William, 1646-1688.</author>
                  <author>Clagett, Nicholas, 1654-1727.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[11], 130 [i.e. 128] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Ric. Chiswell ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed by Wing to William Clagett; identified by some sources as being written by Nicolas Clagett. Cf. Halkett &amp; Laing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Gother, John, d. 1704. --  Reflections upon the answer to The papist mis-represented.</term>
               <term>Johnston, Joseph, d. 1723. --  Full answer to the second defence of the Exposition of the doctrine of the Church of England.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Corinne Vieracker</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Corinne Vieracker</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:60867:1"/>
            <p>Imprimatur, Liber cui Titulus, <hi>[An Anſwer to the Repreſenter's Reflections upon the View of the Controverſie, with a Reply to the Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cator's Full Anſwer.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Jan. 21. 1687.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>H. Maurice,</hi> R<hi rend="sup">mo.</hi> in Chriſto P. D. Wilhelmo Archiep. Cant. a Sacris.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:60867:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ANSWER TO THE REPRESENTER's REFLECTIONS UPON THE STATE and VIEW OF THE CONTROVERSY. With a REPLY to the <hi>VINDICATOR's full Anſwer;</hi> SHEWING, That the Vindicator has utterly Ruined the New Deſign of <hi>Expounding</hi> and <hi>Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting</hi> POPERY.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Ric. Chiſwell,</hi> at the <hi>Roſe</hi> and <hi>Crown</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard. MDCLXXXVIII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:60867:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:60867:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Have here brought together the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> and the <hi>Vindicator,</hi> two Friends that ſeem to have been great ſtrangers to one another of late. They have been ſo buſy each of them is purſuing his own <hi>Proper</hi> part, that they have had no eye to the ſafety of that deſign which is <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> to both.</p>
            <p>Nothing ſeems to require a more nice and exact care, then ſo to <hi>Expound</hi> and <hi>Repreſent</hi> the <hi>Roman</hi> Religion, as to gain <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and yet not to hazard the very pretences to Infallibility in the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, and to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity amongſt themſelves. And therefore, ſince theſe Two were engaged in this Work, they ought above all things to have proceeded by common Advice; and like Two even Squares, if it were poſſible, they ſhould have touched one another in every Point.</p>
            <p>But ſomething or other has broken off this Correſpondence: For the <hi>Vindicator</hi> has undone the <hi>Repreſenter,</hi> if that Man can be undone by another, who had undone himſelf be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. And betwixt 'em Both, there is a hopeful Cauſe loſt, which can never be retrieved but by new Hands, or by a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared War between theſe two, in which the <hi>Repreſenter,</hi> if he can, muſt undo the <hi>Vindicator.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> has a better Opinion of his own Affairs, he is a happy Man; For I dare almoſt undertake, that for the future no Body ſhall go about to diſturb him, but he ſhall keep Poſſeſſion in Peace.</p>
            <p>I was for this time prevailed with to come in for one of his
<pb facs="tcp:60867:3"/>Anſwerers. He has ſhak'd off two or three already, and he is enough to tire out all the Controvertiſts in Town.</p>
            <p>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> write againſt him is now grown as unprofitable a drudgery, as to plow upon a Rock, where there is no Soil to be turned up. He gives little or no occaſion to write any thing that will anſwer the attention of a <hi>judicious</hi> Reader, and hardly of a <hi>curious</hi> one He may be confuted indeed, and expoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as he deſerves to be; but 'tis but a meer trial of skill, which no body is the better for. To Anſwer him now, will never pay the charge of a Book, and therefore he that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakes it, muſt either leave him, as he was wont to ſerve his Adverſaries, or be content with <hi>Pertinence</hi> where 'tis good for nothing.</p>
            <p>This is the beſt Apology I have to make for thoſe barren Pages which occur ſometimes in the Anſwer to him. And if the Reader will accept it now, I paſs my Word to need it no more. The <hi>Repreſenter</hi> may from this time, either carry on the <hi>Character</hi> Controverſy upon his old <hi>Thirty ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi> Points, or he may think of ſome new Additions to patch up a <hi>Fourth</hi> Part out of his firſt <hi>Three,</hi> as he has compound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a <hi>Third</hi> out of his <hi>Firſt</hi> and <hi>Second;</hi> and he may come out with <hi>Fifteen</hi> freſh Articles of Repreſentation once a year as long as he lives, without any great fear of being oppoſed.</p>
            <p>He may now write <hi>with a Privilege,</hi> and ſay what he pleaſes, if <hi>H. Hills</hi> will but give his conſent; for I think no body elſe is like to diſcourage him. And if he puts out a <hi>Reply</hi> to this Anſwer, he ſhall do very well, but then I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe him he ſhall Anſwer it himſelf; and get the Victory by fighting the Battel on both ſides.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Vindicator</hi> is making all the haſte he can after him: In truth the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> came firſt to perfection, by nothing elſe but getting the ſtart of him. For I have no skill at all, if the next Book that the <hi>Vindicator</hi> writes in this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſy, does not make him a <hi>Privileged</hi> Author too.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:60867:3"/>
            <p>Indeed if he ſhould happen to be as good as his word, and try to Anſwer <hi>the Diſcourſe of Extreme Unction,</hi> or fall upon ſome freſh Subject the next thing he does, he will be but an ordinary man ſo much the longer.</p>
            <p>For when thoſe men begin a Controverſie, they write like other men, and ſo long 'tis poſſible to Anſwer them; but they have ſuch a way of carrying it on, as will wear out the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience of any man living. When their Arguments are ſpent without doing any execution, one would believe they muſt of neceſſity yield; but they never appear invincible till then, and they bring ſuch terrible Reſerves, when they can Reaſon no longer, that the beſt we can do, is to make an honourable Retreat.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Vindicator</hi> is much in the ſame ſtate that the Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenter was in, when his laſt Anſwerer plainly ſhewed him that he had <hi>dropt</hi> the <hi>whole Controverſie,</hi> and loſt his whole Cauſe: For the <hi>Vindicator,</hi> as I have ſhewn in the Reply, has loſt the very ſame Cauſe another way; if therefore he intends to be as famous as the <hi>Repreſenter,</hi> I expect from him a <hi>Preface,</hi> or the like, <hi>containing Reflections</hi> upon my Reply to his Letter; and if that happens, he may expect from me one Reply more, and after that, I promiſe him too, that, for me, he ſhall flouriſh all the days of his life.</p>
            <p>It was the ſame ungrateful work to have to do with one of theſe Pieces, as with both; and 'twas pity that more than one man ſhould diſoblige his hands about it; and therefore when I had the <hi>Repreſenter</hi>'s Performance before me, I needed no Intreaty to tack the Vindicator's <hi>Full Anſwer</hi> to it; in my Reply to which <hi>Anſwer</hi> I have ſhown theſe men to one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and the <hi>Repreſenter,</hi> I cannot but fancy, looks like a <hi>Chymiſt,</hi> that having laid out all he is worth in trying for the <hi>Philoſophers</hi> Stone, is in the very nick of his unreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble hopes, undone by an unlucky Friend, who comes in hastily, and by one moments medling, confounds the whole Operation.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:60867:4"/>
            <p>The <hi>Repreſenter</hi> had been ſetting up a good ſubſtantial <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery</hi> for Proteſtants to be fond of, which was to be found in the profeſſion of <hi>Living</hi> men, with whom we may change a word, as occaſion ſerves; but the <hi>Vindicator</hi> who was in with him in the ſame deſign, muſt needs ſhow that he could help it forward by <hi>putting words together</hi> in leſs than a <hi>years</hi> time; and ſo the Popery they have been labouring for ſo long, is dwindled into a <hi>Church-ſenſe,</hi> which 'tis in vain for men to <hi>expound</hi> one to another; he has made it an <hi>Inviſible,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>accountable Popery, and ſomething like a Spirit, that troubles the houſe all night, but no body ever ſaw it.</p>
            <p>This, I take it, must needs be a deadly diſappointment to the <hi>Repreſenter;</hi> and what if theſe two men ſhould now ſerve one another, as they have ſerved us? They are both of them like a pair of Diamonds, hard and ſharp, and nothing can cut the one ſo handſomly as his Fellow.</p>
            <p>If they ſhould chance to fall foul, it would be indeed a <hi>Comical</hi> end of the Controverſie, and not unſuitable to the <hi>Repreſenter,</hi> who ſtudied to make a Farce of it, when he brought in his <hi>Phanatick</hi> Sermon.</p>
            <p>But let them make what end of it they pleaſe, there is a time when it is decent for us to give over, that as hitherto Truth has loſt no ground for want of Argument, ſo it may loſe no honour by want of Diſcretion.</p>
            <p>I have given up the <hi>Repreſenter,</hi> and ſhall but once more trouble the <hi>Vindicator,</hi> which will be more than enough for him, ſince ere long he may expect from his Antagoniſt ſuch an Account of the Articles of the Biſhop of <hi>Meaux,</hi> as will be eſteemed by Judicious and Impartial men, a Final Determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of that Controverſie.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:60867:4"/>
            <head>The CONTENTS of the ANSWER to the REPRESENTER.</head>
            <list>
               <item>HIS Extravagance in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting to the Caſe of the <hi>Diſſenters. Page</hi> 1</item>
               <item>—And his Indiſcretion in upbraiding us with their Sufferings. <hi>Page</hi> 5</item>
               <item>That the Diſcourſe againſt <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> is not ſcurrilous. <hi>Page</hi> 9</item>
               <item>His Pretence that we have written againſt <hi>Popery</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Succeſs, is falſe, and impertinent if it were true. <hi>Page</hi> 10</item>
               <item>That the <hi>Papiſts</hi> are to thank the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> for the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vival of theſe Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies. <hi>Page</hi> 13</item>
               <item>That he now writes to praiſe himſelf, and what he had written before. <hi>Page</hi> 16</item>
               <item>—And preſſes upon us with meer Confidence, and te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious Repetitions. <hi>Page</hi> 21</item>
               <item>That he is a Falſe Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, becauſe he has con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed one part of the Character of a <hi>Papiſt. Page</hi> 28</item>
               <item>The Folly of his Clamour, that we pretend to know what <hi>Popery</hi> is, better than the <hi>Papists. Page</hi> 29</item>
               <item>His Offer to receive us into the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> upon the Terms which he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds, conſidered. <hi>Page</hi> 31
<list>
                     <item>—That we cannot with a good Conſcience ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept his Offer. <hi>Page</hi> 32</item>
                     <item>That if we could, he can give us no Security a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Old Popery. Page</hi> 33</item>
                     <item>That if he were able to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure us, we have no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to think that he is willing. <hi>Page</hi> 34</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>His Inſincerity in telling us that he deteſts ſome Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines and Practices with which his Anſwerer char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and in refuſing to ſay what they are in particular. <hi>Page</hi> 35</item>
               <item>The true meaning of theſe Offers to receive us upon the Profeſſion of his <hi>New Popery. Page</hi> 38</item>
               <item>—And this exemplified by the Terms upon which the Converts of the City of
<pb facs="tcp:60867:5"/>
                  <hi>Orange</hi> were reconciled to the Church of <hi>Rome. P.</hi> 39</item>
               <item>That he has abuſed Mr. <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tague,</hi> by a Falſe Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of his Judgment con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Homilies of our Church. <hi>P.</hi> 45</item>
               <item>That he continues his Charge of Miſrepreſentation upon ſome of our Men, without replying to the Anſwers made in their Defence. <hi>P.</hi> 49</item>
               <item>—But makes bold to ſay, that the Author of <hi>the View</hi> confeſſed what that Author clearly diproved. <hi>Pag.</hi> 53</item>
               <item>His Pretence for declining a particular Anſwer to the <hi>View. Pag.</hi> 57</item>
               <item>His pleaſant way of proving that he has not forſaken the Defence of his Double Characters. <hi>Pag.</hi> 58</item>
               <item>A brief Rehearſal of the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenter</hi>'s Performances. <hi>Pag.</hi> 66</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <head>The CONTENTS of the REPLY to the VINDICATOR.</head>
            <list>
               <item>THAT the Apologies of the New Converts in <hi>France</hi> are a clear Evidence, both that the Diſtinction between <hi>Old</hi> Popery and <hi>New</hi> Popery is generally underſtood there, and that 'tis not a Diſtinction with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Difference. <hi>Pag.</hi> 71</item>
               <item>That he ſtrives in vain to ſhew the Caſe of Monſieur <hi>Imbert</hi> to be no Argument of ſuch a Difference. <hi>Pag.</hi> 78</item>
               <item>That the New Popery is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered for the ſake of the Old one. <hi>Pag.</hi> 82</item>
               <item>The <hi>Good-Friday</hi> Service of the <hi>Miſſal</hi> as to the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of the <hi>Croſs,</hi> once more explained. <hi>Pag.</hi> 83</item>
               <item>How Matters ſtand between Mr. <hi>de Meaux,</hi> Mr. <hi>Widen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>felt,</hi> and Father <hi>Craſſet,</hi> as to the Worſhip of the B. Virgin. <hi>Pag.</hi> 85</item>
               <item>The Vindicator's Rule to know the Churches Senſe in theſe things, by her <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Councils,</hi> and by her <hi>Univerſal Practice,</hi> conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. <hi>Pag.</hi> 88</item>
               <item>That if there be another way to know the Churches Senſe in Doctrines of Faith, beſides her <hi>Voice in General Councils,</hi> and Two Poperies be made to appear that way, the Vindicator gets
<pb facs="tcp:60867:5"/>nothing by Councils. <hi>P.</hi> 90</item>
               <item>That if there be no other way, yet even by this way it is demonſtrated that they have <hi>Two Poperies</hi> amongſt them. <hi>Pag.</hi> 93</item>
               <item>That the Vindicator has brought things to that paſs, that he makes Councils as inſignificant, as the Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenter has made the <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi> to be. <hi>Pag.</hi> 101</item>
               <item>That to avoid <hi>Two Poperies,</hi> he has in truth not left ſo much as <hi>One Popery</hi> amongſt <hi>Papists. Pag.</hi> 105</item>
               <item>But after all, the ill Language we have from the Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cator here, for not grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that his is the True <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery;</hi> and the ill Uſage we ſhould meet with elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, for contending that it is the True one, is a ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Demonſtration of <hi>Two Poperies. Pag.</hi> 106</item>
               <item>A final Defence of our Charge againſt the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> about the Veneration of Reliques. <hi>Pag.</hi> 107</item>
               <item>Of Judging of the Churches Senſe by her <hi>Univerſal Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice. Pag.</hi> 110</item>
               <item>The Biſhop of <hi>Meaux's</hi> argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing againſt the <hi>Pagans</hi> from their Practices, ſhewn to be good againſt the Church of <hi>Rome. Pag.</hi> 111</item>
               <item>That the <hi>Vindicator</hi> has utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ruined the <hi>Repreſenter</hi>'s Deſigns; <hi>Pag.</hi> 113</item>
               <item>— And at the ſame time betraied the Biſhop of <hi>Meaux</hi>'s Expoſition too. <hi>Pag.</hi> 118</item>
               <item>Particular Replies to what remains in his <hi>Full Anſwer. Pag.</hi> 120</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="answer">
            <pb facs="tcp:60867:6"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:60867:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>AN ANSWER TO THE REPRESENTERS REFLECTIONS UPON THE STATE and VIEW OF THE CONTROVERSY.</head>
            <p>HIS firſt Reflection upon the <hi>Stater,</hi> is for Miſrepreſenting the caſe of the <hi>Diſſenters.</hi> Had the <hi>Stater</hi> done ſo, the Repreſenter had buſineſs enough of his own, to let them ſpeak for themſelves. But he had a better opinion of himſelf than ſo. <hi>Hitherto,</hi> ſays he, <hi>I have been concerned with ſuch who have most unjuſtly traduced and expoſed the Doctrine and Faith of our Church,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pref. p. 1.</note> 
               <hi>and now of late an upſtart ſort of Miſrepreſenter has called upon me, who pretends to give an account of the Preſent State,</hi> &amp;c. Which is juſt as if he had ſaid, <q>Have not I for this three years and upwards ſo mauld the <hi>Traducers</hi> and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:60867:7"/>
                  <hi>Expoſers</hi> of Papiſts, that they feel it to this very hour? How then durſt this upſtart ſort of Miſrepreſenter ſhew his head, as if there were not ſuch a Man as I in the Nation?</q>
            </p>
            <p>To this tune he begins, which is not ſeemly in a Man, whoſe Character requires more Humility and Modeſty than this comes to: For I am told he is a <hi>Reverend Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> which makes me the more ſorry for him.</p>
            <p>I am reſolved to be very Civil to the Repreſenter; but as he has behaved himſelf, I am at a great loſs how to expreſs it. His falling upon the forementioned Author as a <hi>Miſrepreſenter,</hi> and the pretence upon which he does it too, is ſo very much out of the common Road of pertinence, that I know not what to do with him. It looks as if he had been a little unſettled with that overweening opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on I mentioned juſt now; and then that thoſe words of <hi>Repreſenting</hi> and <hi>Miſrepreſenting</hi> had rung in his Head ſo long, that while he is awake, he thinks of nothing but chaſtiſing <hi>Miſrepreſenters,</hi> and Dreams of it when he ſleeps, and can find nothing but <hi>Miſrepreſentation</hi> in every Line of ours that he reads; and as if there were ſome cauſe to fear that he may happily forget every Name that he has, but that of a <hi>Repreſenter;</hi> To pretend, as he does, that that Author had <hi>not taken care to ſhew the State of the Controverſy as it was;</hi> and that he <hi>intends</hi> to make this <hi>appear as far as concerns</hi> the Repreſenter; and then preſently to fall upon the <hi>Diſſenter</hi>'s Caſe, is ſuch a confuſion of things, that there muſt be a diſturbance in a Man's head to put them together. And 'tis ſtill a worſe ſign, that he ſpeaks of that Author's <hi>calling upon him: Now of late,</hi> ſays he, <hi>an upſtart ſort of a Miſrepreſenter has called upon me.</hi> For what ſhould it be, but the working of his own Head, that made him fancy that Author <hi>called upon him,</hi> where I dare ſay, he never ſo
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:60867:7"/>much as <hi>thought</hi> of him? For who would think that the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> ſhould be at all concerned for the true ſtating of matters that concerned the Diſſenters?</p>
            <p>It muſt be confeſſed that theſe are ill tokens, when they come thick upon one another; for ſome ſuch diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order as I am ſpeaking of, appears in the very firſt Line of his <hi>Preface;</hi> which is ſo much the more remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, becauſe that which is uppermoſt uſually comes firſt. <hi>'Tis my fate,</hi> ſays he, <hi>always to have to do with Miſrepre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters.</hi> By which it ſhould ſeem that this conceit is <hi>never</hi> out of his Head. If he does but touch a Book written by any of us, his Imagination preſently tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forms it into a <hi>Miſrepreſenter:</hi> And what is meerly his own <hi>Fancy, viz.</hi> That he has <hi>always to do with Miſrepre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters,</hi> he takes to be his <hi>Fate,</hi> as if he were deſtined to be the ſcourge of this ſort of men. And ſo <hi>The Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent state of the Controverſy</hi> coming croſs in his way, the Author of it ſeemed to him to be an <hi>upſtart ſort of Miſrepreſenter,</hi> as the Flock of Sheep ſeemed an Army of Giants to the wiſe <hi>Don,</hi> who alſo thought himſelf <hi>called upon</hi> to redreſs the wrongs that were done any where in the World.</p>
            <p>But I will not peremptorily conclude what the Man ails; all this, it may be, is but deſign, and the Man has a ſerious meaning, tho' at firſt ſight one would be apt to think that he is a little too much ſhattered to have any meaning at all. It may be ſaid, that there is this pertinence in his matter, that it ſeems to ſerve a General end, <hi>viz.</hi> to do the Church of <hi>England</hi> a good turn, which he has been owing to her ever ſince he fell off to the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> and this may be all the perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence that he very much cares for; only becauſe 'tis good to keep to a point, or at leaſt to ſeem ſo to do, therefore when he has raked up a few more materials, he knows
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:60867:8"/>how to diſpoſe them under theſe words of <hi>Miſrepreſenting</hi> and <hi>Repreſenting;</hi> and then out comes a Book. If it be thus, he was only to blame for ſtreightning himſelf at firſt, and for promiſing long ſince that he would keep to his <hi>Repreſenting</hi> Poſt. He ſhould have called that Book of his which led the way to the reſt, The <hi>Firſt Part of Miſcellanies againſt the Church of</hi> England. For this Title would have ſerved him to have written Books <hi>Part</hi> after <hi>Part</hi> as long as he ſhould live; And I think the pertinence of 'em would never have been queſtioned.</p>
            <p>But what has the Author of the <hi>Preſent State</hi> ſaid, to bring upon himſelf the charge of <hi>Miſrepreſenting?</hi> Why, it ſeems he made bold to ſay, that ſome of the Clergy of this City had written Caſes for the ſatisfaction of the Diſſenters in <hi>the plaineſt and moſt inoffenſive manner they could.</hi> But where is the Miſrepreſentation? Was not the manner <hi>plain</hi> and <hi>inoffenſive?</hi> Yes, ſays the <hi>Repreſenter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pref. p. 2.</note> 
               <hi>as to the Method and Stile in which thoſe Tracts were penned, for all as I know, there was plain and inoffenſive writing.</hi> So that, <hi>for all as he knows,</hi> the <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> too might be as plain and inoffenſive as the <hi>Method</hi> and <hi>Stile</hi> of thoſe Books; for I perceive he never read them. What then can be the Miſrepreſentation? To be ſhort, it lies in this, That the Diſſenters were at that time urged with other <hi>Perſuaſives,</hi>
               <note place="margin">P. 3.</note> 
               <hi>by Writ, by Summons, by Seiſing of Goods,</hi> &amp;c. Well, but did that Author deny this? No; but he did not mention it; and therefore <hi>he did not repreſent the state of the Controverſy between the Churches of</hi> England <hi>and of</hi> Rome,
<note place="margin">P. 2.</note> 
               <hi>as it is, but as he would have it thought to be; viz.</hi> becauſe he did not at all Repreſent the ſtate of the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> with reſpect to the Laws, when the Divines wrote for their ſatisfaction. He that can hale and pull in things in this faſhion, will never want matter; but to let that paſs, and to wander
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:60867:8"/>along with him for a while, as every man is bound to do, that will keep him company; I cannot underſtand that it was that Author's Duty to make the leaſt mention of the execution of the Laws upon the Diſſenters, unleſs the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> can prove, That becauſe he either ſtudies to be impertinent, or cannot help it, therefore we are all bound to be ſo too. The <hi>Stater</hi>'s buſineſs was to give an account to his Friend how the Controverſie ſtood be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween us and the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> and he introduced his Matter by ſhewing, That the Divines having written ſome Diſcourſes for the ſake of the Diſſenters, and that with good ſucceſs, did then apply themſelves to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies with the <hi>Romaniſts:</hi> But becauſe he did not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter upon an Enquiry whether the Laws had not more to do in this matter than the Diſcourſes of the Divines, therefore the Repreſenter talks of that Author's <hi>impoſing upon his Reader with poor ſhifts in a matter ſo well known;</hi>
               <note place="margin">P. 3.</note> 
               <hi>and that he muſt not paſs for a true Stater of Controverſie, who thus tells the Story by halves;</hi> ſo that unleſs we drag in matters that are nothing to the purpoſe, as he does, we <hi>tell Stories by halves;</hi> and no body will be ever able to <hi>State Controverſie</hi> right, that cannot foreſee what ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling thoughts will come into the <hi>Repreſenter</hi>'s head the next time he writes a Book: But ſince he is fallen up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this buſineſs, he may now pleaſe to obſerve, That neither the <hi>Stater,</hi> nor any of thoſe Divines of whom he made mention, uſed any of thoſe <hi>Perſwaſives</hi> of which the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> ſpeaks, but ſaved the Diſſenters from them, as far as it conſiſted with their Duty, and were by ſome people called Names for their pains. But I perceive his trouble is, that the <hi>Stater</hi> ſhould believe thoſe Diſcourſes had good Succeſs: <hi>For,</hi> ſays the man, <hi>'tis very probable that theſe ſort of Perſwaſives ſent more to the Church, than the Diſcourſes; ſo that by what I remember
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:60867:9"/>of thoſe times,</hi>
               <note place="margin">P. 3.</note> 
               <hi>had not the Church of</hi> England <hi>taken the Laſh in hand as well as the Pen, the Churches had continued as empty as they are at this day:</hi> Our Repreſenter plainly inſinuates by the way, that our Churches are ſomewhat <hi>empty at this day;</hi> and this is the very man who upon the preſent occaſion obſerves, That <hi>altho dealing out of Relations by Tale and by Scraps might paſs in a matter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond our memory,</hi>
               <note place="margin">P. 4.</note> 
               <hi>as of the Council of</hi> Trent, <hi>of</hi> Lateran, <hi>of Pope</hi> Gregory; <hi>yet to come thus with half Stories in a Concern of Yeſterday;</hi> oh! that is not to be endured. But whether our Churches are, as it were, <hi>empty,</hi> is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all doubt a <hi>Concern</hi> of <hi>to day;</hi> and for a man not to tell <hi>half-Stories</hi> of <hi>ſuch</hi> a Concern, but whole Stories the quite contrary, What is that, I pray? That he thinks it <hi>probable</hi> that the Diſſenters were more wrought upon by Sufferings than by the Diſcourſes of the Divines, I eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly grant; for he knows of a certain Church that has done more by <hi>thoſe ſort of Perſwaſives,</hi> than by all that ever was written in her behalf; as all <hi>Europe</hi> and both the <hi>Indies</hi> can bear her witneſs. Doubtleſs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he thinks it probable that our Church was a gainer by the execution of the Penal Laws at that time; but whether it was ſo or not, is another Queſtion: I find that where he mends the <hi>Staters</hi> Account for him, he would have had him to ſay,
<note place="margin">P. 4.</note> That it was <hi>very likely (for ſuch is the frailty of wicked man) that more were frighted and whipt to Church, than came thither by Force of our Reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Diſcourſes.</hi> By the way, he ſhould learn to be more grave and ſerious, than to make ſport with the <hi>Frailty of wicked man;</hi> which is a thing that a good Prieſt ought to lament, and to remedy what he can, by his Doctrine and Example: When he has to do with his <hi>Adverſaries,</hi> if he finds that any of them grows <hi>exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly impertinent,</hi> and when Argument forſakes them, fall
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:60867:9"/>to <hi>Ridiculing,</hi> or that they uſe Tricks to cover their <hi>Convictions,</hi> and do but diſcover them ſo much the more, let him lay it on handſomly without ſparing, if he likes this way of Correction beſt: But for a <hi>Prieſt of the living God</hi> to rally with the <hi>Frailty of wicked man,</hi> when he means nothing by it, but to help out a <hi>Lampoon</hi> upon a ſingle Adverſary whom he does not love, is very <hi>unprieſt-like,</hi> and a more likely way to make <hi>Atheists,</hi> than to mend that which he, it ſeems, can make merry withal, <hi>the Frailty of wicked man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well: But 'tis not ſo certain, that when the <hi>Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> were under the execution of the Laws; that then, I ſay, human <hi>Frailty</hi> wrought that way which he ſpeaks of; for it might work the quite contrary way; and the Orders for that purpoſe coming from above much about the ſame time, the offence which they took at that, might prejudice many of them againſt all that the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines could ſay, tho the Divines had no hand in it; for mankind is apt to be provoked, as well as to be frighted; and to act inconſiderately in one, as well as in the other caſe.</p>
            <p>But there is this Reaſon to think that they were rather the <hi>Diſcourſes</hi> than the <hi>Penalties,</hi> which filled our Churches, That the <hi>Proſecutions</hi> have been at an end a good while; and 'tis therefore to be hoped that the virtue of the <hi>Diſcourſes</hi> did the good work at firſt, and goes on to do it ſtill; for whatever the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, the Churches are as full <hi>at this day,</hi> as they were in thoſe <hi>times,</hi> when he pretends the Church of <hi>England</hi> took the <hi>Laſh</hi> in hand: They are ſo full, that a Reverend Father may come to ſpy and hearken, and think to eſcape in the Throng without being obſerved; and what if the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> has been upon this Miſſion himſelf? Then, I ſay, he ſhall Repreſent for thoſe that will truſt him; but for
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:60867:10"/>me and my Friends, never whilſt he breathes.</p>
            <p>As for his Story of one Mr.
<note place="margin">P. 2.</note> 
               <hi>de Laune,</hi> I know nothing of it. The <hi>Repreſenter</hi> ſays he wrote a Book, and was ſent to the <hi>Compter;</hi> but he does not ſay it was <hi>for writing that Book;</hi> tho he would inſinuate ſome ſuch matter; from which modeſty of his, if there be any truth at all in the ſtory, one might venture to conclude, that he knew the man was ſent to Priſon for ſomething elſe. And yet if he were ſent to Priſon for the writing of that Book, but if neither that Divine whom he wrote againſt nor any of the reſt, contributed to it ſo much as by a wiſh, the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> ſtings us not by this <hi>Reflection.</hi> Of this I have told him ſomething of my own know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg already.</p>
            <p>For what he ſays of ſome that were <hi>ſtarved,</hi> and of <hi>Orphans</hi> and <hi>Widows</hi> that were <hi>made</hi> ſo by the Penalties inflicted upon the Diſſenters, it is to be hoped that our <hi>Repreſenter</hi> over-does the buſineſs, and rants ſomewhat too Tragically:
<note place="margin">P. 3.</note> For my part, I have always thought that the uſe of thoſe <hi>Perſwaſives</hi> which he talks of, does at the long run, more miſchief to a Church than good; and if I may ſpeak my own experience, I do not find this Spirit of Moderation to prevail any where ſo much as in the Church of <hi>England.</hi> But the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> brings over the Sufferings of <hi>Diſſenters</hi> for nothing elſe but to prejudice them againſt us. I will not here enter into an Enquiry what reaſon there is for it; but this one thing I will ſay, That I am no leſs deſirous than himſelf, that the Diſſenters ſhould be very often told of their Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in thoſe times; only if a man will be telling them, then as the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> ſays, it would do well not to <hi>tell the Story by halves;</hi> but if he does, then (to return him ſome of his own words) I do not think, that <hi>with all his poor ſhifts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">P. 3.</note> 
               <hi>his Readers will be impoſed upon in a
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:60867:10"/>matter ſo well known.</hi> And therefore I, no leſs than the <hi>Repreſenter,</hi> deſire that the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> would think of all that is paſt, as long as they have a day to live.</p>
            <p>As to the Tracts that were ſoon after written againſt the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> obſerves that Two things were not mentioned by the <hi>Stater</hi> upon this occaſion, which we had upon the former; Not the <hi>Plain and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>offenſive manner</hi> of Writing; nor any <hi>News of Succeſs which theſe Diſcourſes had upon the Parties deſigned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the former he ſays,
<note place="margin">P. 5.</note> That the <hi>Stater was too con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcious of the ſcurrilous and bitter Spirit with which ſome of them were penned; that one againſt Tranſubſtantiation being Inſtance enough.</hi> By which he would inſinuate, that others of them too were written in the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: How hard is it for ſome men to be ſincere in any thing! I remember indeed ſome of theſe Expreſſions in that Diſcourſe which he produces, ſuch as <hi>Impudence, Nonſence, Monſtrous Stupidity,</hi> and the like. But I would know of the <hi>Repreſenter,</hi> whether there can be any juſt occaſion for letting theſe words looſe; and to the Senſe and Reaſon of Mankind I may appeal, if there can be an occaſion more juſt than this; for 'tis impoſſible we ſhould have greater Evidence that any thing is true, than we have that the Doctrine of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> is falſe; and then I may ask the <hi>Repreſenter,</hi> whether it be not the greateſt abuſe that ever was put upon mankind? This Argument therefore would bear a little more quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs than was thought convenient for the handling of the reſt: But here lies the ſting of the <hi>Repreſenter</hi>'s Charge, That <hi>Tranſubſtantiation is a Subject in which ſo many</hi> Learned <hi>and</hi> Virtuous <hi>Men of the Chriſtian World are nearly concerned:</hi> To which I anſwer, That 'tis ſo much the worſe for the <hi>Chriſtian World,</hi> but not for the Author of that Diſcourſe: For if indeed <hi>Learned</hi> Men,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:60867:11"/>and <hi>Virrtuous</hi> Men, eſpouſe ſuch a Monſtrous Doctrine as that of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> there is not leſs but great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er cauſe to <hi>exclaim</hi> both againſt them and it: If the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> thought that the <hi>Learning</hi> and <hi>Virtue</hi> of the <hi>Men</hi> ſhould have gained ſome more reverence for the <hi>Cauſe,</hi> than that Author had for it, he may think ſo ſtill for me; I will not go about to queſtion the <hi>Learning</hi> and the <hi>Virtue</hi> of <hi>many</hi> that hold <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> but 'tis <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> ſtill: I think it is no queſtion but there were <hi>many Learned and Virtuous</hi> men in <hi>Egypt</hi> who were <hi>nearly concerned</hi> in the buſineſs of making Gods of Things that grew in their Gardens, and yet he had not been too blame that ſhould have ſaid it was <hi>Impudence, Nonſence;</hi> and <hi>Monſtrous Stupidity,</hi> to Worſhip, and to teach others to Worſhip <hi>Leeks</hi> and <hi>Onyons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now for the Second Obſervation,
<note place="margin">P. 5.</note> That <hi>we have no news of any Succeſs thoſe Diſcourſes had upon the parties deſigned.</hi> I ſay, if they had indeed <hi>no Succeſs,</hi> the <hi>Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> was the honeſter man not to ſay they had <hi>any;</hi> tho he ſcaped here very well, that he was not made a <hi>Miſrepreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> for not confeſſing that they had <hi>none.</hi> But upon this occaſion the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> is very angy: <hi>It could not,</hi> ſays he, <hi>be rationally expected that thoſe who — choſe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to forgo all the intereſt and convenience of humane life, than join with a Schiſmatick Congregation, ſhould be after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards brought to Church by a few empty Diſcourſes, which making no more Converts than they deſerved, made, as I can hear of, none at all:</hi> But why <hi>Schiſmatick Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and a <hi>few empty Diſcourſes?</hi> When men keep what their Adverſaries would get from them, and when they have diſappointed all their deſigns, they uſe to be pleaſed, and in good humour; and tho perhaps they may laugh hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily at their <hi>Antagoniſts</hi> for loſing their pains, yet 'tis not ſo natural to rage againſt them, as if themſelves were the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:60867:11"/>
               <hi>Loſers:</hi> I begin therefore to ſuſpect that our <hi>Repreſenter</hi> knows of ſome <hi>Succeſs</hi> thoſe <hi>Diſcourſes</hi> had, which he is not willing to own. But be that as it will; as we did not think the better of the former Performances, for their having had ſome Succeſs, ſo neither ſhould we think the worſe of theſe if they have had none, which may perhaps be imputed to the prejudice of the perſons for whoſe good they were deſigned, rather than to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended <hi>Emptineſs</hi> of the <hi>Diſcourſes</hi> themſelves; unleſs the <hi>Repreſenter</hi>'s word may be more ſecurely relied upon for <hi>Empty Diſcourſes</hi> now, than for <hi>Empty Churches</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: We are ſorry that is proves ſo difficult a matter to recover theſe men; yet 'tis ſome Conſolation to us that we have loſt ſo very few out of ſo great a body as the Communion of the Church of <hi>England</hi> makes: And therefore if Diſcourſes are to be judged of by their Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, the <hi>Repreſenter,</hi> and ſuch as he, ſhould have a care of <hi>boaſting</hi> at this time of day. Our deſign was not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to recover thoſe that are deceived, but likewiſe to keep thoſe from Error that are in the way of Truth; and therefore it may be reaſonably preſumed, that our en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours have had good Succeſs upon the greateſt part of thoſe whom they were deſigned to ſerve, tho not up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all.</p>
            <p>But when I have told this man what perhaps himſelf knows, that by theſe Diſcourſes we have gained ſome from Popery to the Reformed Religion; I will alſo tell him, that if we had never gained ſo much as one, it had been no diſparagement to our <hi>Arguments,</hi> ſince they have ways of fixing their Proſelytes, which we abhor; of which I ſhall give this one Inſtance: It is their <hi>Rule</hi> (let otherr judg whether it be their <hi>Practice</hi>) to require a dreadful Oath of all whom they can gain, not to be prevailed withal <hi>Quocunque Argumento,</hi> by <hi>any Argument,</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:60867:12"/>to forſake the Communion of the <hi>Roman</hi> See; This Oath is to be ſeen in the <hi>Pontifical</hi> under the Title of <hi>Ordo ad Reconciliandum Apoſtatam, Hoereticum aut Schiſmaticum;</hi> and if the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> be importunate, he ſhall have it next time at length: To doubt only of any Point which the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> teaches, is a ſin that muſt come under Confeſſion, by which the Prieſt is ſure to have notice when the Spirit of Truth begins to work; and upon ſignal given, to extinguiſh the firſt Motions of it: We have a hard Task, who are not only to oppoſe Reaſons to Reaſons, and to the common prejudices of men, but to produce Reaſon againſt particular En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements and Oaths never to hearken to any Reaſon at all.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Repreſenter</hi> gives out himſelf to be a Convert, and may therefore be preſumed not to be ignorant of theſe things, but to be himſelf intangled by an Oath to be moved by no <hi>Argument whatſoever,</hi> to return to this <hi>Schiſmatick Congregation,</hi> as he calls it; and therefore in him it was great forgetfulneſs to aſcribe the Steadineſs of the Engliſh <hi>Romaniſts</hi> to nothing elſe but a <hi>Christian Reſolution,</hi> when he could not but know of ſome other Engagements that are amongſt them, which are not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether ſo <hi>Chriſtian:</hi> Which I had not obſerved here, if his Severity to the <hi>Stater</hi> had not led me to it; for it was but the very Page before, in which he ſet upon him with all his Eloquence for imputing the <hi>fulneſs</hi> of our Congregations to the Reaſonings of the Divines, without mentioning the execution of the Laws. If I had been a <hi>Repreſenter,</hi> that Page, I think, would have kept me in ſome awe, and hindred me from doing that in the very next, which he calls <hi>telling Stories by halves.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:60867:12"/>
            <p>As for the <hi>moſt cruel perſecution,</hi> which, as he ſays, thoſe of his Communion ſuffered lately, for <hi>not joyning with our Schiſmatick Congregation,</hi> he deſcribes it ſo ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribly, and aſſigns the Cauſe of it as poſitively, as if this was a <hi>matter beyond our memory,</hi> which he knows it is not. But when a Man has a mind to exerciſe his Stile, one Subject may ſerve him as well as another.</p>
            <p>But to return to the <hi>Preſent State;</hi> the Author of it either made but very ſmall faults in drawing it up, or he is very much obliged to the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> for letting the great ones paſs. His next quarrel with the <hi>Stater</hi> is, for making the <hi>Roman</hi> party the Aggreſſors;
<note place="margin">P. 6.</note> and the <hi>Papiſt Miſrepreſented,</hi> &amp;c. the beginning of this Book-War. For this Man will have the Onſet to have been given by Dr. <hi>Sherlock,</hi> in his Sermon before the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, which was publiſhed as near as I can learn, about Two Months before the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> came forth. The Author of the <hi>Agreement,</hi> &amp;c. concurs with him in this Objection, as he does in <hi>Humour</hi> to admiration, tho' they have their ſeveral ways: For one of them proves that we are <hi>Agreed</hi> with the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the other that we <hi>Miſrepreſent</hi> the ſame Church, and yet ſo like one another, as if the ſame Planet govern'd them both. But, as to the Doctor's Sermon, I do acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg that there was one paſſage in it that grated upon the <hi>Papiſts.</hi> And I have two things to ſay to it: Firſt, the <hi>Stater</hi> aſſures me that he did not think of that Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon at all, when he was at work, and could therefore have no deſign in omitting it; but withal, now that he is told of it, he cannot grant that a ſingle Reflection in a Sermon, that was afterwards Printed at the deſire of the <hi>Houſe,</hi> ought to be eſteemed the beginning or the occaſion of thoſe Controverſies. And he believes, that if we had publiſhed ſuch a like Book for this Church, as
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:60867:13"/>the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> did for his Party, and one of their Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons had been not long before publiſhed by <hi>Command,</hi> with a like Reflection upon us, they would for all that have thought us to be the Agreſſors. He ſays farther, that he ſpake only of Diſcourſes that profeſſedly treated of theſe Controverſies; and therefore that if he had thought of that Sermon, he thinks it was not his Duty to take notice of it; and he wonders that the <hi>Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenter</hi> ſhould be ſo overſet with a Cavilling humour, as not to obſerve thoſe words;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>State,</hi> p. 4.</note> that from the <hi>Death of our late Royal Sovereign,</hi> our Divines <hi>thought fit to be of the Defenſive ſide, and for ſome time publiſhed no more DIS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RSES OF THAT KIND, but waited to ſee,</hi> &amp;c. In the next place I muſt tell the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> my thoughts, and leave others to judge of them as they ſee cauſe. I ſay then, that the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> publiſhed indeed his Book about two Months after the Sermon; but, if the Truth could be known, I would venture all that little I am worth, that the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> had been hammering out that Book ſome Months before that Sermon was made. For not to inſiſt upon it, that he has taken more time to write Books that are a great deal worſe; for perhaps he was otherwiſe imployed, or gave himſelf ſome conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient Relaxation: This, I believe, all conſidering per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons will grant me, that to repreſent <hi>Popery</hi> in a kind of <hi>Proteſtant</hi> dreſs, is ſo nice, and withal ſo dangerous, tho' now, it ſeems, ſo neceſſary an undertaking, that no performance can require greater Art and Application of mind. Between the danger of <hi>giving up</hi> a point, which the Church muſt not quit under the penalty of <hi>forfeit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> her <hi>Infallibility,</hi> and the danger of <hi>guarding</hi> it too plainly to the <hi>offence</hi> of <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> the Undertaker is obliged to have his Eyes about him, and to look on eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſide. Every expreſſion muſt be exactly weighed: It
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:60867:13"/>will ſometimes happen that but one will pleaſe, which will not be thought of till many others are tried and rejected: Sometimes again, when the firſt of all is not liked, after the rejecting of many others that are found more liable to exception, the firſt muſt be taken with all its faults. So that here will be much altering, and ſome reſtoring, and not a little ſining and ſuperfining: And when one Man has done what he can, one Man's judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in a Cauſe ſo perillous is not to be truſted; It muſt be reviſed by others; and becauſe faults will come in one upon the neck of another, where every place is a place to let them in, it muſt be reviſed again and again; as the Biſhop of <hi>Condom</hi> can tell this Man, if he needs that any body ſhould tell him. Now, tho' the <hi>Papiſt Miſrepreſented and Repreſented</hi> does not riſe up to the Spirit, and the Art of the <hi>Expoſition of the Catholick Faith;</hi> yet conſidering the untractableneſs of the Matter, it was no ill wrought piece of work; and excepting that blunder of his, that when he was a <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> he belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the <hi>Sermons</hi> of the Papiſts to be in <hi>un unknown Tongue,</hi> as well as their <hi>Prayers,</hi> and two or three leſs conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able misfortunes, it was conveniently contrived for its end, which was to amuſe leſs thinking people. In a word, it appears to be a work of ſo much labour and time, that I believe few will queſtion, but tho' the Doctor's <hi>Sermon</hi> was firſt rigg'd out, yet the <hi>Papiſt Miſrepreſented and Repreſented</hi> was upon the Stocks a good while before. And then the <hi>Repreſenter</hi>'s Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſhould have forbidden him to find fault with the <hi>Stater,</hi> for intimating that the Gentlemen of the <hi>Roman</hi> Communion were firſt guilty of breaking the Peace. This I think is enough in return to a ſmall exception; but whether it be or not, the <hi>Stater</hi> is reſolved to put himſelf upon the mercy of the World for the future,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:60867:14"/>rather than he will run out into any more Apologies up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſo ſlender an occaſion.</p>
            <p>To proceed; it was ſaid in the <hi>Preſent State,</hi> that we were <hi>ſurprized</hi> to find no notice taken of the former Tracts againſt Popery, in the <hi>Repreſenter</hi>'s firſt Book. This he turns well enough,
<note place="margin">P. 7.</note> confeſſing that <hi>it muſt needs be a matter of ſurprize,</hi> That the Papiſts now enjoying the <hi>Royal Favour,</hi> ſhould after ſo many provocations, <hi>be contented to make no other return, than in a ſhort, mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and peaceable Tract, to give an account of their Faith and Doctrine,</hi> &amp;c. And ſo he takes occaſion to praiſe their <hi>Meekneſs and Charity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To all which it might be enough to ſay, that ſo long as it does no body any hurt, other men may be ſafely allowed to commend themſelves; and let them conſider whether it will do them any good: But that if it were not more difficult to Anſwer ſome Books, than to give a Reaſon for not Anſwering them, in all likelyhood we had heard the Victories of theſe Writers more celebrated at this time, than their <hi>Meekneſs and Charity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But whereas he magnifies the Good Spirit of his <hi>ſhort, moderate and peaceable Tract,</hi> upon this ſcore, That there was no <hi>upraiding the Church of</hi> England <hi>Divines</hi> in it, notwithſtanding <hi>Abuſive Reflections,</hi> &amp;c. he does in effect confeſs of the firſt,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>View.</hi> p. 65.</note> what was proved of all his Books but the firſt, That the Church of <hi>England</hi> Divines were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended in them, as we were very ſure that they were. He has for ſome time loſt that warineſs, which ſuch a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenter</hi> as he ſets up for, ſhould be always provided with. Well; but however the Tract was <hi>moderate</hi> and <hi>peaceable, without any ſevere Word or Expreſſion in it, or any upbraiding of the Church of</hi> England <hi>Divines of the miſchiefs they ſuffered from their hands.</hi> Now indeed, the Tract does not call them Knaves and Villains, but
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:60867:14"/>only inſinuates from one end to the other, that they had abuſed the people, and made them believe that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> owns thoſe things which ſhe utterly diſowns. Which how <hi>Moderate</hi> and <hi>Peaceable</hi> a Charge it was, I might almoſt appeal to himſelf, or to the <hi>Agreement</hi>-maker, when I have put him in mind, that what he at firſt called <hi>Miſrepreſentation,</hi> after his anger had made him ſpeak out, he bluntly calls <hi>Lying</hi> and <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumny,</hi> and what not? Now this I acknowledg to be a <hi>ſhort,</hi> but ſure it is no <hi>moderate</hi> and <hi>peaceable</hi> way of managing Controverſies: And this was ſome reaſon for wiſe men to be a little ſuprized at it. But this was not all: For there was no colour (whatever the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenter</hi> pretends) for neglecting thoſe Tracts againſt Popery, and beginning a new Repreſentation of it. For they proceeded upon the old and received Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Popery, and ſuch as had been allowed by <hi>Bellarmin, Becanus, Harding, Stapleton,</hi> and all the renowned Champions of the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Church for an Age and half before us; whom this Man does by neceſſary conſequence Arraign of Miſrepreſenting Popery, whilſt he accuſes our Divines of doing ſo; altho their Diſcourſes went upon that ſtate of the Fact which was agreed to by thoſe old Diſputers.</p>
            <p>Had theſe Books been written in their days, we ſhould have had no <hi>Repreſentations</hi> in return to 'em, but down-right diſputing upon the ſeveral points as they are ſtated there. For to give them their due, when our Divines came up to their own ſide of the Queſtion, thoſe Gentlemen came up to theirs, and maintain'd it as well as it could be maintain'd. But our Friend the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> has taken another way, which is in <hi>peaceable</hi> and <hi>moderate</hi> terms to give us the Lye, for calling that <hi>Popery,</hi> which we diſpute <hi>againſt,</hi> and which they diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted <hi>for.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:60867:15"/>
            <p>Having thus commended <hi>Himſelf</hi> and <hi>His,</hi> for their Meekneſs and Charity, it came preſently in his mind to ſay ſomething in praiſe of his Book, tho' it did not <hi>mention thoſe Diſcourſes:</hi>
               <note place="margin">P. 7.</note> Which he ſays could be no <hi>ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize,</hi> but <hi>only to ſome half-witted men, who read things without underſtanding, and to whom plain ſenſe is a Riddle,</hi> and not to <hi>any others, tho' but of moderate parts.</hi> And thus in pure kindneſs to his Book, he does in the firſt place take the ſize of our <hi>underſtandings</hi> by it; and from this time forward, whoever ſhall queſtion the pertinence of his Book, muſt go for a <hi>half-witted man,</hi> and one that has not ſo much as <hi>moderate parts.</hi> So that our buſineſs is preſently done; and then the <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes</hi> are brought to the Teſt of the Book, as you ſhall hear. <hi>There was,</hi> ſays he, <hi>ſcarce any controverſial Point, or Matter of moment in them, but what was ſpoke to, and opened in this one little Tract:</hi> And they muſt needs be in an evil condition, if there is <hi>ſcarce any Point</hi> of theirs but what was <hi>ſpoken to, and opened</hi> in ſo dangerous a Piece as that <hi>one little Tract.</hi> But it were well for 'em to ſcape ſo, if they might; For by and by the <hi>Stater</hi> is told, that <hi>if he will compare theſe Diſcourſes with the Chapters of that Treatiſe, he may find them All there ſpoke to as to the ſubſtance, and ſomething to ſpare.</hi> Now, if after <hi>ſcarce any point was omitted,</hi> the truth is, that <hi>All</hi> the Diſcourſes were ſpoken to, and <hi>ſomething to ſpare;</hi> then it is like to go <hi>very hard</hi> with 'em. All the comfort is, That the <hi>Diſcourſes</hi> and the <hi>Points</hi> are as yet ſaid to be but ſpoke to; For there are divers ways of <hi>ſpeaking to</hi> things,
<note place="margin">P. 8.</note> and ſome of 'em harmleſs enough. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore now comes the killing ſtroke: <hi>The true Reaſon of the ſurprize was, that in ſo little room, and ſo plain a method, there was enough to ANSWER thoſe Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes.</hi> Nay, he affirms, that <hi>there was a Noiſe about
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:60867:15"/>it throughout the Nation, not for Anſwering too little, but for Anſwering too much.</hi> So that the <hi>Diſcourſes</hi> are gone beyond redemption, for there was <hi>enough</hi> to <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer</hi> them; and if that would not do, they were <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered too much:</hi> And which is more wonderful, there <hi>was enough to Anſwer<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> not only thoſe Diſcourſes, but a great part of the Books and Sermons that had ever been Writ or Preached againſt Cath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>licks;</hi> to which if he had but added, <hi>or that ever ſhall be Written or Preached againſt Catholicks;</hi> he had made an end of his work once for all, and his <hi>one little Tract</hi> had made a pretty Triumph over Ages paſt, preſent, and to come.</p>
            <p>Were I ſo happy as to grow upon an Adverſary in the way of Reaſoning, as this Man does in boaſting and preſſing forward with new and greater confidence; I ſhould not yet take my ſelf to be a match for him: For I now perceive that he carries ſuch Invincible Force in his <hi>Face,</hi> that no modeſt man, tho' fortified with the Conſcience of Honeſty, and the Advantage of a Good-Cauſe, can always bear up againſt it, but muſt at length let his Countenance fall, and turn away from him.</p>
            <p>As to every Article of this ſo much magnified <hi>Tract,</hi> he has been twice diſtinctly Anſwer'd, and the World has ſeen that he neither replied to the particulars of the firſt, nor of the ſecond Anſwer, but that at length he fairly dropt the defence of his Charge upon every one of the Thirty ſeven Points he began with, as the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the <hi>View</hi> has ſhewn beyond contradiction. But what cares the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> for all this? Still he goes on proclaiming what Execution his <hi>Tract</hi> has done upon us: <hi>There,</hi> ſays he, <hi>are laid open all the Little Tricks and Artifices,</hi> &amp;c.
<note place="margin">P. 84.</note> 
               <hi>There 'twas ſeen how often abuſes in pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice were condemned as the Faith of the Church,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Here the ſurpriſe firſt began,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>It began now to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:60867:16"/>that the Papiſts were not what they had been render'd,</hi> &amp;c. Suppoſe now, that another <hi>View of the whole Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy</hi> were taken, and it were diſcover'd yet more particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, if that were poſſible, that there were no ſuch ſights <hi>to be ſeen</hi> in his Book as he proclaims; ſtill it would hold good, that <hi>Tricks are laid open there,</hi> that <hi>there it may be ſeen how Principles are miſtaken, Doctrines confounded, and Imaginary Monſters knocked down,</hi> and that that is the Book which can <hi>Inform people of the Truth, and diſcover to them all the Pulpit-deluſions.</hi> For by what I can ſee, he intends to talk on at this rate as long as he lives, if any Man does but give him occaſion; and for his part, he deſires no better occaſion, than to have it ſhewn him that there is not the leaſt ground for all this boaſting. We have a comfortable imployment, to be engaged with ſuch a Writer as this; for if you <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute</hi> his Charge and his Arguments, he falls a commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf and his Book as faſt as he can; and if you make it plain that you <hi>have confuted</hi> him, and that he has nothing to reply, he takes occaſion to write another Book, and to commend himſelf the faſter for it; and to rant as much or more than he did at firſt.</p>
            <p>Which makes me almoſt wiſh that the <hi>Defender</hi> had not promiſed an account of theſe Reflections. For the Man's Confidence will ſerve him ſeven years hence, as well as it does now, and I doubt, ſomething better; for his Force encreaſes, as that of <hi>Anteus</hi> did, with his Falls. 'Tis impoſſible that ever he ſhould want Matter, for he can repeat the very ſame to the Worlds end, if he lives ſo long; and tho' it has been conſidered by his Anſwerers never ſo particularly, 'tis all one for that, he is grown paſt taking any notice of ſuch things. For a little variety, he has no more to do but to ſtudy ſome ridiculing <hi>Harangue,</hi> and to gather Flowers
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:60867:16"/>from <hi>Bartholomew-Fair,</hi> the <hi>Pall-mall,</hi> the Gaming Houſes,
<note place="margin">P. 1, 8, 17, 19.</note> the <hi>Hind</hi> and <hi>Panther,</hi> and ſuch like, for the adorning of his Characters, and ſo he is compleatly furniſhed for a new Book: To which we can have no more to ſay, than to that which we had juſt before it, unleſs it be to admire the man's Confidence, which we have admired ſo much already, that when we are a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle more uſed to it, we ſhall not admire it at all.</p>
            <p>That he has hitherto behaved himſelf in this manner, is what himſelf and all the world knows, that has taken notice of this Controverſy; or at leaſt he has been very careful that they ſhould know it now, if they could be ignorant of it before: The Author of the <hi>View</hi> had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced the whole Diſpute from the beginning, and it was made exceedingly plain, that this man had dropt the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence not only of every Point he began with, but of thoſe very pretences upon which he did ſo; and the worſt of all was, that the ſame Author had made him, as it now appears, ſick of his laſt Reply too, where he had diverted himſelf with ſo many things that were nothing to his firſt buſineſs: This now was a very great ſtreight, and there was no other way to be taken, but either in <hi>Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> to ſit ſtill, and ſo let the world forget what was paſt; or with exceeding <hi>Modeſty</hi> to confeſs that a man may be miſtaken, and ſo forth; or with the exceſs of the <hi>contrary</hi> quality, to do as the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> has now done: For now he has taken up a pretence which he <hi>dropt</hi> the Defence of, but in his Second Reply, <hi>viz.</hi>
               <note place="margin">See <hi>View,</hi> p. 24.</note> That his Anſwerer did ſometimes appeal to private Authors, and ſo all that he has ſaid ought to go for nothing. <hi>An Anſwer,</hi> ſays he, <hi>is ſet forth to amuſe the World, as the faſhion is,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Preſ. p. 9.</note> 
               <hi>with the banding and toſſing to and fro of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny School-Queſtions, but never coming to the point of diſpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Character of a</hi> Papiſt Repreſented, <hi>or endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:60867:17"/>to ſhew that the Faith as there ſtated, was not really the Faith of Catholicks; nay, this was ſcarce ſo much as offer'd at, except in Two or three Points, which yet ought to have been the main deſign of the Anſwerer, and the only way of giving it a juſt Reply.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus he preſſes upon us with mere confidence; in which tho poſſibly he might feel no checks from his own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, yet 'tis ſomething ſtrange that he ſhould not fear his Readers Knowledg; for that Author had ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently <hi>diſproved the Character of a Papiſt Repreſented,</hi> if to ſhew from Point to Point that it was no ſincere Character, be to <hi>diſprove</hi> it. He made it plain, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt every where too much was put in, or too little, as might beſt ſerve the deſign of ſetting the <hi>Papiſt</hi> out fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the people: The <hi>Repreſenter</hi> ſhould have ſhewn, that the Anſwer came ſhort of that Account which the <hi>View</hi> gave of it, <hi>That every Queſtion was particularly and exactly ſtated;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>View</hi> p. 3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>That the Senſe of the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>about it was ſhewn by the Decrees of their</hi> Trent <hi>Council, or their</hi> Roman <hi>Catechiſm, or their publick Offices, and their moſt approved Divines and Caſuiſts, as the matter required. — And by the way, all the falſe Colours of the Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenter were taken off, where he thought it for his purpoſe to lay them on too Foul on his Miſrepreſenting, or too Fair on his Repreſenting ſide.</hi> If this was done as it was ſaid, and ſo done, that the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> has long ſince dropt his Two or three Exceptions againſt it, and never from the firſt ventured upon a particular Reply to it, ſurely he has been rubbing hard ever ſince, to come forth now, and think to put us off with ſaying that the Anſwer <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver came up to the Point,</hi> &amp;c. Indeed he brings over Two or three Particulars again in this Preface, which he Repreſented upon in his firſt Book: But is it to compare his own Characters with his Adverſaries Anſwer, and to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:60867:17"/>ſhew that he had not come to the Point? No ſuch mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, I aſſure ye; but only to let us know, That when they repreſent themſeves right, we call it <hi>New Popery,</hi> which he would make the world believe is all that we now have to ſave our ſelves from being accounted <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumniators;</hi> which he purſues with ſuch noiſe in ſaying the ſame thing over and over again, that if Repetition of little Matter, and more Words, were an Argument of Truth, he would be the moſt convincing Writer that ever ſet up for the Cauſe.</p>
            <p>For, ſetting aſide the Prophets that cried from Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Noon, <hi>O Baal, hear us;</hi> I think no man has out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> in this kind of Eloquence, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly when it came into his head to be revenged on the <hi>Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pits,</hi> thoſe <hi>High-places</hi> the <hi>Pulpits,</hi> for all the miſchief they have done to Popery, and to inveigh againſt that unlucky diſtinction between <hi>Old</hi> and <hi>New</hi> Popery.</p>
            <p>He tells us,
<note place="margin">P. 8.</note> That <hi>ſeveral things were heard from the Pulpits</hi> which were <hi>found not to ſquare with Truth;</hi> and that <hi>from thoſe High-places,</hi> the <hi>innocent Hind</hi> had been <hi>made to look like Tygers, Wolves, and Bears.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>All is true Repreſenting when Popery is to be ſhown from the Pulpits.</hi>
               <note place="margin">P. 12.</note>—<hi>In this manner did Proteſtants treat Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts; in this manner are they now handled by Protestants, and yet all muſt paſs for true Repreſenting: And becauſe the Cath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>licks will not own that to be their Faith and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, as it ſtands thus ſtretched and racked upon Proteſtant Tenters and Hyperbolies, the cry is now forſooth, they are aſhamed of their Old Religion, and have brought in a New Popery. A poor ſhift, God knows! No, we are not aſhamed of our Old Religion.—To us the Old and the New is all the ſame,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:60867:18"/>
            <p>
               <hi>But this Cant of New-Popery must be kept up to ſave the credit of the Pulpits.</hi>
               <note place="margin">P. 13.</note>—And <hi>were it not for this little come-off, this poor ſhift of</hi> New-Popery, <hi>they would be eternally blemiſht with the fouleſt of Imputations, that of Miſrepreſenting, of Calumniating, of inventing ſcandals againſt their neighbour. 'Tis evident now to thoſe that look upon Popery as it appears amongſt us at this day, with an unprejudiced eye, that it has quite another Face, other Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, other Features, than they have painted her with for ſo many years from the P<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LPITS: All that they have heard of from theſe HIGH PLACES, has been full of Dread and Horror, Cruelty in her Looks, Malice and Wickedneſs in her Heart, Blood-thirſting in her Deſires,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>If it be poſſible, he will make the Pulpits hear of all theſe things again; and therefore he goes on, <hi>Where are all theſe Abominations, theſe marks of the Beaſt? SHEW <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S, P<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LPITS, SHEW <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s: Where is her Cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, her Bloodineſs, her Tyranny, her Arbitrary Power? — How many Throats hath ſhe cut? Where has ſhe wrong'd her neighbours? Where is</hi> This, and <hi>Where is</hi> That, and <hi>Where are</hi> all theſe Things? <hi>SHEW <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if none of theſe things can be ſhewn,
<note place="margin">P. 14.</note> then <hi>the P<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LPITS muſt paſs for Falſe Prophets, Miſrepreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and diſturbers of the Nation: And what Return now do the P<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LPITS make to this demand? Oh! This is a New ſort of Popery. — The Papiſts are weary of their OLD Religion, and have taken up a NEW one.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now this is admirable, if the man had but known when he was well; but he has not done yet by a great deal; for having obſerved that the Papiſts are found by experience to be very good men, the Pulpits are ſure to hear of it again:
<note place="margin">P. 15.</note> 
               <hi>How,</hi> ſays he, <hi>ſhall the Characters of the P<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LPITS be reconciled with this Experience?
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:60867:18"/>Oh! The Papiſts diſſemble their Principles, and are aſhamed of their OLD Religion;</hi> and this <hi>forſooth acquits the P<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LPITS.—And the ſame poor ſhift is to ſerve them upon all occaſions;</hi> or elſe what would become of the Pulpits? If <hi>the Papists</hi> do this good thing, <hi>this is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently ſet out for NEW Popery.</hi> The Papiſts <hi>declare</hi> this Doctrine. <hi>This again is NEW Popery.</hi> The <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts teach</hi> that Doctrine, and the other Doctrine. <hi>This is all NEW Popery.</hi>
               <note place="margin">P. 16.</note> — And <hi>it evidently appearing to the world, That Catholicks neither believe nor do as was repreſented by the P<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LPITS, the only remedy for the keeping their Credit whole, is to cry out, This is not the OLD Religion, This is a NEW Popery.</hi> And indeed it muſt needs be a <hi>NEW Popery</hi> to thoſe that <hi>knew no more</hi> of Popery, than the <hi>P<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LPITS</hi> ſhewed them. —For <hi>they who never heard more of Popery,</hi> than <hi>P<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LPIT Characters,</hi> muſt needs think the preſent Popery a <hi>NEW</hi> Popery. — And <hi>who ſhall ever make them believe that this is that OLD P<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LPIT POPERY, thoſe OLD P<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LPIT PAPISTS, which they have ſo often ſeen painted out in their Sunday Lectures.—For the Church of</hi> England <hi>in her P<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>L<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PITS, made Popery and the Papiſts ſo unlike what they now appear, that Popery muſt be cut into an OLD and a NEW Popery to ſave their Reputation; i. e.</hi> The Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the Pulpits.</p>
            <p>And thus he runs on for five or ſix pages together,
<note place="margin">P. 17. P. 14. P. 18.</note> crying out, <hi>P<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LPITS! P<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LPITS! OLD PO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PERY! NEW POPERY! Pulpit</hi> Popery! <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant-Rack</hi>-Popery! <hi>Sons of Anak</hi>-Popery! <hi>Wry-neck'd, Hunch-back'd, Swag-bellied, Broken-legg'd, and Splay-footed Popery!</hi> which is the ſimilitude he took from the <hi>Poſture-Maſter</hi> in the <hi>Pall-mall,</hi> as he did the former out of the Scripture.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:60867:19"/>
            <p>Certainly, if one of us had anſwered him in this manner, and he had got a Companion, it had been the moſt entertaining ſort of Controverſie that ever was written;
<note place="margin">P. 9.</note> and the world will never care for the <hi>banding and toſſing to and fro of School-Queſtions</hi> any more, after the benefit of <hi>toſſing</hi> a few Exclamations to and fro, as he can do it, ſhall be well underſtood.</p>
            <p>Now one would be glad to know what the meaning of all this is; and I think 'tis this; he had obſerved, that <hi>after all the vain attempts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">P. 9.</note> 
               <hi>his first Book remaining in its full force, now at last a new one was invented,</hi> viz. <hi>That the Belief of Catholicks as there deciphred, is a New Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery.</hi> And he thought that this new force which we had raiſed againſt him and his Book, was ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible, that he had nothing to do, but to ſhout it out of the Field. The truth is, after he had per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded himſelf that <hi>all the Attempts upon his Book were vain,</hi> he might eaſily believe any thing to his own advantage; and if what he ſaid of his Book, that it <hi>remained in full force,</hi> had been ſaid of <hi>himſelf,</hi> no body would have wondred at him. I have already diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered ſome fear that all is not well in his head; but if it be ſo, his diſorder inclines the right way, and to make him happy; for if a man has a ſtrong fancy that he has won Battels, and conceits himſelf a very Emperor, and another <hi>Julius Caeſar,</hi> or perhaps <hi>Caeſar</hi> himſelf, it may be, as ſome ſay, an unkind part to bring him to his true underſtanding.</p>
            <p>But if the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> ſhould merely affect this way of writing, and be ſenſible all the while how the matter ſtands; I pity him with all my heart, and ſo much the more, leſt any of thoſe that have not read what was written againſt his Firſt Book, ſhould believe that it <hi>stands in its full force,</hi> becauſe
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:60867:19"/>he ſays ſo; for there are men in the world that believe implicitely, and this Gentleman muſt reckon for thoſe that believe him ſo, as well as they for themſelves. If his Livelihood comes in by writing Controverſies, he ſhould conſider that there are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny honeſt ways of getting a Livelihood, and no ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of taking this. I will here take occaſion to ſay a good word of my ſelf, and that is, that rather than <hi>prevaricate</hi> in things of this nature, I would make ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry hard ſhifts: If it were too late to apply my ſelf to Handicraft Trades, yet may be I could <hi>dig,</hi> or the like; but if I could not dig, I would not be aſhamed to <hi>beg:</hi> Perhaps I might get ſomething by turning my Pen another way, and writing of things where I had more liberty, as by writing <hi>Almanacks</hi> or any ſuch thing, where Miſtakes will be committed in abundance, and are forgiven in courſe, and will be ſure to do no body any hurt: But to impoſe upon men in Books that treat of Divinity, is one of the laſt diſhoneſt things I would take to; I ſhould think of that, and of ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a convenient ſtand near the Town, much about the ſame time; and the reaſon why he that does the one, does not the other, is becauſe all mens Abilities do not lye the ſame way.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Repreſenter,</hi> I imagine, will ſubſcribe to theſe Notions, and perhaps bid me apply them effectually to my ſelf; which if he does, I will heartilty thank him for it, and promiſe to take all the good Counſel he ſhall give me, as well as I can, and to follow good Examples where they are to be had.</p>
            <p>In theſe <hi>Reflections</hi> of his, a man muſt have very good luck that meets with any thing that is worth anſwering; but if he cannot find what he would, he muſt learn patience, and be content with what he can get.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:60867:20"/>
            <p n="1">I. He would make us believe, That the <hi>only way of giving</hi> his firſt <hi>Book a just Reply,</hi>
               <note place="margin">P. 9.</note> was to have <hi>ſhewn that the Faith as there stated, was not really the Faith of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks.</hi> Now this indeed might have been the <hi>Only way,</hi> according as the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> might have drawn his Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters; but as he has ordered the matter, 'tis not the <hi>only way,</hi> for he has for the moſt part <hi>told stories hy halves</hi> in the Character of a Papiſt <hi>Repreſented;</hi> and ſurely one Miſrepreſenting Trick is diſcovered on his ſide, if it be ſhewn that the Faith of a <hi>Papiſt</hi> as ſtated under this or that Article,
<note place="margin">P. 15.</note> is not <hi>all</hi> his Faith, but that it ſeems there was ſomething concealed which was too bad to be ſhewn. For inſtance, The <hi>Repreſenter</hi> takes occaſion to bring in this Character of a Papiſt under the head of <hi>Indulgences.</hi> The <hi>Papiſts teach, That neither the Pope nor any other Power upon Earth can give leave to ſin for a ſum of money.</hi> Nay, in his firſt Book, the Papiſt believes it <hi>damnable to hold that any Power in Heaven or Earth can do it.</hi> Now we will ſuppoſe this to be the <hi>Faith</hi> of a Papiſt. But then to repreſent him as he is, he ſhould have added thus much at leaſt; <q>That he does <hi>not</hi> believe it <hi>damnable</hi> to hold that an <hi>Indulgence or Pardon</hi> of <hi>ſins</hi> can be obtained for a Sum of Money after they are committed, nor that the <hi>Tax</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtolick</hi> Chamber, which ſets the pardons of the moſt horrid ſins at very reaſonable rates, is a <hi>Damnable</hi> Scandal, nor that they who truſt in the Popes Bulls for <hi>plenary remiſſion of ſins,</hi> are <hi>damnably</hi> deceived:</q> Now all this is concealed; and yet I doubt it will be found to belong to the Character of a Papiſt, with reſpect to the matter of <hi>Indulgences</hi> and <hi>Pardons;</hi> and in all like caſes to ſhew what the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed, is a <hi>Juſt Reply</hi> to his <hi>Characters;</hi> but whether it be a juſt Reply to <hi>Him,</hi> is a point wherein he is more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned than we need to be.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:60867:20"/>
            <p n="2">II. He ſeems to lay great weight upon this, That <hi>to this pitch of Confidence if not more, are ſome Church of</hi> England <hi>Divines arrived, that they pretend to know what the Religion of Papiſts is, better than they.— Is, it likely,</hi> ſays he, <hi>the Jews can tell better what Chriſt teaches, than Chriſt himſelf or his Apoſtles? — Can Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants tell better what Catholicks believe, than Catholicks themſelvrs? If the Character of a thing is beſt received from profeſſed, intereſted and bitter Enemies, then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed they may put in for the beſt Informers of our Faith.</hi> Much more he ſays to this purpoſe, juſt as he cried out <hi>Pulpits</hi> and <hi>Popery,</hi> without adding any thing of new matter. Now, where no Anſwers are needful, I am ſure theſe that follow may ſuffice.</p>
            <p n="1">1. 'Tis falſe, that I (for inſtance) <hi>preten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to know what the Religion of Papiſts is, better than</hi> he, the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenter:</hi> But for all that, 'tis true, that unleſs he mends his Characters of a <hi>Papist Repreſented,</hi> I do pretend to repreſent Popery with more <hi>honesty</hi> than he does. I <hi>cannot tell what</hi> this Man <hi>believes, better than</hi> he <hi>does</hi> himſelf, nor ſo well neither; but I can tell as well as he, what their <hi>Trent</hi> Council, their <hi>Catechiſms,</hi> their <hi>Pontifical,</hi> their <hi>Miſſal,</hi> their <hi>Breviary,</hi> and their eſtabliſhed <hi>Offices</hi> ſay. Are theſe Myſteries that no Man muſt pretend to underſtand but a <hi>Repreſenter,</hi> and ſome few beſides? For,</p>
            <p n="2">2. Why muſt we be brought in as pretending to know what <hi>Popery</hi> is; <hi>better</hi> than <hi>Papists</hi> know it? Was <hi>Bellarmin</hi> (with all thoſe of the old ſtrain) a Proteſtant? Is Father <hi>Craſſet</hi> a Proteſtant? or Cardinal <hi>Capiſucchi,</hi> who approved the Biſhop of <hi>Condom</hi>'s Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition too? Are they Proteſtants in <hi>Spain</hi> or <hi>Italy?</hi> Do we repreſent their <hi>Worſhip</hi> of <hi>Images</hi> ſo groſly as that very Cardinal does? Do we repreſent Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:60867:21"/>otherwiſe than as all theſe have and do profeſs and practiſe?</p>
            <p n="3">3. It had been an Impudent thing in the <hi>Jews,</hi> to pretend that they could tell <hi>better</hi> what <hi>Chriſt</hi> taught, than <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf or his <hi>Apoſtles.</hi> And it was ſilly in the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> to run to ſo high an inſtance, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs he would inſinuate that we are as it were <hi>Jews,</hi> and himſelf a kind of an <hi>Apoſtle.</hi> I would have him obſerve, that we are not ſo ſenſleſs, as to think that we can tell what a <hi>Repreſenter</hi> and an <hi>Expoſitor</hi> teach, better than themſelves; but in many things we can tell as well as they; by the ſame token that they teach ſome things for <hi>Catholick</hi> Doctrines, which in their Church have been accounted little better than <hi>Hereſies;</hi> and ſuppreſs others, which their predeceſſors ſcorned to ſuppreſs. But tho' ſome <hi>Romaniſts</hi> do now think fit to palliate their Religion in this manner; yet <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles</hi> did no ſuch thing, and were not therefore liable to that Reproof which theſe men muſt bear in ſpite of their hearts.</p>
            <p n="4">4. For what he ſays, That <hi>Bitter Enemies</hi> are not to be <hi>believed</hi> in the <hi>Characters</hi> they give of others; I Anſwer, That neither are deſigning and ſelf-intereſted men to be believed in the <hi>Characters</hi> they give of themſelves. <hi>Animoſity,</hi> ſays he, <hi>ſets</hi> a Biaſs <hi>upon the Heart.</hi> And is there nothing that does it beſide? What thinks he of the Deſign, to reconcile a Nation ſo averſe to Popery as this is? and of the ſeveral con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniencies that will follow ſuch a Change? Nor is it ſo certain that we are their <hi>Bitter Enemies,</hi> as that they are very great <hi>Lovers of themſelves.</hi> I am ſo far from being a <hi>Bitter Enemy</hi> to the <hi>Repreſenter,</hi> that I am now doing him the Office of a <hi>ſevere Friend,</hi> by telling him the Truth, which he cares not to hear; but, it
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:60867:21"/>may be, I may bring him to bluſhing, which he ſeems to have taken his leave of; and he may in time thank me for it. I tell him, that in this place he talks wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly, and I deſire him to <hi>reflect</hi> upon himſelf, before he pretends to make any more <hi>Reflections</hi> upon us. <hi>Don't every body know,</hi> ſays he, <hi>that the Church of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land <hi>has proclaim'd her ſelf an</hi> open <hi>and</hi> profeſſed Enemy <hi>to the Church of</hi> Rome? <hi>Does not this unqualify her for a True Repreſenter?</hi> Now admitting our Church to be as <hi>open</hi> and <hi>profeſſed</hi> an Enemy to his, as ſhe is to the Errors and Abuſes of it; yet <hi>who does not know</hi> that this can only <hi>unqualify</hi> her for a <hi>Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenter,</hi> to <hi>be believed upon her own word?</hi> But ſhe may Repreſent <hi>truly</hi> for all that: Which is ſo plain a Caſe, that this Man, if he was in his right mind when he wrote thoſe things, <hi>could not but know it.</hi> The moſt therefore that he could honeſtly make of this ſuppoſed enmity of our Church againſt his, is, that we are not to be truſted with an <hi>implicit Faith;</hi> which we deſire not to be; but rather to be believed in theſe matters ſo far as we prove what we ſay, and no farther: And if he be truſted no farther, we deſire no more.</p>
            <p n="3">III. <hi>We offer,</hi> ſays he, <hi>and are ready to accept any into our Communion, that will but embrace and receive the Doctrine as it there ſtands</hi> [in his firſt Book] <hi>under thoſe very colours, and that ſhape; owning, not only the ſubſtance of it, but even that appearance,</hi> &amp;c. Now this he hath offered twice or thrice before, and his offer has been as often anſwered, but he will not take the leaſt notice of it. He thought at firſt no doubt, that here he had nicked the buſineſs; but tho he has had ſome reaſon to fall in his opinion of the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:60867:22"/>Propoſal, yet he comes over with it, as if this too <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained in its full force.</hi> I will try, however, if it be poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, to oblige him to reflect upon what we have to ſay in this matter.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Then this <hi>offer</hi> ought to be eſteemed no otherwiſe than a Ludicrous one, made without good Faith, and with no other meaning than to put ſome colour upon his own deceitful <hi>Characters</hi> of a <hi>Papiſt;</hi> becauſe he has been told, and indeed could not be ignorant of it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that we cannot ſwallow Popery even as he has ſmooth'd and gilded it for us. He has in the firſt An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to his Book, <hi>our Reaſons againſt Popery, as by him Repreſented;</hi> which he did not, and I imagine durſt not reply to. And ſo long as our Reaſons are good againſt that which he <hi>confeſſes</hi> to be Popery, he offers a vain tryal of his ſincerity about that which he <hi>denies</hi> to be ſo; becauſe he knows, that as the Caſe ſtands, 'tis impoſſible for us, if we will keep a good Conſcience, to accept the offer. And therefore this beloved offer of his, which he intended for a <hi>Varniſh</hi> to ſet off his Characters, will to all men that can uſe their Eyes, give a juſt occaſion to ſuſpect they are <hi>falſe;</hi> and that the ſincerity he has uſed in his <hi>Repreſentation,</hi> is of one piece with that which he has ſhewn in his <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which I may add, That if we are very ſure that his Characters are <hi>Deceitful,</hi> if we ſee that himſelf de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clines the defence of them, and that no importunity will provoke him to undertake the vindication of them, and that he writes time after time to excuſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf from it; we cannot have juſt cauſe to believe that he is not <hi>deceitful</hi> in the offer he makes upon ſuch Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:60867:22"/>
            <p n="2">2. Suppoſe that we could accept, and ſhould be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted here upon the Terms he propounds, yet we have no ſecurity that when we are in, this Repreſenter either can, or will if he could, ſave us from being preſſed to profeſs and practiſe that Popery which he either denies or conceals. On the one hand we are very certain that the prevailing part of his Church holds that, which he either rejects from his Faith, or ſays no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of; and (if we underſtand any thing) that they declare agreeably to their Councils and Publick Offices. On the other hand, we have no reaſon at all to believe his Authority in the <hi>Roman</hi> Church to be conſiderable enough to carry on his Repreſentation when the turn is once ſerv'd; or to ſecure us from being ſerved in due time, as Monſieur <hi>Imbert</hi> has been, who was baſely left in the lurch by the Biſhop of <hi>Meaux,</hi> after he had declar'd for worſhiping not the <hi>Wood,</hi> but Chriſt, not the <hi>Croſs,</hi> but him that ſuffered on it. Where the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition</hi> is ſet up, could this Man, that talks as if he were ſomebody, govern the proceedings by his Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters? If he thinks that he could, that's a new Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to ſuſpect that his Wits are ſet aſide by ſelf-conceit: If that he could not, what Conſcience could it be in him, to try if he could draw us into Snares? and by his <hi>New</hi> Popery wheedle us into a ſubjection to the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> See, and ſo into a neceſſity of being uſed as the Phyſician at <hi>Goa</hi> was,
<note place="margin">Relation de l'Inquiſition de <hi>Goa,</hi> chap. xxvii.</note> who ſuffered under the Inquiſition for two things, whereof one was, no more than his declaring, as his Accuſers ſaid, that an Ivory Crucifix was a piece of Ivory, which, I ſhould think, may as ſafely be ſaid according to the Rules of <hi>New</hi> Popery, as what the Repreſenter offers might be done, <hi>viz.</hi> to burn an Image or a Crucifix if that will ſatisfy us that he has no Superſtition in theſe
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:60867:23"/>things. For, as I remember, he talks at that rate.</p>
            <p>But then again, if the Repreſenter were a Man of that Figure in his Church as to be able to ſave us in a time of Exigence, we have not yet any good reaſon to truſt him that he would be willing to do ſo, for he has not given us reaſonable aſſurance that himſelf rejects that <hi>Popery,</hi> which he knows we call ſo. I ſhall therefore take the ſame liberty with him, that he has done with us, and put him upon a Teſt, which I think he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not honeſtly refuſe. He has taxed his Anſwerer with charging the Determinations of <hi>Schoolmen,</hi> and the Sentiments of <hi>private Authors,</hi> and ſome Paſſages in <hi>Old Miſſals</hi> and <hi>Rituals,</hi> upon the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as if her Doctrine were to be concluded from thence. I will not here repeat what has been ſaid in anſwer to it. But this, I ſay, will the Repreſenter be content to go through his <hi>Thirty ſeven</hi> Points as they are conſidered by his firſt Anſwerer, and make his Mark upon every thing which he rejects, and which he ſays we falſly charge upon the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and declare before the World upon his honeſt Word, what it is that he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves to be impious there, and ought not to be faſtened upon his Church? This perhaps would be ſomething, and we who are not a little diſpoſed to hope well of other Men, might then conceive our ſelves obliged to think that he means honeſtly. He has more than once or twice offered, that his Church ſhall receive us upon his Terms, and he has been anſwered. But, as I do remember, he has been asked whether he would refuſe us if we deſired to come into the <hi>Roman</hi> Communion, with that which we call <hi>Old Popery.</hi> But I do not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that he has anſwered to that. And yet I will aſſure him this was a very material Queſtion; and which I will make him take notice of here if I can.
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:60867:23"/>Will the Repreſenter take us by the hand and preſent us to his Church, if we ſhould come with the <hi>Lateran</hi> Popery about depoſing Sovereigns for Hereſy, and with the <hi>Trent</hi> Popery about the Worſhip of Images, as it is underſtood by <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> or rather by <hi>Capiſucchi,</hi> and as it is practiſed by the <hi>Tartuffs</hi> of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, and with all that old Popery which the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerer gives an account of? If he will not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take for us upon theſe Terms, let him do two things which may fairly be demanded:</p>
            <p n="1">1. Let him go through the 37 Heads, as I ſaid before, and tell us particularly what the Anſwerer charges upon Papiſts, which we do well in rejecting, but ill in imputing it to them. And,</p>
            <p n="2">2. Let him ſay plainly to every particular where he thinks there is juſt occaſion to ſay ſo, The Church of <hi>Rome</hi> will not receive you if you come with this Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, or with this Practice, which yet you preſume to call Popery.</p>
            <p>But if the Repreſenter will undertake for us upon theſe Terms, even of <hi>Popery</hi> as 'tis repreſented by that Author; then I muſt beg of him to tell us what he meant by ſuch Expreſſions as theſe. <hi>If you have truly repreſented the Doctrines of the Church of</hi> Rome,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reflect.</hi> p. 18.</note> 
               <hi>I would as ſoon be a</hi> Turk <hi>as your</hi> Papiſt. That <hi>Imaginary Monſters are raiſed up to knock down at pleaſure:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pref.</hi> p. 1.</note> 
               <hi>That we raiſe a Monſter of Religion, ſuch as none can be in love with,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 21.</note> 
               <hi>but thoſe that are bold enough to embrace Damnation bare-fac'd, and then this is the Character of Popery.</hi> And much more to the ſame purpoſe which he ſays up and down in his Replies. Nothing is more familiar with him than to ſay, we <hi>abhor,</hi> and <hi>deteſt,</hi> and <hi>abominate</hi> that which is charged upon us. But I beſeech you, Sir, is your Church ſo <hi>Catholick,</hi> as to take in Men
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:60867:24"/>who ſay and do ſuch things as part of their Religion, which you <hi>deteſt</hi> and <hi>abominate,</hi> who come with a <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of Religion that none can be in love with,</hi> but the Lovers of <hi>bare-fac'd Damnation?</hi> Or does it take in <hi>Turks?</hi> for you <hi>would as ſoon be a Turk as our Papiſt,</hi> as you told us long ſince. Here I am apt to think you will need all the improvement of your Confidence, and it will not help you neither. You have been thus long dancing in a Net, and if you are not ſecured that way I have ſo often hinted before, you will now begin to ſee it. For I pray obſerve, if the <hi>Characters</hi> that your firſt Anſwerer ſet a <hi>Papiſt</hi> out with, are black enough to make a Man look like a <hi>Turk,</hi> nothing could have been more eaſie to note than theſe <hi>Characters;</hi> and you know <hi>Monſters</hi> are very remarkable things, and may be ſhown with a Finger. And therefore we do expect that you would now at laſt point them out, as they lie <hi>at large</hi> (for ſo you ſay they do) <hi>throughout the</hi> Anſwerer<hi>'s Book.</hi> And when you have done this, it will then come upon you to declare whether with theſe Monſters you will preſent us to your Church, and undertake for our Admittance, or not. If you will not, pray ſay ſo, and by the way think of giving ſome account how thoſe Schoolmen, and private Authors came to be the celebrated Members, and thoſe <hi>Old</hi> Rituals and Maſs-books the ſtanding Offices of your Church; for you do not accuſe your Anſwerer for ſeeking any where elſe to find theſe <hi>Monſters.</hi> But, to come cloſe to the Point, if you will take any Man that comes with theſe <hi>Monſters,</hi> have we not great reaſon to ſupect that if we ſhould come without them, you would not expoſe your ſelf to defend us from them, if it ſhould be thought fit to let them looſe upon us? I hope therefore that we ſhall be troubled with this
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:60867:24"/>offer no more, of coming into your Church upon your Terms, till you give us ſome better reaſon than yet we have had, to believe that you are willing to ſecure us from thoſe Terms, which in general you ſay are monſtrous, but which you have not yet told us what they are in particular.</p>
            <p>HERE THEREFORE I CHALLENGE YOU TO DECLARE WHAT THOSE PARTICULARS ARE, THOSE MONSTERS, THOSE DOCTRINES AND PRACTICES WHICH YOU DO SO DETEST AND ABOMINATE; AND IF YOU REFUSE SO TO DO, I FASTEN UPON YOU THE MARK OF INSINCE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RITY AND JUGGLING, FOR OFFERING THAT WE SHALL BE RECEIVED INTO THE CHURCH OF ROME WITH<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>OUT THEM.</p>
            <p>For, obſerve me Sir, if for fear of falling foul upon thoſe of your own Party, you dare not declare in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular what thoſe Monſters are; tho this be neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to gain us to your Communion; how much leſs will you ſtand between us and them when once we are gain'd?</p>
            <p>Nor muſt you think to give us the ſlip now, as hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto you have done. It will no longer ſerve your turn to feign <hi>Characters</hi> of a <hi>Papiſt Miſrepreſented</hi> for us, and to <hi>raiſe up Imaginary Monſters,</hi> as you ſpeak, <hi>to knock down at pleaſure.</hi> Remember to take your Anſwerer's Characters of a Papiſt, who has ſo deſcribed your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, that you would as ſoon be a <hi>Turk</hi> as <hi>his Papiſt.</hi> This you know is to be done for <hi>our</hi> ſatisfaction, and therefore our Characters of a Papiſt, as we deſcribe them for our ſelves, not as you deſcribe them for us, are to be marked by you. Remember again, that you go from Point to Point, and tell us all along as you go,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:60867:25"/>what it is in his way of ſtating your Religion, which you deteſt and abominate; for we ſhall take it for gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that you do not deteſt, or at leaſt that you do not ſay that you deteſt, what you let go without any note of your Indignation. In a word, this is but what you ought to have done all this while, and the Repreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Controverſy had been ſoon at an end. But now it is neceſſary for you to do it, that we may at leaſt know what your Popery is, and what reaſon we have to truſt your Offers.</p>
            <p>Whether I ſhall hear from you upon theſe Matters, I cannot foreſee; but in the mean time I do not much care if I give you my Thoughts concerning the bottom of this Buſineſs; I queſtion not but you are willing to receive us into the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, upon our making the Profeſſion of your <hi>Papiſt Miſrepreſented;</hi> and, I have ſome reaſon to think, upon much eaſier terms of <hi>Profeſſion,</hi> for which I ſhall by and by give my Reaſon. If we would but do as you do, we might for ſome time put what Interpretation upon it we pleaſe. If we would ſubſcribe Pope <hi>Pius</hi> his Creed, we might de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver in a Proteſtation of what ſenſe we pleaſe; if we would but adore the <hi>Croſs,</hi> and worſhip the Sacrament as you do, we might declare what Intention we pleaſe: But in Matters of Religion, Inſincerity and Diſſimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion are ſuch odious things, that we who dare not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varicate with our own Conſciences, can neither have a very good Opinion of thoſe who would help us to do ſo, nor of the Cauſe which needs it. We cannot but ſee that the ſecret meaning of all is this, that we muſt ſubmit to <hi>Rome,</hi> and do as they do at <hi>Rome;</hi> and till better care can be taken, we may be allowed to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon what we do even as we liſt, and while we take our Rule of Faith and Worſhip from Papiſts, we
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:60867:25"/>may, if that will content us, go on to talk like Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants. And I doubt not, but that if this were honeſt, we might make better Conditions for our ſelves, than the Repreſenter has made for us. One thing I am ſure of, that the Converts of the City of <hi>Orange,</hi> were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived upon ſuch eaſy terms in point of Declaration, that if Subjection and Communion had not been to follow, one would have look'd upon the whole Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>action, as a ſolemn Jeſt between the French General, and the Biſhop of <hi>Orange</hi> on the one ſide, and the Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens of <hi>Orange</hi> on the other. The Paſſage is very re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable and inſtructing, and therefore I ſhall not think much to ſet down the Articles of Reconciliation, as I have received them from hands of unqueſtionable credit.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>1.</head>
                  <p>
                     <q>The Citizens of the Town of <hi>Orange</hi> that are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der written, conſidering that it is the Will of God (of which Kings are the principal Interpreters) that all <hi>Chriſtians</hi> ſhould reunite themſelves into the ſame Church; To teſtify their ſubmiſſion to the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Divine Providence, and that which they bear to the Holy Intentions of the King; do intreat of his Majeſty, that his Troops commanded by the Count de <hi>Teſſé,</hi> ſhould depart from them; and that the Expence which has been, or ſhall be made by them, be levied upon the whole State, without di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction of Religion.</q>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>We Order the Execution of the preſent Article, according to the full Tenor of it.</salute>
                     <signed>Teſsé.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:60867:26"/>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>2.</head>
                  <p>
                     <q>They declare that they do reunite themſelves to the Catholic Apoſtolic and <hi>Roman</hi> Church, after the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner which that Church do's uſe, to believe and to profeſs all the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> and <hi>Orthodox</hi> Truths con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the Holy Scripture, which God hath mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted to the Prophets, Apoſtles, and Evangeliſts, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the Interpretation and Senſe of the Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Church, and renouncing all Errors and Hereſies contrary thereunto.</q>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>3.</head>
                  <p>
                     <q>That for their great Conſolation and Edification, every <hi>Sunday</hi> before the Service, there ſhall be read a Chapter of the Holy Scripture, of the Old and New Teſtament in <hi>French,</hi> according to the Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlations approved by the Church; and that all the Divine Service which is performed in <hi>Latin,</hi> ſhall be explained in <hi>French</hi> by the Paſtors of the Church.</q>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>4.</head>
                  <p>
                     <q>That they ſhall invoke no other beſides God the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt.</q>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>5.</head>
                  <p>
                     <q>That they ſhall not believe that it is neceſſary to Salvation to have any other Interceſſion and Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, than that of our Lord <hi>Jeſus</hi> Chriſt towards God the Father.</q>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:60867:26"/>
                  <head>6.</head>
                  <p>
                     <q>That they ſhall not be obliged to render any Divine Honour to Images which ſhall be in the Church.</q>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>7.</head>
                  <p>
                     <q>That they ſhall adore <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> in the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> who is Really, Spiritually, and Sacramentally con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd in that Adorable Sacrament.</q>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>8.</head>
                  <p>
                     <q>That this Conſolation ſhall be given to the Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, that they ſhall communicate in both Kinds, if the Univerſal Church ſhall think it convenient.</q>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Done at</hi> Orange <hi>the</hi> 11th <date>
                           <hi>of</hi> Nov. 1685.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <q>We <hi>James d' Obeilh,</hi> by the Grace of God Biſhop of <hi>Orange,</hi> Abbot and Count of <hi>Montfor,</hi> Counſellor of the King in all his Councils, have admitted theſe who are counterſigned, to the Reunion of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholic, Apoſtolic, and <hi>Roman</hi> Church, upon the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions expreſſed in the Eight Articles above writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten.</q> Done at <hi>Orange</hi> this 13th of <hi>Novemb.</hi> 1685.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>John James</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Orange.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The Repreſenter may, I think, ſee in this Example that he is out-done in his own way, and that there are in the World more mild and inoffenſive Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of <hi>Popery</hi> than his own; and ſome proviſions for
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:60867:27"/>ſaving the Conſciences of the Reformed, which him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf has not made. But I would know of him whether he do's believe that thoſe who united themſelves to the <hi>Roman</hi> Church with theſe Cautions, can be reaſonably judged to have proceeded with ſatisfaction in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and about what they did: Or rather, whether there be not all the Signs that one can have in a thing of this Nature, that being diſtreſſed between a trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome Conſcience on the one Hand, and Count <hi>Teſſés</hi> Troops on the other, they <hi>capitulated</hi> as well as they could for their own quiet, and granted what they did, to be delivered from the Souldiers; and no more than what they did, if by that means they might pacify their own Minds. A very miſerable Caſe moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly! And that which is yet more to be lamented is, that theſe things ſhould be done by <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> upon <hi>Chriſtians.</hi> Let the Repreſenter take it into his ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Conſideration, and I believe it will be one of thoſe things that he will always forget to put into the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of his Papiſt Repreſented.</p>
            <p>But why muſt the Minds of Men be racked in this manner? Why muſt they be brought under the moſt dangerous Temptations to cheat themſelves, and for the gaining of reſt from outward Miſeries, to betray the Tranquillity of their own Conſciences, and be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to play ſuch Tricks with them, as if one Man ſhould chuſe to put upon another, he would be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted no better than a cunning Knave? He that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſee the true Reaſon of this unmerciful dealing, and that too by this very Example, can ſee but little. It is <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi> that is to ſay <hi>Submiſſion,</hi> to what they call the <hi>Catholic, Apoſtolic,</hi> and <hi>Roman</hi> Church, that muſt be by theſe means, or by any means carried on. This we meet with at the very head of the Proviſions, and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:60867:27"/>again at the foot of them in the Biſhop's Certificate; Nor are any of the Reformed to expect otherwiſe but that this ſhall be expreſly inſiſted on.</p>
            <p>But becauſe the poor People knew that Union to that Church carried dreadful Things along with it, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they ſtrugled, and it ſeems they gained one of the prittieſt Limitations of that <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> that ever was heard of; <hi>viz. To believe and to profeſs all the Chriſtian and Orthodox Truths contained in the Holy Scripture, which God hath manifeſted to the Prophets, Apoſtles, and Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſts.</hi> But then this Limitation would make the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> very inſignificant: for thus one may be united to the Turk, <hi>viz.</hi> to <hi>believe and to profeſs all the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian and Orthodox Truths contained in the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</hi> And therefore ſomething muſt be added to that; and certainly greater Artifice on both ſides, ſhall ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom be ſeen, than what is ſhewn in putting in theſe words, <hi>after the manner which that Church dos uſe;</hi> which may indifferently refer, either to <hi>reuniting</hi> or <hi>believing.</hi> The People may underſtand it of being <hi>united</hi> to the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, after the manner it uſes, till the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop teaches them to underſtand it of <hi>believing</hi> the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Truths of the <hi>Scripture,</hi> after <hi>the manner of that Church.</hi> And ſo by <hi>underſtanding the Scripture, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Interpretation and Senſe of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Church,</hi> the Biſhop has his meaning, and they have theirs as long as he will ſuffer them. The moſt jealous Princes never treated more nicely for their Honour, than theſe poor Proteſtants did for their Conſcience, and their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters for the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> And conſidering that they had but two hours allowed them to unite to the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, before the laſt Extremity ſhould be uſed upon refuſal; and that there were <hi>Difficulties on both Sides;</hi> the Proteſtants conſulted for their Conſciences as much
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:60867:28"/>as it was poſſible for Men to do, who ſaw Miſery be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, which they had already ſo deeply taſted of, that their Hearts were quite ſunk with the apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of what was juſt coming. But is this dealing for the Credit, I will not ſay of the Managers, but of the Cauſe they ſerve, and of the Method that is now taken to ſerve it by <hi>Expoſitions</hi> and <hi>Repreſentations?</hi> Why, if no more ſincerity were uſed in Fairs and Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets, than this comes to in the Concerns of Everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Salvation, Men had better live alone, and make what ſhift they can each one for himſelf, than to have any thing to do with one another. I was going to deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant upon every one of the other ſeven Articles; but to ſhew the Intrigue of them, though never ſo gravely, would look ſo like a <hi>Farce,</hi> that I count it decent to forbear, leſt I ſhould ſeem to make ſport with the Sins and Miſeries of Men. I ſhall only give the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this Note, that the Relation only ſays, there were <hi>Difficulties on both Sides,</hi> but that by the wording of the <hi>Conditions,</hi> it appears very probable that the Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens had brought them in another Form, when the Capitulation began; but that this was all they could obtain; and now that they are reduced to this Form, the ſagacity and watchfulneſs of one ſide is no leſs diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered, than of the other. But, O God, to what a paſs is the State of Religion brought amongſt <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have here given the Repreſenter an Example of reconciling <hi>Proteſtants</hi> to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> upon Terms much after his own way, only 'tis ſomething finer; though the Application I confeſs was more rug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, the Principality having felt the Dragoons to the ruin of it; and the utmoſt Extremities being threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in two hours, in caſe of refuſal to ſubſcribe.</p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:60867:28"/>
            <p>Thus much at leaſt they gained, that they might not be obliged to go to <hi>Maſs</hi> for three Months, nor to be preſent at the Offices of the Church; which was a plain demonſtration that theſe miſerable Perſons had ſubſcribed with an unſatisfied Mind; and that <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> and <hi>Submiſſion</hi> was the thing aimed at by the Reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers: but whether it was done upon the Convictions of the Citizens, what cared they? I can give no farther account of this Matter, but ſhall only put the Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenter in mind of one Paſſage in the <hi>State of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſy,</hi> which he cared not to reflect upon,
<note place="margin">State. <hi>p.</hi> 23.</note> 
               <hi>viz.</hi> That after the Biſhop of <hi>Meaux</hi> had treated of a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation upon Terms more moderate than his own Expoſition, while the Dragoons were at the Gates; he came in three Months, and treated them now as Perſons Reconciled; and without any regard to his own Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, or to their Conſciences, let the Dragoons looſe upon thoſe that refuſed to compleat their Conviction by going to <hi>Maſs.</hi> The Repreſenter may from all this, pick out ſome Reaſon, why he ought to be aſhamed of his Offer, that we ſhall be received upon the Terms of his Book.</p>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <head>IV.</head>
               <p>I come next to his Quotation of Mr. <hi>Montagu,</hi> from whence he would prove that the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land began too early</hi> to Miſrepreſent Papiſts; <hi>to deſerve now much credit in her Repreſentings.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Appello Caeſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum c. 23. p. 60, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> But what ſhall I call our Repreſenter here? Not the <hi>modeſteſt</hi> thing in Nature; for Mr. <hi>Montagu</hi> is moſt vilely abuſed by him, while he makes him bring in the Homilies as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenting the Papiſts. That which he ſays of them is this; <q>That they contain certain <hi>godly</hi> and <hi>whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome</hi>
                     <pb n="46" facs="tcp:60867:29"/>
                     <hi>Exhortations</hi> to move the People to Honour and Worſhip Almighty God, but not as <hi>the publick Dog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical Reſolutions</hi> confirmed of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> And again, They have not <hi>Dogmatical Poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions or Doctrine</hi> to be <hi>propugned</hi> and <hi>ſubſcribed</hi> in all and every Point, as the Books of <hi>Articles</hi> and of <hi>Common Prayer</hi> have.</q> Then follow the words which the Repreſenter begins with, <hi>They</hi> may <hi>ſeem</hi> ſecondly to <hi>ſpeak ſomewhat too hardly, and ſtretch ſome Sayings beyond the uſe and practice of the Church of</hi> England, both then and now; which laſt words the Repreſenter mentions not, nor theſe that follow immediately; <q>And yet what they ſpeak, may receive a fair, or at leaſt a tolerable conſtruction and mitigation well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough. For you have read peradventure, how ſtrangely ſome of the Ancienteſt <hi>Fathers</hi> do ſpeak, and how they <hi>hyperbolize</hi> ſometimes in ſome Points in their <hi>popular Sermons,</hi> which in <hi>Dogmatical De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſions</hi> they would not do, nor avow the Doctrine by them delivered <hi>reſolutivè.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Now the occaſion of all this was that Mr. <hi>Mountagu</hi> was charg'd by his Adverſaries for granting an allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able uſe of Images, contrary to the Homilies of the Church of <hi>England</hi> in the Sermon againſt the <hi>Peril of Idolatry,</hi> which ſeemeth to inveigh againſt all uſe of them. To this Mr. <hi>M.</hi> anſwered as before, producing the Homilies not as ſpeaking of what the Papiſts do, or not do, but as univerſally condemning the uſe of Images in Churches.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 262.</note> And he gives this account of it more fully, than I need to tranſcribe, <hi>viz.</hi> That as the <hi>Fathers ſpake againſt Images with ſome tartneſs and inveighing ſort,</hi> leſt the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> who had been Pagans themſelves, and now lived amongſt <hi>Pagans,</hi> might <hi>learn to worſhip Idols.</hi> So our Predeceſſors <hi>coming late
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:60867:29"/>out of Popery, and converſing with Papiſts, and knowing that Images uſed to be crept unto, incens'd, worſhipped and adored amongſt them, might, if they were ſuffered to ſtand as they did, induce them to do as they had ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time done; and therefore in a godly Zeal ſuch as moved</hi> Ezekias <hi>to deſtroy the Brazen Serpent, they ſpake thus vehemently, and indeed hyperbolically againſt them. For the People with whom they then dealt were by all means <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o be preſerved from the taint and tincture of their Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious Practices.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is the whole truth of the buſineſs, which the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> did not think fit to ſhew, but without taking the leaſt notice of the occaſion and ſubject of this Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, runs away with a few Phraſes, that he pick'd out from the reſt, as beſt fit for his purpoſe; ſuch as <hi>hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perbolizing, ſtretching upon the Tenters, by all means,</hi> and the like; and would make as if Mr. <hi>Mountague</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed the Church of <hi>England</hi> regarded not how ſhe repreſented <hi>Papiſts</hi> and <hi>Popery:</hi> Which wretched dealing is according to no common Honeſty but his own; and whoever goes on at this rate, will write himſelf out of all Credit, and there will be no need of anſwering his Books.</p>
               <p>'Tis to the ſame purpoſe that he brings in Mr. <hi>M.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pref.</hi> p. 19.</note> again, <hi>not thinking it any Reflection upon him if he does not altogether agree or ſubſcribe to the Doctrine of the Book of Homilies in his time, becauſe it being a Book fitted for a Seaſon, and declared neceſſary for THESE Times, what great wonder if what was a good Doctrine under</hi> Edward VI. <hi>was not ſo in the time of King</hi> James, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For thus he would perſwade us that <hi>we alter and change our Religion according to Times and Seaſons,</hi> which is what we juſtly charge upon them. The Compilers of the Homilies and Mr. <hi>M.</hi> meant
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:60867:30"/>the ſame thing, which this Man may ſhew a fault in, when he can, <hi>viz.</hi> that more Care is <hi>neceſſary</hi> at ſome times to ſecure People from <hi>Image-worſhip</hi> than at others, though our Religion, which will not allow us to worſhip Images, be the ſame at all times. If he thinks that the Homilies ſtretch their <hi>Hyperboles</hi> too far, let him compare them with what <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus, Tertullian, Minutius Felix,</hi> and other Antients ſay of the ſame Subject, and then tell <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> more of his Mind. But ſince, as Mr. <hi>M.</hi> judiciouſly obſerv'd, their ſevere Reflections againſt all uſe of Images whatſoever, are to be interpreted by the danger of being ſeduced to Idolatry which the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans were in in <hi>thoſe Times;</hi> ſo may the leſs hyperbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizing of our Homilies bear a good Conſtruction with reference to <hi>Theſe Times,</hi> in which we are ſure Images are worſhipped by certain People that the Repreſenter can tell of, with no leſs Devotion than the <hi>Pagans</hi> wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped theirs.</p>
               <p>The Reader, I hope, will now excuſe me, for taking no more notice of his proteſting againſt the diſtinction of <hi>Old</hi> and <hi>New</hi> Popery, his declaring that their Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief is always the ſame, and his lamentable Complaints that we are Miſrepreſenters,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pref.</hi> p. 20, 21.</note> and that we <hi>rake together ſome odd Opinions out of private Authors,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>that the Heads upon which our Repreſenting ſtands are ſo many Fallacies and Sophiſtry,</hi> &amp;c. For if a Man, after the Particulars of his Book have been particularly an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd, will ſtill betake himſelf to general Out-cries, and makes as if he intended to go on in this way as long as he lives, he ought to know at laſt, that he may do ſo without any more diſturbance, and that no body will go about to anſwer him.</p>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:60867:30"/>
               <p>And ſo I come to conſider his <hi>Reflections</hi> upon the <hi>View of the whole Controverſy, with the Anſwer to his laſt Reply.</hi> It <hi>ſeems the Stater,</hi> as he obſerves, <hi>had ſo good an Opinion of it, that he thought it would put an End to the Controverſy.</hi> The Repreſenter ſays that he is <hi>almost of the ſame Mind.</hi> And I ſay that I am <hi>alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether</hi> of the ſame Mind: And ſo there is one thing in which we do all of us <hi>almoſt</hi> agree.</p>
               <p>But why is the Repreſenter <hi>almost</hi> of that Mind? <q>
                     <hi>Becauſe</hi> the Anſwerer had ſaid ſo little to that long Bill which was drawn up againſt the Members of his Church,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pref.</hi> p. 22.</note> wherein the Crime of miſrepreſenting is laid to their Charge; that beſides what he <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſes,</hi> the very Guilt appears ſo plainly in the forced Excuſes he makes for the reſt, that there's little need of any more beſides reading his Defence to ſee how far they are from being <hi>innocent.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>So that by his own Confeſſion, he brought in a <hi>long Bill</hi> againſt ſome of our Church, wherein the Crime of miſrepreſenting is laid to their Charge. And the truth is, it was long enough conſidering that it had neither Truth nor Pertinence, as it was particularly ſhewn him in the Anſwer to his laſt Reply.</p>
               <p>For I muſt add, that the Anſwerer brought in a longer Anſwer of about 28 Pages to the Particulars of the Repreſenter's Bill, not omitting any one Charge upon any one of our Authors, where there was di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection to the Paſſage by Page or Chapter.</p>
               <p>And I do aſſure the Reader, that thoſe ſix or ſeven Lines of his which I tranſcribed juſt now out of his Preface, is all the Reply that he has given to that Anſwer. And I deſire the Reader to remember and conſider, that that tedious Charge of his, the Defence
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:60867:31"/>of which he now ſo viſibly forſakes, was manifeſtly brought in to ſupply the place of defending his 37 Points of Repreſentation, nay and of defending his very Pretences for forſaking them: And yet that now at laſt he forſakes the Defence of thoſe Imputations upon particular Authors, by which he hoped to divert the Reader from an expectation of Replies pertinent to his firſt undertaking.</p>
               <p>Now therefore I apply my ſelf to the Repreſenter, and deſire him to take as much notice of what I ſay, as if there was a Finger againſt it in the Margin: That becauſe he was ſo very modeſt, as not to offer the leaſt particular Reply to thoſe Anſwers to his Charge; therefore his continuing that Charge is the greater <hi>Impudence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>With all my Soul I wiſh that the Gentlemen of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> would imply other ſort of Men to write againſt us, for this Man carries on the Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſy not only to the diſparagement of their Cauſe in particular, but to the diſcredit of Religion in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral.</p>
               <p>But ſince I have ſuch a Countenance to deal with, I muſt not think to let even thoſe ſix Lines go with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſome particular Anſwers to them: For tho he can with a good Grace, drop his own Challenges and Undertakings one after another, and as he once ſaid, <hi>gravely turn over</hi> I know not how many Pages of ours, without offering a word to any one Particular that he finds there, and never change Countenance for the matter: Yet we are to watch every Line of his, and unleſs we intend to have another Book from him, we muſt prove that the Sun ſets before Midnight, if he ſhould happen to deny it.</p>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:60867:31"/>
               <p>He pretends that his Anſwerer ſaid <hi>ſo little</hi> to his <hi>long Bill,</hi> &amp;c. What ſhould I ſay to this? Should I print over again here the 28 Pages which were taken up in refuting thoſe Cavils of the Repreſenter? Or is it not enough, that I do now forbid him to make any Replies to the Particulars of that An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer?</p>
               <p>He pretends that the Anſwerer <hi>confeſſed</hi> ſomething, <hi>Beſides what he confeſſes,</hi> ſays he. So that if he may be believed, the Anſwerer has <hi>confeſſed</hi> that ſome of thoſe whom he mentions, have miſrepreſented the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> But this is adding Sin to Sin: For he <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs'd</hi> no ſuch thing, and I will add that he had no cauſe to confeſs it.</p>
               <p>Theſe words indeed I find in the Anſwer. <q>Did ever either of his Adverſaries undertake to juſtify all that any Proteſtant Divine or Hiſtorian has at any time ſaid in oppoſition to Popery? Or, was it not poſſible to give a more honeſt account of Popery than he did, without ſuch an Undertaking?</q> 
                  <hi>And again.</hi> 
                  <q>Tho it be no part of our buſineſs to bring off every thing that has been ſaid or done by Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, yet I ſhall a little examine what our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenter has charg'd thoſe with, whom he has ſingled out to expoſe them to the World—For my own part, where his Accuſations in whole or in part fall juſtly, there they ſhall lie for me, nor will I make another Man's fault my own, by going about to defend it.</q>
               </p>
               <p>But is this <hi>confeſſing,</hi> that <hi>Miſrepreſentation</hi> was proved upon any one Author that was charged with it? The Anſwerer it ſeems was reſolved, as became him, never to wrangle either for a Friend, or againſt an Enemy; and he found in the long Bill one or two
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:60867:32"/>filly Sayings of Proteſtants, which this Man called <hi>Miſrepreſentations;</hi> for inſtance, a very weak Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of <hi>Sutcliff</hi>'s from as weak a Propoſition of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinas.</hi> For this reaſon the Anſwerer thought fit to declare, that he would not juſtify what he thought was to be blamed. But if this Man was reſolved to call what he pleaſed a <hi>Miſrepreſentation</hi> of his Church, by his leave he ſhould have asked the Anſwerer, whether he would call it ſo too, before it was lawful for him to bring in the Anſwerer confeſſing I know not what, of our miſrepreſenting the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> For my own part, I am reſolv'd, that if any particular Authors of ours have in any one Point miſrepreſented Popery in the leaſt degree, I will not do it for Company, nor defend thoſe that have done it. But I am not a little pleas'd to find that when the Repreſenter forſook the defence of his 37 Chapters, and diverted to the buſineſs of tranſcribing all thoſe Proteſtant Authors, where he hoped to find ſome In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of our <hi>miſrepreſenting;</hi> he ſhould yet come in with ſo lamentable an account on his part, and not be able to produce any one clear Inſtance to ſupport his Charge.</p>
               <p>When I had read his Charge, I was ſomething a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maz'd, that conſidering how much has been written againſt the Errors of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> ſince the Reformation, by Men of different Abilities, he ſhould not have been able to make better work of his laſt impertinent deſign than he did. And it will be to all impartial Judges an Argument, that the ſeveral Writers of our Church have upon the whole matter, obſerved a ſtrange exactneſs of Truth in charging the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> when this Man was able to produce
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:60867:32"/>no more than he did for a colour to accuſe us of the contrary.</p>
               <p>But what do we think the Repreſenter concludes in another place from the Anſwerer's declaring before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand, that he will not be anſwerable for <hi>every thing that has been ſaid or done in oppoſition to Popery?</hi> Why,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pref.</hi> p. 26.</note> ſays he, <hi>then it ſeems now there are ſome Proteſtants that charge more upon the Papiſts than can be well brought off or juſtified, and ſome Proteſtants are accuſed juſtly, and not to be defended without partaking of their fault.</hi> What, of miſrepreſenting the Church of <hi>Rome!</hi> But the Anſwerer did by no means confeſs that he had brought any pertinent Inſtances of that. There may be ſuch for ought I know, and if there are, let them bear it as I ſaid before; but as I ſay now, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants have been very honeſt and careful as to this buſineſs of Repreſenting, or ſurely we ſhould have had one or two clear Inſtances of the contrary from this good Friend of ours; unleſs we ſhould ſay 'tis all one to him whether his Inſtances be good or bad, becauſe he has a certain quality that will make them do whether they will or not: Which I believe will be acknowledged by every one that conſiders thoſe words of his which immediately follow. <hi>If this had been as freely owned at firſt, we had excuſed a great deal of Pains and Paper; for I had never gone about to prove that Proteſtants miſrepreſent Papiſts,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 26.</note> 
                  <hi>if the firſt Replier had thus ingenuouſly confeſs'd that Charge. And becauſe it was not owned, I therefore found my ſelf obliged to take ſome Pains about it,</hi> that is,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 22.</note> 
                  <hi>in my long Bill that was drawn up,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Well! He ha now done His worſt; for the next ſtretch beyond this will break him. I confeſs that the Anſwerer did <hi>ingenuouſly</hi> declare againſt abet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:60867:33"/>any Man's <hi>Miſpreſentations:</hi> But that he did <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuouſly confeſs that Charge</hi> againſt the Authors that were produced, is, what I hope no Man living this day, excepting the Repreſenter only, will have the face to ſay. He I know <hi>took ſome pains to prove</hi> the Charge, and the Anſwerer took a little Pains too about the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs; but ſurely he was as much beſide himſelf, as ſometimes I would for Charity ſake imagine the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenter to be, if he was all the while <hi>ingenuouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing it;</hi> for I verily thought, and do think ſtill, that he was all the while plainly and honeſtly <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futing</hi> it.</p>
               <p>But becauſe upon this occaſion I would be glad to underſtand with what Caution a Man muſt write, that has to do with one of the Repreſenter's Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution; I have ſeverely examin'd what occaſion this Man ſhould pretend for the liberty he takes. I find that as to one or two Inſtances the Anſwerer acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged a fault where the Charge was laid, but he did not confeſs that it was <hi>Miſrepreſentation. Sutcliff</hi>'s was the plaineſt, whoſe Inference from <hi>Aquinas</hi> he acknowledg'd to be very ſilly. But as to all the reſt, he ſhewed that the Repreſenter's Charge was either falſe or very fooliſh: And that this Man was for the moſt part an egregious Miſrepreſenter in uſing thoſe Authors of as ours he did. So that 'tis <hi>Sutcliff</hi>'s Caſe that muſt bring in the Anſwerer for that ſame inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuous Confeſſion. And the Reader is bound to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that if we had at firſt confeſſed that <hi>Sutcliff</hi> made a ſilly Inference from as ſilly a Principle of <hi>Aquinas,</hi> here had been <hi>a great deal of Paper and Pains excuſed, and this Man had never gone about to prove that Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants miſrepreſent Papiſts.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:60867:33"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Doctr. and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices of the Ch. of R.</note> And yet after all, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>p.</hi> 9, &amp;c.</note> his firſt Anſwerer would not undertake for all that any Proteſtants had ſaid of Popery, but appeal'd to the publick and eſtabliſh'd Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly, he pretends in thoſe ſix Leaves, that <hi>beſides what the</hi> Anſwerer <hi>confeſs'd, Guilt appears plainly in the forced Excuſes he made for the reſt.</hi> Now if he made but <hi>forced Excuſes</hi> for them, he had, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, done a great deal better, to follow the Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenter's Example, who, when ſome Popiſh Authors were charged for moſt vile and ſcandalous reports of us and our Religion, was ſo very prudent as to make <hi>no Excuſes at all</hi> for them.</p>
               <p>Which gives me occaſion to ſay here, what the True reaſon was of the Anſwerer's putting together thoſe few Inſtances how we have been uſed by thoſe of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church. We hoped this at leaſt from the Repreſenter's Firſt Book, that it would occaſion ſuch a clear and perfect ſtating of the Queſtions be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween us and the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> that the People of both Communions would be well prepared to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand afterwards the pertinence of the ſeveral Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Anſwers that ſhould be brought on ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide. Nor could any Man of Senſe and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty imagine that his Book was good for any thing elſe, but to lead to that. With this purpoſe the Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Author of <hi>the Doctrines and Practices of the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>truly Repreſented;</hi> complied in his Anſwer to the Repreſenter. But it was none of the Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter's Deſigns, that People ſhould know the True ſtate of the Controverſy, but that they ſhould believe his
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:60867:34"/>Repreſentations; and therefore he has ever ſince, by one Wile after another, declined cloſing with his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerer; and at laſt by raking for Inſtances of <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Miſrepreſenters.</hi> This Deſign he largely purſued in his <hi>long Bill.</hi> The Author of the <hi>View</hi> having ſhewn him that he was foully to blame in charging even thoſe Proteſtant Writers whom he ſingled out, took a courſe to divert him for the future, from this wild and unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable way of proceeding, and that by letting him ſee that if he was reſolved to perſiſt in this way, he would loſe by it; ſince he would not be able to excuſe his own from thoſe Faults, which he had without juſt cauſe charged upon our Men. And ſo he ſhewed by a few Inſtances, how <hi>Proteſtants</hi> had been uſed by <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts.</hi> Now one would have thought, that at leaſt he ſhould have reinforced his Charge upon our Men, and defended his own againſt the Anſwerer, if he was ſtill reſolved to continue his Clamours of Miſre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation. But what has he done? He has taken about a Years time to conſider of the Matter, and at laſt replies not to any one Defence that had been made for thoſe whom he had put into his <hi>Long Bill,</hi> and do's not offer the leaſt Syllable for one of thoſe that the Anſwerer had put into his <hi>Short</hi> One. I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, he ſays, that the Anſwerer made but <hi>Forced Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſes</hi> for our Friends. Now as the Repreſenter has behaved himſelf, I think my Credit may be good e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to encounter his. I ſay therefore, that the Anſwerer made no <hi>forced Excuſes,</hi> becauſe for the moſt part there were no <hi>Excuſes</hi> at all, but down-right <hi>Vindications.</hi> And as for the Excuſes that are there, if there be any ſuch, I do not deſire the Reader to take my word for them, if he will promiſe not to
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:60867:34"/>take the Repreſenters neither, but to go to the View, and Judg for himſelf.</p>
               <p>After all, the Repreſenter is to be commended for one thing, that he ſays the Anſwerer <hi>drew him back to his firſt Book—in reality to put a ſtop to this part of the Controverſy, and that we might hear no farther of the Church of</hi> England<hi>'s Miſrepreſenting.</hi> For though he meant this to the Anſwerer's Diſgrace, yet 'tis true that this was one part of his Deſign, for he ſaw the Repreſenter was got upon an Idle Haunt, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhewed him that it would turn to no better ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count for him, than any Body elſe. But this was not all, for the Anſwerer would have drawn him to his Firſt Book, that he might either like an able Man de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend his Characters, or like an honeſt Man confeſs that he could not; which had been ſomething to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the ſettlement of the State of the ſeveral Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions: Though I think they muſt be acknowledged to be well ſetled by the Learned Anſwerer that firſt appeared againſt him, ſince the Repreſenter dares not go about to ſtir them. But whereas he thinks, he was fetched up to his Firſt Book, <hi>under a pretence</hi> of ſhewing him, that he had drop'd his Cauſe, and gone out of the way: I confeſs all that too, excepting the word <hi>Pretence;</hi> For his Anſwerer did the Buſineſs ſo effectually, that I forbid the Repreſenter ſo much as to <hi>pretend</hi> to vindicate himſelf againſt thoſe plain and particular Proofs of this thing that were brought againſt him. For that he is well reſolved againſt any ſuch <hi>Pretence,</hi> is plain to me, from the Similitude wherewith he has fortified himſelf againſt all thoughts of any thing like a Reply to the <hi>View.</hi> For, ſays he, <hi>this is nothing but what we ſee by daily experience, that
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:60867:35"/>when two have been debating a Point a great while, at length one that finds himſelf aground, begins to unra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel the whole Diſpute from the beginning, with you ſaid this,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pref.</hi> p. 23.</note> 
                  <hi>and I ſaid this; and then you ſaid this, and I ſaid this, and you ſaid this.</hi> I hope the Reader will not ſo much as ſuſpect that I have abuſed him in this; but if he thinks it incredible that a Man in his Wits ſhould put ſuch ſilly ſtuff into a Book. I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not help it if he takes him to be out of his Wits; but as for theſe Sayings, I am ſure he may find them in the <hi>Preface</hi> to his <hi>Third Part;</hi> and though the Pages are not numbred, he may find them in that Page to which I have referred in the Margin, if he will pleaſe to num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber them himſelf.</p>
               <p>And yet after all, he would not have it thought that he is afraid to go back as far as to the <hi>Papiſt Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repreſented and Repreſented:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 23.</note> Which he does for a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Reaſon, <hi>viz.</hi> to give us an account once more of his Deſign in writting that Book, and of his <hi>Motive</hi> to it.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 24.</note> His Deſign was to <hi>deſcribe a Catholic as he is,</hi> and <hi>as he is thought to be.</hi> His Motive was an Obſervation of his, that his Catholics ſuffered very much by <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Miſrepreſentations.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But that which follows is rare, that he did not think himſelf obliged to give an account of <hi>both</hi> his Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters to <hi>Proteſtants.</hi> Indeed, as for the Character of a <hi>Papiſt Miſrepreſented,</hi> he <hi>looked upon</hi> that as <hi>ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing relating to them.</hi> But as for that of a <hi>Papiſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented,</hi> it belonged not to <hi>Proteſtants</hi> to meddle with that at all, but only to his <hi>pretended</hi> Catholics. <hi>For,</hi> ſays he, <hi>to whom ſhould the examination of a Syſtem of any ones Faith belong, beſides thoſe whoſe Faith it is ſaid to be?</hi> I thank him heartily. It ſeems we are to take
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:60867:35"/>from him a Syſtem of Popery, without examining whether it be (as he ſpeaks) <hi>exact</hi> and <hi>true,</hi> or not; and the reaſon is plain, becauſe as yet <hi>'tis not our Faith,</hi> and therefore the <hi>examination</hi> of it <hi>belongs not to us.</hi> But when we are become <hi>Papiſts</hi> upon his Terms, then if we pleaſe we may examine whether it was wiſely or fooliſhly done of us, to take a <hi>Syſtem</hi> of the Popiſh <hi>Faith</hi> upon his Word. And therefore he could not be obliged to juſtify his Character of a <hi>Papiſt Rrepreſented,</hi> after we had ſhewn it was not a ſincere <hi>Character,</hi> becauſe we meddle with a Matter that <hi>belonged</hi> not to us, and was none of our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern.</p>
               <p>But for one thing we are not a little beholden to him, that though in truth we were buſy where we had nothing to do, <hi>viz.</hi> in the <hi>Firſt, Second,</hi> and <hi>Third Anſwers</hi> to him, yet he mended the Matter for us, by <hi>looking upon</hi> thoſe Anſwers <hi>as chiefly relating to the Character of a Papiſt Miſrepreſented,</hi> in which he confeſſes we had <hi>ſomething</hi> to do: So that though thoſe Anſwers <hi>chiefly related</hi> to one, as we thought, yet he did but <hi>look upon them,</hi> and forthwith they <hi>chiefly related</hi> to the other. And ſo care is taken for the Character of a <hi>Papiſt Repreſented.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We will go to the other Character preſently, when I have given him a neceſſary <hi>Item</hi> upon this great Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, <hi>viz.</hi> that when he draws any more double Characters, he would take very great care, that his <hi>Papiſt Miſrepreſented,</hi> be drawn very honeſtly, that we may the more eaſily ſwallow what he ſays of a Papiſt Repreſented; leſt if we find, as hitherto we have done, that he plays tricks in a Buſineſs that does <hi>belong</hi> to us to examine, we ſhould have the leſs rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:60867:36"/>to take his word for a Buſineſs that does not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to us to examine, till we have taken his word for it.</p>
               <p>And now for the other Character; he obſerved, it feems, that <hi>the Anſwers appeared to be all from Church of</hi> England <hi>hands,</hi> who <hi>ſeemed much concerned to clear themſelves from being thought Miſrepreſenters;</hi> and therefore they <hi>denied the Charge,</hi> which as he ſays, <hi>was part of their Plea.</hi> But therefore it might be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, that he ſhould either make good his Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters againſt the Church of <hi>England</hi>-Men, or hold his hand till ſome other Proteſtants came forth to clear themſelves, who had Miſrepreſented Popery, juſt as he pretended <hi>ſome</hi> Proteſtants at leaſt to have done: But being reſolved to write on, and not being able to faſten any of his Firſt Miſrepreſentations upon the Church of <hi>England,</hi> he fell to ranſack ſome <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Writers of our Communion, for new Miſrepreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. And ſo the <hi>Miſrepreſenting</hi> ſide of his Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters was left to ſhift for it ſelf, as well as the other.</p>
               <p>But why were not his firſt Characters of a Papiſt Miſrepreſented, either proved againſt us, or charged upon ſome Body elſe, or confeſſed to be impertinent and fooliſh, as the ſecond Anſwer ſhewed moſt of them to be? What excuſe has he for troubling the World with a Book of two Columnes, neither of which he thought it his Duty to defend? Why, he tells you that he <hi>Fathered not the Character of a Papiſt Miſrepreſented upon the Church of</hi> England,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 25.</note> 
                  <hi>but upon his own APPREHENSIONS.</hi> So that
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:60867:36"/>he wrote half a Book againſt <hi>his own Apprehenſions;</hi> and as long as he was ſure that his <hi>own Apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions</hi> would not write againſt him, he was ſecure al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo that he ſhould never be obliged to defend his. Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of a <hi>Papiſt Miſrepreſented,</hi> againſt any Body, and therefore not againſt the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Indeed he tells us, ſome time after,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 26.</note> that he <hi>ſet down ſome former Apprehenſions of his own concerning Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, with ſome little Addition of what he had heard from others.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And again; <hi>I ſaid,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 27.</note> 
                  <hi>that Character was according to the Apprehenſions I had formerly of a Papiſt — and if I extended it any farther than my ſelf, it was becauſe I had found the ſame in others.</hi> But he is as ſecure from being called to account by thoſe <hi>others,</hi> as by his <hi>former Apprehenſions.</hi> For if thoſe <hi>others</hi> be <hi>ſome Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,</hi> they muſt needs be aſhamed to appear in this Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs; nor do I think they are capable of writing Books, who charge the Conſequences of what the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts hold and do upon them, as their declared and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vowed Doctrines and Practices. But if thoſe others be <hi>No-body,</hi> then there is No-body to hurt him. He underſtood his Advantage in all this perfectly well. For, ſays he, <hi>This, i. e.</hi> that he had heard the ſame from others, <hi>was no more to be denied or diſproved than the other part, as it related to himſelf. 'Tis enough,</hi> ſays he, <hi>for my purpoſe, that in the Miſrepreſenting Character, a Papiſt is expreſſed and made to appear other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe than he is, and that I apprehended a Papiſt ſomething after that manner while I was a Proteſtant. When this is diſproved, I have ſomething to Anſwer, but till then I can have forſaken no Defence, becauſe nothing has been ſaid againſt me,</hi> &amp;c. If this Man can forbear <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving</hi>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:60867:37"/>himſelf, all the World can not touch him, whatever he makes bold to write. But let him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, and he will in time do his own buſineſs, as he has begun to do it here. For now he tells us that he apprehended a Papiſt <hi>ſomething</hi> after that manner. <hi>Something</hi> is a dangerous word in this place. For if he did not apprehend a Papiſt <hi>altogether,</hi> or <hi>very much</hi> after that manner, I wonder who is to anſwer for the reſt. For I reckon that his <hi>ſomething,</hi> and the <hi>little Addition</hi> he heard from others, will hardly ſave half his Characters from being an Impoſture, if we judg of it by his own words.</p>
               <p>But, ſays he, <hi>what then ſignifies all the noiſe of my having forſaken the Defence of the thirty ſeven Chapters in my firſt Book?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 25.</note> I know not truly what elſe it ſhould <hi>ſignify</hi> but an undeniable Truth that he has <hi>forſaken</hi> it. For he has forſaken the Defence of the Papiſt <hi>Repreſented,</hi> becauſe that <hi>belonged not to us</hi> to meddle with, but only to his <hi>Catholicks.</hi> And he has for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken the Papiſt <hi>Miſrepreſented</hi> too, for though this Character <hi>ſomething related</hi> to us, as he once thought, yet upon better conſideration, that belonged to us no more than that other, but only to <hi>his own Apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions,</hi> and to ſome <hi>others</hi> in the Clouds, that are never likely to give him any diſturbance.</p>
               <p>Well; but he has ſhewn however that the Church of <hi>England</hi> has miſrepreſented Papiſts, though per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps not according to his firſt Characters of a Papiſt <hi>miſrepreſented.</hi> Now though this be a Charge which we might be concern'd upon other accounts to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs againſt thoſe particular Men, that are arraign'd by him, or to diſprove it: Yet ſtill it remains true,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:60867:37"/>that he has forſaken the Defence of both ſides of his 37 Chapters, as the Author of the <hi>View</hi> has unanſwerably proved: And in his wretched way of ſhifting it off, he has confeſſed it as much to his ſhame, as a plain Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of it had been ſomething for his credit. But then I add, that neither is it true that he has proved his new Charge of Miſrepreſentation either upon the Church of <hi>England,</hi> or upon Church of <hi>England</hi>-Men. For his ſaying that the Author of the <hi>Veiw ſeemed to give up the Point,</hi> and <hi>that he freely owned it,</hi> and the like, is a ſtretch beyond what is at any time done for Mony. For the World ſees, that on the other hand, that Author pretended to ſhew that the Man was in this alſo an egregious Miſrepreſenter of our Writers. And one would think it was done effectually: for the Man has dropt alſo the Defence of that his laſt Charge againſt the particular Anſwers that were made to it; juſt as he dropt all before, only with this Addition of <hi>Face</hi> now, that the Author of the <hi>View</hi> had <hi>freely owned it,</hi> and <hi>ingenuouſly confeſs'd it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If this Anſwer of mine ſhould fall into the hands of any of our Communion, that have not read theſe his <hi>Reflections,</hi> I muſt once more confeſs my ſelf a little afraid, loſt they ſhould think I banter him in this account of his ſhuffling off one thing after ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And therefore I do ſolemnly aſſure the Reader, that he does not ſay theſe things once only, but he comes over with them again. And becauſe 'tis an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary caſe, I muſt tranſcribe him; and firſt where he ſpeaks of his Character of a <hi>Papiſt Miſrepre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:60867:38"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Well,</hi> ſays he, <hi>but in ſo doing,</hi> i. e. <hi>in proving his new Charge of Miſrepreſentation, I left it ſeems the Defence of the thirty ſeven Chapters. How ſo? As to the firſt Character in all theſe Chapters, I only undertook to ſet down ſome former Apprehenſions of my own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Popery, with ſome little Addition of what I had heard from others. Now what had I to defend in this? Could any one ſay I had not ſuch Apprehenſions? or, that formerly while a Proteſtant, I had not ſuch Notions and Thoughts of the Papiſts, and of their Religion wrought in me by what I had heard from the Pulpit and other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways? And if this neither was nor could be pretended, what had I to defend in that Character throughout the thirty ſeven Chapters?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then as to the ſecond Character. <hi>What Defence,</hi> ſays he, <hi>have I forſaken there? — I undertook to give an account of my Religion as I was taught it.— The Religion there delivered is the Popery I was taught; there is expreſſed the Papiſt; I then was at the penning that Character, and now am. And this I ſuppoſe no body has diſproved yet, and ſo I have forſaken no Defence of it.</hi> So that this Character was written too according to his <hi>own Apprehenſions:</hi> And unleſs a Man can prove that he had not thoſe Apprehenſions of Popery, ſince he became a Papiſt, and when he wrote his Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters, it is to no more purpoſe to write againſt this Repreſenting Character, than it is to write againſt the Miſrepreſenting Character, unleſs one could prove that he had not thoſe other Apprehenſions of Popery, when he was a Proteſtant. Never was Man ſo ſecure againſt being confuted. I do not wonder at his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:60867:38"/>at all, for he has reaſon for it, and ſuch as I believe no Man ever found out before him. And I expect that in his next Book he ſhould with no little Triumph tell the Reader, that I confeſs him to be <hi>Invincible.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But I muſt not forget that other Reaſon, <hi>viz.</hi> of this Character <hi>not belonging to Proteſtants to examine.</hi> He ſays, <hi>If there was any thing faulty in this, I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected to hear of it from Catholicks, for whilſt I pretended to deliver their Faith, who ſhould judg whether it was right or wrong but they?</hi> And at this rate he goes on for almoſt two Pages together, concluding, that <hi>the currant paſſing of the Book and general reception of it without exception,</hi> i. e. <hi>among</hi> Papiſts, <hi>was enough to war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant the Doctrine for Authentick.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now he had nothing to account for, but for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaking the Defence of his Reaſons for that Popery which he owned. For the truth is, he forſook all, as the <hi>View</hi> undeniably ſhewed. Only there is one Quality which God grant he may forſake, but I fear he never will. I will not give it the <hi>Name</hi> here, but leave the Reader to do that, when I have given one more Inſtance from our Repreſenter of the <hi>Thing. And ſo,</hi> ſays he, <hi>at laſt it is here confeſs'd that the Doctrines are rightly propoſed, and that I have duly repreſented a Catholick, but that I made no Defence of the Reaſons.</hi> He had before brought in the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the <hi>View</hi> as <hi>freely owning</hi> and <hi>ingenuouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing</hi> the <hi>Charge</hi> of <hi>Miſrepreſentation.</hi> And now at laſt to make one ſide hang even with the other, he brings him in <hi>confeſſing</hi> that he had <hi>duly repreſented</hi> a
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:60867:39"/>Catholick too. This Man has conſidered <hi>Machiavel</hi>'s Rule, that he that will thrive by the left-hand way, muſt never look towards the right one.</p>
               <p>Well, he tells us now for a cloſe, that <hi>he has not been ſhort of any thing he undertook.</hi> Not of any thing? What is then to be ſaid for forſaking the <hi>Reaſons;</hi> the <hi>Defence</hi> of the <hi>Reaſons?</hi> Why, he has a trick for that too, and becauſe it cannot be mended, the old one ſhall ſerve the turn. Says he, <hi>Since I only engaged to ſet down ſome of the Reaſons which hold Men in that</hi> [the Roman] <hi>Communion, 'tis plain I did all only by way of propoſal or hiſtorically, and till ſome body has demonſtrated that theſe are not ſome of the Reaſons which hold Men in that Communion, I have no Defence to make, and ſo can have forſaken none.</hi> That is to ſay, his buſineſs was not to ſet down Reaſons, and make them good afterward, if any body ſhould be ſo croſs as to ſet upon them, but his buſineſs was to ſhew ſome Reaſons for his Doctrine, ſuch as they are held by, but whether they were good Reaſons or bad Reaſons, what was that to us?</p>
               <p>At laſt we have a Reaſon why he was not for <hi>Diſputing,</hi> viz. becauſe <hi>nothing has been offered in that kind by any Adverſary, but what has been anſwered by Catholicks five hundred times over.</hi> Now <hi>five hundred</hi> is a good round even Number, and he was loth to make it irregular by adding <hi>one</hi> more to it; for then it muſt have be ſaid henceforward, that we had been anſwered 501 times over. This I take to be as good a Reaſon as any we have had from him yet, or are like to have from him in haſte.</p>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:60867:39"/>
               <p>To come to a Concluſion: He began with his <hi>double Characters,</hi> and forſook the Defence of them.</p>
               <p>He gave us <hi>Reaſons</hi> and <hi>Reflections,</hi> and he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſook them too.</p>
               <p>He made a <hi>Fanatick Sermon,</hi> and great defiance there was about it; but the Sermon was undertaken, and we hear no more of the Sermon.</p>
               <p>He tried what was to be done by drawing up a <hi>new Charge</hi> of <hi>Miſrepreſentation</hi> upon ſome <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. The Charge was anſwered; and he takes no farther care of that Charge; if it will ſtand upon its firſt Legs, well and good: if not, what cares he?</p>
               <p>The Author of the <hi>View</hi> gave him a ſample of ſome <hi>Popiſh Miſrepreſentations</hi> of us and our Religion. And he does not offer ſo much as to excuſe them, no not by a word.</p>
               <p>What is to be done next?</p>
               <p>Even let us once more begin the World again, with <hi>fifteen</hi> new Chapters of a <hi>Papiſt Miſrepreſented and Repreſented;</hi> for the worſt is paſt, we may ſpeed better next time; but 'tis impoſſible for us to come off more ſhamefully than we have done al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="reply">
            <pb facs="tcp:60867:40"/>
            <pb n="69" facs="tcp:60867:40"/>
            <head>A REPLY TO THE VINDICATOR<hi>'s Full Anſwer.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE <hi>Vindicator</hi> has expreſs'd ſome contempt of the <hi>Defenders</hi> laſt Book.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>P.</hi> 1.</note> If I had been in his caſe, it had been ſome temptation up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me to do the like: And therefore I will not aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate this Matter againſt him.</p>
            <p>Some Anger alſo is expreſs'd, for being told by the Author of <hi>the Diſcourſe concerning Extreme <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction,</hi> that the Biſhop of <hi>Meaux</hi> and he might now go and put words together, eſpecially becauſe <hi>another Year</hi> was given them. I perceive he ſcorns to have it thought, that he either needs the Biſhop of <hi>Meaux</hi>'s help, or a <hi>Years</hi> time to put words together. And ſo about a Month after the <hi>Second Defence,</hi> out comes a <hi>Full Anſwer</hi> of his own.</p>
            <p>As for the Biſhop, the Vindicator has ſaid nothing for him: And I think the Biſhop is beholden to him for it, who is in this one thing happy that his Vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor has left him to ſhift for himſelf.</p>
            <p>When I ſaw a Sheet and half come forth for a <hi>Full Anſwer</hi> to the <hi>Second Defence,</hi> I preſently underſtood, the Man's meaning to be, that the Defence had little
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:60867:41"/>or nothing in it. For ſome ſuch thing as this, the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender inſinuated of the Repreſenter's laſt Book, by calling his Poſtſcript, a <hi>Full Anſwer</hi> to it. But now the Repreſenter has been anſwered more largely in the foregoing Part, and therefore we might expect in Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour a more Full Anſwer than this <hi>Sheet</hi> and <hi>Half-</hi> to the <hi>Second Defence.</hi> But we expect no ſuch thing for all that: For tho as the World goes, ſome Men are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to ſay much againſt Nothing, yet others finding it very painful to ſay much for Nothing, have had the Face to call <hi>Half-ſheets</hi> and ſuch things <hi>Full Anſwers</hi> to ſuch Books; as if their more Learned Predeceſſors were now alive, they would have given us, we are apt to think, what weight they had, and at leaſt equal mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in Return for them.</p>
            <p>To this <hi>Full Anſwer</hi> of his,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>P.</hi> 2.</note> I intend to give a Reply more Full than his Anſwer is, which ſlips over many Conſiderations in the Defenders Book, for which I am ſure he cannot pretend in the Repreſenter's ſtrain, that they have been anſwered five hundred times o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</p>
            <p>He <hi>declares once for all, that he is reſolved not to let any of the Defenders pretended Proofs eſcape, or any thing that looks like a ſolid Anſwer paſs unſatisfied.</hi> Which Declaration was the more fit to be made <hi>once for all,</hi> becauſe it would trouble a Man's Conſcience a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain to make it the <hi>ſecond time:</hi> or at leaſt it would ſtartle the Reader <hi>as often</hi> as it was made.</p>
            <p>But <hi>in purſuit of this Intention</hi> as he ſays, and it may be to make good his own Title of a <hi>Full Anſwer,</hi> he falls in the firſt place upon the Defender's <hi>Title-Page;</hi> where he would have had the Book called, <hi>A free Confeſſion of the Matter of Fact in all the Vindicator's
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:60867:41"/>Exceptions.</hi> The Defender, I am ſure, neither pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to <hi>prove</hi> nor to <hi>anſwer</hi> in his Title Page. But they are often buſy, where no need is, who are idle where their Buſineſs lies. However I ſhall remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber this, and deſire to know what there is in the Book to make it deſerve the Title of a <hi>Free Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>In the mean time I obſerve, that he and the Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenter are agreed to rid their hands of this Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſy, by affirming now at laſt, that we <hi>freely confeſs</hi> ſomething or other, which they have all this while la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured in vain to prove.</p>
            <p>But before I have done with this Full Anſwer of his, I may perhaps convince them both, that they did not lay their Heads long enough together; and that while they were agreeing what to make us <hi>confeſs,</hi> they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got a more material Point, and that was, now in ſo great a ſtrait as the Repreſenting Controverſy was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to, to agree in what they ſhould confeſs them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
            <p>The Firſt Part of the <hi>Defence</hi> which he pretends to anſwer, is the <hi>Hiſtorical Vindication</hi> of the <hi>Diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> between <hi>Old</hi> and <hi>New</hi> Popery. For the Defender obſerving how much that <hi>Diſtinction was diſliked</hi> by this Man, told him, that he <hi>found it in effect made to his hand in ſome of the Biſhop of</hi> Meaux<hi>'s own Converts, and in Books which are ſaid to have undergone his parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular peruſal before they were permitted to come into the World.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Def. Pref.</hi> P. 3.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But the Vindicator declares, that in the proof of this, <hi>when he came to examine it, he found nothing to the purpoſe.</hi> Which is more than I ſhall ſay of his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions to it, for I think ſomething will be found in
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:60867:42"/>them to our purpoſe, how little ſoever there may be to his own.</p>
            <p>The Firſt Inſtance of the Converts is Monſieur <hi>Brueys,</hi> who vehemently exhorted the Proteſtants to return to the <hi>Roman</hi> Communion by this Argument, That <hi>the Doctrine of the Church was ſo expounded, as none of their Forefathers underſtood it.</hi> Of which, and much more to the ſame purpoſe, the Vindicator ſays, <hi>I ſtand in need of your Spectacles, Sir, to ſee how he</hi> [Monſieur <hi>Brueys] proves that there was New and Old Popery any where, but in the Conceit of our Adverſaries, their Forefathers, as he calls them.</hi> Which certainly is none of the wiſeſt Anſwers that ever was made, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it grants a <hi>New</hi> and <hi>Old</hi> Popery ſomewhere, though it be not ſo honeſt, as to confeſs it where it is. Becauſe he was reſolved not to find it where Mr. <hi>Brueys</hi> did, and where it is to be found, he would find it where it never was, <hi>viz.</hi> in the <hi>Conceit of our Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers.</hi> But neither dos Mr. <hi>Bruey</hi>'s arguing ſuppoſe that our Fore-fathers had any ſuch Conceit, but the quite contrary, nor is it in it ſelf true that they had; For there was no ſuch Diſtinction going in their Days, nor occaſion for it. The Reaſon why our Fore-fathers never underſtood Popery, as it is now underſtood by Monſieur <hi>Brueys</hi> and the new Converts, is, becauſe the Biſhop of <hi>Meaux</hi>'s Fore-fathers never explain'd it, as 'tis explain'd now by him, and ſome few others that have taken the hint from him. And this New Expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion muſt have made a New Popery according to that Gentleman, becauſe the whole Force of his Argument to perſuade his Old Friends to turn Papiſts lies evidently in that.</p>
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:60867:42"/>
            <p>He ſays indeed, That <hi>if their Proteſtant Forefathers had believed things to be as in effect they were, and are now propoſed, they would never have ſeparated from the Communion of the Church.</hi> In which words I acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that he leſſens the Difference between the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer and Later Expoſitions of Popery, as much as ever he can: Which no Man will wonder at, who conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders that he is a Convert. But 'tis plain that he makes the Difference to be the Reaſon why on the one ſide their Forefathers went off from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and why on the other ſide themſelves ought now to return to it. And this I am ſure is <hi>in effect</hi> to confeſs an <hi>Old</hi> and a <hi>New</hi> Popery; and not only a more clear and intelligible way of expounding the very ſame things, which the Biſhop of <hi>Meaux</hi> has got above all that were before him: Unleſs the Vindicator will ſay, That their Forefathers, as well as ours, were ſo ſtupid, that they could not ſee, either the one what Doctrines they held, or the other what they rejected; but were ſtill playing at Blindman's-buff about Notions which they could not make one another underſtand, becauſe they were not able to expreſs them as they ought to have been expreſſed: Which I am confident Mr. <hi>Brueys</hi> will never ſay, and perhaps not the Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cator neither; tho, without ſaying it, he muſt in ſpite of his Heart find a New and Old Popery acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged by that Gentleman, and that there was no oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion for that diſtinction till theſe happy Days of ours.</p>
            <p>But for the Vindicator to find in Mr. <hi>Brueys</hi>'s words a New and an Old Popery charged upon the Conceits of our Forefathers, is ſo very ridiculous, and utterly inconſiſtent with his Argument to perſuade us to put <hi>Matters into the ſame State in which they were</hi> before, by reuniting to the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> that any one
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:60867:43"/>may ſee he was hard put to it to make this Teſtimony nothing to the purpoſe, becauſe, rather than fail, he would make Nonſenſe of that Gentleman's Arguing, where his Purpoſe is as clear, and his Senſe as intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible, as a Man would deſire it to be.</p>
            <p>He anſwers next to what was obſerved again from Father <hi>Craſſet;</hi> but we will conſider what belongs to him by it ſelf, and in the mean time go on with the Converts.</p>
            <p>The next produced was Monſieur <hi>Ranchin,</hi> who confeſſed a New Popery more boldly and roundly than Mr. <hi>Brueys</hi> did. The Vindicator therefore ſlurs off his Teſtimony with ſaying only this:
<note place="margin">Pag. 4.</note> 
               <hi>The Defender has ſhewn of what Credit ſuch a Perſons Authority is, who weighed things ſo little, as to ſell his Religion for Money and Preferments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this is not ſo eaſily to be ſet aſide. For, if he <hi>ſold his Religion,</hi> as there is too great reaſon to fear he did; yet his Teſtimony to the Diſtinction between <hi>Old</hi> and <hi>New</hi> Popery is a very good one, and an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anſwerable Proof of what the Defender ſaid, That the Diſtinction was not of his own making, but that in effect he found it made to his hands amongſt the Biſhop of <hi>Meaux</hi>'s Converts.</p>
            <p>Men often change their Religion for Worldly Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts; but I think they never ſay ſo, and that becauſe they would ſtill keep their Credit. For which reaſon, if they pretend ſuch Motives to the Change they have made, as are Matters of Fact eaſie to be judged of, they will not be ſo careleſs of their Reputation, as to pretend thoſe things which the World can bear wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, againſt. Therefore ſince Mr. <hi>Ranchin</hi> laid his Change upon the great Difference between Old and New Popery, there is no reaſon to queſtion, but whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:60867:43"/>this was the principal Cauſe of his Converſion or not, yet ſuch a Difference was commonly believed: nay, and that the Alteration in the Biſhop of <hi>Meaux</hi>'s way of expounding Popery, from what had been in former Times, and from the Belief and Practice of the <hi>Tartuffs,</hi> and the <hi>People</hi> that now are, was indeed notorious. For otherwiſe he had taken a better way for his Reputation, to pretend that he had been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced by Old or by New Arguments, of the Truth of that Doctrine, which the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> conſtantly and univerſally held, than to ſay that he was enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by a New Expoſition, no leſs needful for the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of <hi>Catholics,</hi> than for the Converſion of <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants.</hi> For whether ſuch an Expoſition made any no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table difference in Doctrine from what went for Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery before, is a Matter that they can eaſily diſcern, who perhaps are not ſo good Judges of a Diſputation for Popery or againſt it. If therefore Monſieur <hi>Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chin</hi> was as careful of his Credit, as he was ſollicitous for Means to live like a Perſon of Quality, he no doubt was very ſure that the World was ſufficiently aware of a notable Difference between the Old Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the New Popery of the Biſhop of <hi>Meaux:</hi> And it was frivolouſly done of the Vindicator to refuſe his Teſtimony, becauſe the Defender was afraid his Worldly Intereſts had too great an Influence in the Change.</p>
            <p>Really if theſe Men ſerve their New Converts in this faſhion, it will mightily diſcourage them. They have ſweetned and gilded Popery for them, to make it go down the better; and yet they will not allow them to ſay what it was that made them ſwallow it with little or no ſtraining. Tho Eaſe, Honour, and Wealth did effectually determine them, yet they ſhould
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:60867:44"/>be permitted to tell their Friends what made the Change ſomewhat eaſie, <hi>viz.</hi> that which theſe Men deſigned ſhould do it: Or elſe our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and Vindicators may ſpoil their Market here, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they have well begun to bid for Converts. And this Inconvenience may preſently follow, that thoſe who have yielded to them upon New Terms, will begin to ſuſpect that their Inſtructers mean to bring them into the Condition of the <hi>Tartuffs</hi> and the <hi>Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> in due time, ſince they will neither themſelves ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge that there is ſuch a Difference, nor ſo much as ſuffer their Converts to make any words of it, but fall to reproaching them when they do ſo.</p>
            <p>The ſame Reply may ſerve to the Vindicator's Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception againſt Mr.
<note place="margin">Pag. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Pawlet,</hi> who <hi>becauſe he made his Conſcience comply with his Intereſt, is no fit Man to be brought in as one of the Defender's Witneſſes for ſuch an odious Accuſation.</hi> So ſays the Vindicator. But Mr. <hi>Paw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let</hi> was not the leſs <hi>fit</hi> Man for that: For altho Inſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity does by no means qualifie a Man to be a <hi>Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> yet there are Caſes in which the Teſtimony of an Inſincere Man cannot reaſonably be refuſed; that is, when his Intereſt does manifeſtly oblige him to ſpeak the Truth. Such is the preſent Caſe. For had there been no good ground for this Diſtinction be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Old and New Popery, as theſe Men would now perſuade us there is not, Mr. <hi>Pawlet,</hi> by uſing that Diſtinction, could not but know, that in ſtead of covering his own Inſincerity, he had more openly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed himſelf for a Knave.</p>
            <p>He calls this Charge of an <hi>Old</hi> and a <hi>New</hi> Popery an <hi>Odious Accuſation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 4.</note> as the Diſtinction it ſelf but a little before was <hi>That Odious Diſtinction.</hi> But he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets that this Diſtinction, as Odious as it is, is uſed
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:60867:44"/>by thoſe of his own Communion, and who being Converts, their Teſtimony is ſo much the more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable. They cannot be preſumed to diſtinguiſh thus for the prejudice of their Converters, nor to make the Diſtinction a matter of <hi>Accuſation</hi> againſt them, as the Vindicator very poorly inſinuates. They uſe it to defend themſelves againſt the Expoſtulations of thoſe whom they have forſaken; and the nature of their Defence implies not only that they believe what they ſay in this Caſe, but that they had reaſon to believe it. For if it were altogether a Dream of theirs or ours, that there are two ſorts of Popery in the Communion of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, they might as well have defended their Revolt by pretending that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> requires not the Veneration of Images, or the Invocation of Saints in any ſenſe at all, or any other ſuch thing as notoriouſly Falſe as that would be.</p>
            <p>As to the Inhabitants of <hi>Montauban,</hi> that became Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts too upon M. <hi>de Meaux</hi>'s Principles, he ſays, That <hi>their Acknowledgment is no convincing Proof that there was truly an Old and New Popery, excepting in their Imaginations.</hi> But their Teſtimony, and the former Teſtimonies, are I hope a convincing Proof, that the Defender did not make this Diſtinction, but that it was in effect made to his hand even by the Biſhop of <hi>Meaux</hi>'s Converts: Which is the thing this Man ſhould have ſpoken to, but that every Mans Caſe will not bear Pertinence in his Anſwers.</p>
            <p>But I have ſhewn him by the way, that theſe Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies are a Terrible Argument of the <hi>Thing,</hi> and that there is cauſe for ſuch a Diſtinction as this, which, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I have done, I ſhall make as evident as the cauſe of another thing is, <hi>viz.</hi> Why the Vindicator is not able to bear the mention of it.</p>
            <pb n="78" facs="tcp:60867:45"/>
            <p>His harping upon the Odiouſneſs of this <hi>Diſtinction</hi> and of this <hi>Accuſation,</hi> does but give us juſt occaſion to ſay, that becauſe it was neceſſary in theſe times for ſome of them to bring in a New Popery, they muſt needs count it an <hi>Odious</hi> thing in us to put them in mind of the <hi>Old</hi> one.</p>
            <p>But it ſeems that if we had ſaid nothing of it, they had been little the nearer; for the Converts themſelves have proclaim'd the <hi>Odious</hi> buſineſs; who, altho they were to be ſeduced by the inviting Appearance of a New Popery, and ſome other <hi>New Popery-Motives,</hi> not altogether ſo Sweet and Gentle, were not yet to be ſo far truſted with the Secret of this Affair, as to be told that they muſt conceal it from the World.</p>
            <p>Theſe men, no doubt, could have wiſhed, that the Converts and we had kept their Counſel, and left them to be the Firſt Diſcoverers of it, after that happy Work was done every where, which they call <hi>Converſion.</hi> If they expected this, it was a vain preſumption. But whatever they imagined at firſt, they cannot endure to be told now, that the Trick was invented too late, and diſcovered too ſoon to do all thoſe Wonders, which they deſigned by it. And ſo much for the Vindication of the Diſtinction of Old and New Popery, by the Teſtimony of the <hi>Converts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Defender touched upon Monſieur <hi>Imbert</hi>'s Story, which alſo clearly ſhewed the ſame Diſtinction going amongſt <hi>Romaniſts</hi> themſelves, before the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender inſiſted upon it.</p>
            <p>The only Queſtion, as to the evidence of this Inſtance, is, whether Mr. <hi>Imbert</hi> was oppreſſed by his Dioceſan the Archbiſhop of <hi>Bourdeaux,</hi> for following Monſieur <hi>de Meaux</hi>'s Expoſition, in declaring that not the <hi>Wood</hi> of the Croſs, but <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> who ſuffered upon it, was
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:60867:45"/>to be Adored in the <hi>Good-Friday</hi> Service. The proof that has been made of this is ſo good, that the Vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor denies not the Fact, but contents himſelf not to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs it. He ſaies indeed, <hi>The Biſhop tells of Extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancies committed in the Church by Monſieur</hi> Imbert; <hi>and I ſuppoſe, if it were worth while, he could prove them to you.</hi> But, in Conſcience, was it not <hi>worth while</hi> to <hi>prove</hi> them, or at leaſt to <hi>name</hi> them, and to ſay what they were? Was it not Mr. <hi>Imbert,</hi> who, in his Letter to the Biſhop of <hi>Meaux,</hi> appealed to the <hi>Proceſs</hi> againſt him,
<note place="margin">Deſence of Exp. p. 126.</note> and <hi>defied his Enemies to reproach him for his Life and Manners, or for any other Doctrine than that of his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip?</hi> Did he not publiſh a <hi>Factum</hi> of his Caſe all to the ſame purpoſe? And can any other reaſon be given why it <hi>is not</hi> confuted in the Face of the World, but becauſe it <hi>cannot?</hi> Sure I am, that if it could have been done, the Biſhop might with leſs pain have diſproved it, than it hath coſt him from time to time to ſhuffle it off, in which labour he has ſo viſibly added Inſincerity to Inſincerity. Can the Vindicator think, that it was not worth while for the Biſhop to defend his Reputation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his Inferior, as Mr. <hi>Imbert</hi> indeed is? But the Biſhop is now brought upon the Stage of the World for this matter, and I muſt tell his Vindicator, that <hi>Imbert</hi> being not only the Biſhops Inferior, but a man oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed too by the Authority of the Archbiſhop of <hi>Bourdeaux,</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Meaux</hi>'s Friend; the World does more undoubtedly believe, that he delivered nothing but plain Truth in his <hi>Factum,</hi> becauſe if he had in the leaſt ſwerved from it, he had thereby expoſed himſelf yet more to the power of that Greatneſs which oppreſs'd him, to add to his Sufferings now with ſome Colour of Juſtice. Whatever was at firſt inſinuated by the Biſhop, it now appears that <hi>Imbert</hi> was no Fool, unleſs in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:60867:46"/>that the Biſhop was in good earneſt in his Expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition. But the World will forgive him that, when it will not ſo eaſily forgive the Expoſitor.</p>
            <p>What ſhould I ſay more? the Vindicator himſelf has in effect acknowledged, that it was worth while to make the pretended Extravagancies, of the unfortunate <hi>Imbert</hi> appear: For he confeſſes that the ſevere Reflexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which the Defender makes againſt the Proceedings of the Archbiſhop of <hi>Bourdeaux,</hi> are made <hi>juſtly enough</hi> if <hi>Imbert</hi> ſaid <hi>the whole Truth, and nothing but the Truth:</hi> which is as much as to ſay, that it was <hi>worth while,</hi> to ſhew that the World ought not to think ſo <hi>ſeverely</hi> of the Archbiſhop, as it certainly would, if <hi>Imbert</hi> were believed. But the Vindicator's Conſequence is as abſurd as poſſible, that <hi>this will make unbyaſs'd perſons think that</hi> Imbert <hi>was not juſt in the delivery of the matter:</hi> For becauſe one Story is good till another is told, unbyaſs'd Perſons muſt think that <hi>Imbert</hi> was very juſt in the Relation; ſince it ſo nearly concerned the Archbiſhop to have it diſproved, and yet he never went about it. As for the Biſhop of <hi>Meaux,</hi> it concerned him much more, who has not only forſaken this poor Man, that ſuffers for nothing, but <hi>conforming to the Biſhops Expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition,</hi> but has alſo endeavoured to take away his good Name; and without offering any colour of proof, has added Reproaches to his other Afflictions.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, the Biſhop has, in all appearance, ſaid for himſelf what he is able: But the pretended <hi>Extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancies</hi> are yet to be named; unleſs the Vindicator will inſiſt upon that, for which the Defender has brought Cardinal <hi>Capiſucchi,</hi> to acquit Monſieur <hi>Imbert</hi> and to condemn the Biſhop: Which I deſire the Reader to take ſpecial notice of in the Anſwer to the Biſhop of <hi>Meaux</hi>'s Letter, <hi>p.</hi> 41.42. But I forbid the Vindicator
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:60867:46"/>ever to ſay one word about it, or to offer the leaſt Reply to what I add concerning it: That 'tis ſuch a blot to his Biſhop, and to his expounding Deſign, as will ſtick upon them, till they are ſo happy as to be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten.</p>
            <p>But the Vindicator was ſo ſenſible of the Evidence of <hi>Imbert</hi>'s Story, that he thought fit to make an <hi>If</hi> of the main part of it, and ſo to ſpeak to the Suppoſition. <hi>If the Curate,</hi> ſaies he, <hi>cried out as</hi> Imbert <hi>accuſes him,</hi> The Wood, The Wood, <hi>he was as much in the wrong as your ſelf,</hi> meaning the Defender: That is, the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate miſtook the meaning of the Church, as much as the Defender did. But the Vindicator ſhould have gone on thus: And <hi>if</hi> the Archbiſhop of <hi>Bourdeaux</hi> cauſed Proceſs to be made againſt <hi>Imbert</hi> for crying out <hi>Not the Wood, but</hi> Jeſus Chriſt; then the <hi>Archbiſhop</hi> mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtook the meaning of the Church as much as the <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate.</hi> And <hi>if</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Meaux</hi> abetted the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop and forſook <hi>Imbert,</hi> he was more to blame than either the Curate or the Archbiſhop; not indeed for <hi>miſtaking,</hi> but for betraying the pretended Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Church, which he had ſo publickly own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before.</p>
            <p>Now, not to enquire by what Authority the Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cator pronounced the Curate to be <hi>in the wrong,</hi> ſince the Archbiſhop of <hi>Bourdeaux</hi> thought <hi>Imbert</hi> to be in the wrong, and the Curate in the right: This at leaſt is enough for the Defender, that there are two ſorts of Popery amongſt them, as to this matter of <hi>adoring the Croſs:</hi> One, that of the <hi>Curate</hi> and the <hi>Archbiſhop;</hi> ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that of <hi>Imbert</hi> and the <hi>Vindicator;</hi> between both which, the Biſhop of <hi>Meaux,</hi> hath, by this unhappy accident, been conſtrained to play faſt and looſe. Here, therefore, if I had the Repreſenters Talent, I
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:60867:47"/>might cry out, where is the <hi>Calumny?</hi> Where is the <hi>Miſrepreſentation?</hi> Where is the Falſhood in charging the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> with two ſorts of Popery, when the matter of Fact is ſo evident, that <hi>Proceſs</hi> has been iſſued out by the <hi>Old</hi> Popery againſt the <hi>New</hi> in the Proceedings of the <hi>Archbiſhop</hi> againſt <hi>Imbert.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the Vindicator ſaies, That the Curate was <hi>in the wrong,</hi> for crying out, <hi>The Wood, The Wood;</hi> and whatever the Biſhop of <hi>Meaux</hi> himſelf ſaies, his <hi>Expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition</hi> muſt ſay what the Vindicator does. But now poor <hi>Imbert</hi> ſaid the ſame: And yet, tho they all agree in ſaying the ſame thing; ſuch is the hard Fate of ſome above others; the Biſhop and his Vindicator flouriſh and are applauded, for ſaying what <hi>Imbert</hi> ſaid; but <hi>Imbert</hi> ſuffers for ſaying no other thing than what the Biſhops Expoſition ſaid before him, and his Vindicator after him.</p>
            <p>Upon which, no <hi>unbyaſs'd</hi> man can reflect, but he muſt acknowledge, not only that there is a New and an Old Popery amongſt them; but withal, That the <hi>New</hi> one is ſet up for nothing but to decoy us into the <hi>Old</hi> one. For let the Vindicator tell me, why <hi>Imbert</hi> has been ſo ſeverely treated for ſaying that the Curate <hi>was in the wrong,</hi> but that he ſeemed to be in <hi>good earneſt,</hi> and in truth, would not have the <hi>Wood</hi> to be Adored. And if others ſay the ſame thing, and are yet approved, what other reaſon can be given for the Difference, but that they are underſtood to be <hi>in Jeſt,</hi> as to the matter which they affirm, and in earneſt only, as to the end they aim at; which is, in good time, to make us A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorers of <hi>the Wood,</hi> according to the ſtrain of Old and True Popery. The Expoſition was framed to catch <hi>Proteſtants:</hi> It was <hi>Imbert</hi>'s miſtake, to think it deſign'd for the Reformation of <hi>Papiſts.</hi> For which reaſon,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:60867:47"/>Monſieur <hi>Ranchin</hi> would be adviſed to have a care how he talks of the Expoſition being no leſs needful for the Inſtruction of the Catholics, than of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed.</p>
            <p>The Defender ſaid, That <hi>Imbert</hi>'s Caſe was enough to clear him from the Charge of <hi>Calumny</hi> and <hi>Falſifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,</hi> in that <hi>Account</hi> he gave of their <hi>Good-Friday</hi> Service; and in Tranſlating thoſe words, <hi>Ecce Lig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num Crucis, Venite Adoremus;</hi> Behold the Wood of the Croſs, come let us Adore <hi>It. For,</hi> ſays the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender, not only the <hi>Curate,</hi> but the <hi>Archbiſhop thought there was no Calumny in it:</hi> And he would not be ſo uncharitable as to wiſh the Vindicator the like Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction of it, that <hi>Imbert</hi> has met with. But ſince this Man goes on ſtill to cry <hi>Calumny</hi> and <hi>Falſification,</hi> I may without breach of Charity wiſh Monſieur <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert</hi> out of <hi>Durance,</hi> and the Vindicator in his room, who without queſtion would get out again preſently.</p>
            <p>The Vindicator ſays, That <hi>the Falſe Tranſlation is ſo manifeſt, that he needs not make any more words of it.</hi> I ſay, If there were nothing to juſtifie the Defender's Tranſlation, but the <hi>Antiphone</hi> it ſelf in its full length, that were enough. <hi>Behold the Wood of the Croſs, upon which the Saviour of the World did hang: Come, let us Adore.</hi> Adore what? <hi>It,</hi> ſays the Defender: <hi>Him,</hi> ſays the Vindicator. Now in Common Senſe the <hi>Quire</hi> invite one another to <hi>Adore</hi> that which the <hi>Prieſt</hi> ſhews them with a <hi>Behold.</hi> Surely he that ſhould ſay, Behold a Houſe by the Wood-ſide; come, let us go in: or, Behold a Dinner upon the Table; come, let us eat: or, Behold <hi>Virgil</hi> amongſt the Poets; come, let us read; would take it ill to be underſtood of any thing, but going into that Houſe, or eating of that Dinner, or reading of that Book. But if indeed
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:60867:48"/>there were any thing in that Service to oblige a Man to depart from the common Conſtruction, as to thoſe Words, and to apply the Adoration not to the <hi>Wood</hi> which the People are called to <hi>Behold,</hi> but to him that ſuffered upon the Croſs, whom they cannot be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, then the Defender would be in an ill Caſe. But if the Rubric upon this occaſion does expreſly make the Wood the Object of Adoration, then the Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cator is in a worſe caſe, who has both the natural Conſtruction of the Words, and the Circumſtances of the Place againſt him.</p>
            <p>Once more therefore, and but once, the Reader ſhall by ſome part of the Rubric judge of the Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty of this Man; and the Vindicator ſhall have the pleaſure of imagining all the while, what the Reader muſt think of him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Afterwards, i. e.</hi> after thrice ſinging of the <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phone,</hi> and the Proſtrations of all upon thrice ſhewing the Croſs, <hi>the Prieſt alone bears the Croſs to the place prepared for it, before the Altar, and kneeling he lays it there. By and by putting off his Shoes, he comes to ADORE THE CROSS, thrice bending his Knees before he kiſſes it.—After a while the Miniſters of the Altar, and then other Clerks and Laics, with thrice bended Knees, as was now ſaid, ADORE THE CROSS.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Miſſale Rom. Feria VI. in Paraſc.</note> 
               <hi>In the mean time, while the ADORA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TION OF THF CROSS is made, the Expoſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations and other Hymns are ſung which follow, either all or ſome of them, as the greater or leſſer number of Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers requireth.</hi> One of the <hi>Antiphones</hi> ſung in <hi>Common</hi> is that which begins, <hi>WE ADORE THY CROSS, O LORD.</hi> And to make all ſure, the <hi>Rubric</hi> that cloſes this Ceremony, and paſſes to other things, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins thus: <hi>Towards the end of the ADORATION OF
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:60867:48"/>THE CROSS, the Candles are lighted upon the Altar,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Yet ſays the Vindicator, <hi>Let us Adore IT,</hi> is a <hi>Falſe Tranſlation;</hi> nay, 'tis <hi>ſo manifeſt, that he needs not make any more words of it.</hi> That it is not Falſe as to the <hi>Senſe,</hi> is <hi>ſo manifeſt</hi> both by the <hi>Antiphone</hi> and the <hi>Rubric;</hi> nor as to the Words by the uſe of our <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh,</hi> which requires the repetition of the thing by a Pronoun, more than the <hi>Latin</hi> does: This, I ſay, is ſo manifeſt, that I will never make any more words about it with the Vindicator, or any one elſe in his behalf.</p>
            <p>And this is the Old ſtanding Propery of the <hi>Roman</hi> Miſſal; by which any body may ſee, that the Curate had reaſon to cry out, <hi>The Wood, the Wood;</hi> and the Vindicator none, to ſay, that the Curate was <hi>in the wrong,</hi> unleſs by the help of that odious Diſtinction, which indeed will ſet all right: For the Curate was in the <hi>wrong</hi> as to New Popery, but very much in the right, with reſpect to the Old.</p>
            <p>The Defender again juſtified his Diſtinction by <hi>The wholeſom Advices of the Bleſſed Virgin to her indiſcreet Worſhippers,</hi> and by the Fate which that Book met with. For thoſe Advices did not only of themſelves intimate that there were ſome in the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> who needed them, but by the Oppoſition that was made againſt it, they ſhewed too, that there were ſome Practices condemned there, which the prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing part of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church could not bear the Condemnation of. The Vindicator indeed would make us believe,
<note place="margin">Pag. 5.</note> that the Church is <hi>not to anſwer for the Extravagancies</hi> condemned in thoſe Advices, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>ſhe has always taken care to inſtruct</hi> the People <hi>better.</hi> But he regards not what he ſays. I pray what care did ſhe take to <hi>inſtruct them better,</hi> when Monſieur
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:60867:49"/>
               <hi>Widenfelt,</hi> who took a little honeſt Care about it, was ſerved as Father <hi>Craſſet</hi> aſſures us he was; when the <hi>Holy See condemned him,</hi> when <hi>Spain</hi> baniſhed him, and <hi>forbad the Reading and Printing of his Book;</hi> and in a word, when the <hi>Learned of all Nations</hi> were ſaid to <hi>condemn him;</hi> and all this but for adviſing the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple better? The Vindicator calls this a <hi>Scandalous In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuation,</hi> and ſays, that <hi>the Defender knows it to be ſuch,</hi> and talks as if <hi>he had proved</hi> it, without ſaying a word where he has done ſo. And yet Father <hi>Craſſet</hi> pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed it no longer ago than in the Year 1679. in the Preface to his <hi>La Veritable Devotion, &amp;c.</hi> What ſhall we do with this Man, who grows rude when he has nothing to ſay to the Argument, and will then have us to ſpeak againſt our Conſciences, when he either does ſo himſelf, or talks of things without knowledge?</p>
            <p>He ſays, the <hi>Defender has given us in another place, it may be thro forgetfulneſs, a ſhort Anſwer to this;</hi> 
               <q>They who oppoſe that Book of wholeſom Advices, are not therefore Enemies to every one of thoſe Particulars.</q> But how is this an Anſwer to it? For they muſt oppoſe it for ſomething or other that <hi>M. de Meaux</hi> is bound to anſwer for. For <hi>M. Wid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nfelt</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows as much to the Bleſſed Virgin as <hi>M. de Meaux</hi> does; and <hi>M. de Meaux</hi> would be thought to deny all that <hi>Widenfelt</hi> denies to her. When <hi>Craſſet</hi> is at leiſure to tell us what thoſe Particulars are, which <hi>he,</hi> and the <hi>Pope,</hi> and the Learned of all Nations do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn, we ſhall then know more particularly, what we are undoubtedly aſſured of in the general, <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>Craſſet</hi> brings the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal</hi> Church againſt the Expoſition of the Biſhop of <hi>Meaux:</hi> For I ſay it again, <hi>M. Widenfelt</hi> allows as much Honour to the Bleſſed Virgin, as the Biſhop's Expoſition does.</p>
            <pb n="87" facs="tcp:60867:49"/>
            <p>The Conſequence of all this is clear; if the Biſhop has expounded <hi>Popery</hi> to us, as they ſay he has; and if for all that the Biſhop's Expoſition be, as Father <hi>Craſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet</hi> aſſures us <hi>Widenfelt</hi>'s Advices are, an <hi>Outrage</hi> to the whole Church; then of neceſſity there muſt be two Poperies among them, and theſe not only different from, but <hi>outrageouſly,</hi> contrary to one another.</p>
            <p>And here I will take notice of the Vindicator's Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception to <hi>Craſſet</hi>'s Teſtimony for an <hi>Old Popery.</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Craſſet,</hi> ſaies he, <hi>is again brought upon the Stage, for defending what he himſelf does not acknowledge to be an Article of our Faith, and therefore belongs not to what you call</hi> Popery <hi>at all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Man would fain ſay ſomething, if he knew what: Does nothing then <hi>belong to Popery at all,</hi> which <hi>Father</hi> Craſſet <hi>does not acknowledge to be an Article of Faith?</hi> I am ſomewhat ſure that Father <hi>Craſſet</hi> will not acknowledge it to be an Article of Faith, That no more Honour is to be given to the Virgin than what Mr. <hi>Widenfelt,</hi> or M. <hi>de Meaux</hi> allow to be given to her; nay, inſtead of <hi>defending,</hi> we are very ſure, that he has oppoſed that Doctrine. And does not the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop's Expoſition of the <hi>Catholic Faith,</hi> in this point, belong to Popery at all?</p>
            <p>But letting this paſs at preſent, Fa. <hi>Craſſet</hi> defends in groſs what <hi>Widenfelt</hi> condemns, and does withal, defend it as the Doctrine of the Univerſal Church, to what he took <hi>Widenfelt</hi>'s Book to be an <hi>Outrage.</hi> And if <hi>Craſſet</hi> believes what he defends, not only to belong to Popery, but to be the true and genuine Popery of the Church, this Man hurts himſelf, and not us, by doing all he can, to prove that <hi>Craſſet</hi>'s Doctrine cannot <hi>belong to Popery at all.</hi> This is what we ſay, that ſome of them call that Popery, which others deny to be
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:60867:50"/>ſo, and that what was heretofore univerſally maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as Popery, and is ſo maintained by the moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable, as well as the moſt numerous Party of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church now, is by ſome others that we have to do with, rejected, as not <hi>belonging to Popery at all.</hi> Which makes good what the Defender ſaid, that <hi>'tis not in our Calumnies, that this reflecting Diſtinction is to be found, but in the real diſagreement of thoſe of their own Communion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But becauſe theſe Men are always flying to the <hi>Churches Sence,</hi> to make them and the Old Papiſts <hi>One,</hi> though all the World ſees that they are divided about this Queſtion, <hi>What is Popery?</hi> therefore the Defender was deſirous to know, <hi>what at laſt this thing called the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches Sence is, and how we may come to the knowledge of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To both parts of this Queſtion, the Vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor condeſcended, tho with ſome frowning to return an Anſwer.</p>
            <p>Firſt,
<note place="margin">Pag. 5.</note> ſaies he, <hi>the Churches Sence in our Caſe, is that which ſhe delivers as a Doctrine of Faith, or a neceſſary Practice.</hi> I ſhould be too troubleſome to him, to ask upon this occaſion, what he ſhould mean by thoſe Words, <hi>In our caſe,</hi> and by ſome other Expreſſions that occur in the Interpretations of this Anſwer. I ſhall therefore take his Anſwer without any exception to it; that <hi>the Churches Sence, in our caſe, is what ſhe delivers as a Doctrine of Faith, or a neceſſary Practice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But how ſhall we come to the knowledge of this Sence?
<note place="margin">Pag. 6.</note> To this he anſwers; <hi>By the Voice of the Church, in her General and Approved Councils, and by her univerſally practiſing ſuch things as neceſſary;</hi> That is to ſay,</p>
            <pb n="89" facs="tcp:60867:50"/>
            <p n="1">1. We are to know what ſhe delivers as a Doctrine of Faith, by her Voice in her General and Approved Councils.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We are to know what ſhe delivers as a neceſſary Practice, by her univerſally practiſing ſuch things as neceſſary.</p>
            <p>This I take to be his meaning, and to theſe two Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, ſome little I have to ſay, with the Vindicator's good leave: And firſt of the former.</p>
            <p n="1">I. Where I deſire him not to take it ill, if I ask him one Queſtion or two, with ſome under Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions which cannot be ſpared; for if he has no mind to anſwer them, he may let it alone. The Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion is this?</p>
            <p>
               <q>Whether there be no way to know what the Church delivers as a Doctrine of Faith, but by her Voice in her General and Approved Councils.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The reaſon of the Queſtion is this, Becauſe if there be another way, and if the Gentlemen of the Old Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery ſhould chance to prove their Doctrine to be the Churches Sence that way, the Vindicator will be at a loſs again, and the Sence of the Church in Council will do him little Service in thoſe Points, where, it may be, Councils are ſilent, if the Sence of the Church out of Council be plainly and loudly againſt him and his Party.</p>
            <p>If the Vindicator then ſhould ſay, That tho the Church has a Sence of Doctrines of Faith out of Council; yet that Sence cannot, or at leaſt is never delivered but by her Voice in General Councils. Then I have one o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Queſtion to put, which will break out into a few more, but which he who hath conſidered theſe things very well, will make no difficulty to anſwer.</p>
            <pb n="90" facs="tcp:60867:51"/>
            <p>This Queſtion is, <q>How the Churches Sence came to be known concerning Doctrines of Faith, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore any <hi>General</hi> and <hi>Approved Councils</hi> delivered them for ſuch?</q>
            </p>
            <p>Which Queſtion will appear to be a very rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable one, if he will pleaſe to read theſe that follow.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Whether <hi>Doctrines of Faith</hi> be not the <hi>ſame</hi> now that they were from the Beginning?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Whether the <hi>Sence of the Church</hi> concerning theſe Doctrines has not been always the ſame?</p>
            <p n="3">3. Whether the Church therefore had not the ſame Sence of them, before they were delivered by her Voice in General and Approved Councils, that ſhe had afterwards? Or, Whether ſhe had one Sence, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered another? And then, as I ſaid at firſt;</p>
            <p n="4">4. If ſhe had the ſame Sence before it was ſo deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, that ſhe had when ſhe delivered it, and after ſhe delivered it; How came that Sence to be known before?</p>
            <p>This, I think, is plain enough; but if it be not, I will try to make it plainer. Therefore,</p>
            <p n="1">1. We ſay with the <hi>Romaniſt,</hi> That it is a Doctrine of Faith, that <hi>The Son is of the ſame Subſtance with the Father.</hi> But this Doctrine was never delivered in a Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral and Approved Council, before the Firſt Council of <hi>Nice;</hi> as it was impoſſible it ſhould, becauſe that was the Firſt General Council. I would know of the Vindicator, whether the Churches Sence concerning that Doctrine, was not to be known before, and how it was to be known?</p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>Romaniſts</hi> ſay, That 'tis a Doctrine of Faith, That in <hi>the Euchariſt, the Subſtance of the Bread, is tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into the Subſtance of Chriſt's Body, and the Subſtance
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:60867:51"/>of the Wine into the Subſtance of his Blood.</hi> But this was never delivered in any <hi>pretended General</hi> and <hi>Approved</hi> Council, as we are very ſure, before the Council of <hi>Lateran,</hi> under <hi>Innocent</hi> III. I would know of the Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicator, whether the Church had the ſame Sence of this <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> before that <hi>Lateran</hi> Council, which 'tis ſaid to have had ſince? and whether that Sence of the Church was known? and if ſo, then <hi>how</hi> it was known?</p>
            <p>I have given the Vindicator two Inſtances, One of a Doctrine of Faith, for which we contend no leſs than the <hi>Roman</hi> Church; and as we think, to better pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe: Another of a Doctrine which that Church ſays is <hi>of Faith,</hi> tho we ſay, it deſtroys All Faith; and theſe two in behalf of all that are Real, and of all that are by them <hi>pretended</hi> to be Doctrines of Faith. For till I am better informed by the Vindicator in anſwer to the foreſaid Queſtions, I ſay of all the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines of both kinds, that there ſhould be ſome way to come to the Churches Sence about theſe things, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhe <hi>delivered</hi> her <hi>Sence</hi> of them, in the <hi>Voice of Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral and Approved Councils.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This I ſhall preſume, till he acquaints me otherwiſe; and if he does not yet underſtand which way theſe Queſtions drive, I will now tell him. Let him keep to his Principles, and ſhew me, by what way the Churches Sence came to be known concerning <hi>Doctrines of Faith,</hi> before they were delivered by the Voice of General and Approved Councils; and then let him leave it to me, to ſhew him by the ſame way, that Old Popery, as we call it, has been the Sence of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> till theſe <hi>expounding</hi> and <hi>repreſenting</hi> Days of ours: Nay, and that Father <hi>Craſſet</hi> ſhall prove by the ſame way, that it is now the Sence of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:60867:52"/>whatever ſome few Men of that Communion may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to the contrary.</p>
            <p>And when I have done this, the Vindicator ſhall by me be never contradicted, while he on the other ſide proves the Senſe of the Church to be quite different from what Father <hi>Craſſet</hi> in his way proves to be ſo: For moſt undoubtedly he thereby does our Work for us, and enables us to prove, that there muſt of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity be two Church-Senſes betwixt them, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently two ſorts of Popery, an <hi>Old</hi> Popery, and a <hi>New</hi> Popery.</p>
            <p>Whereas therefore the Vindicator ſays, <hi>Till you can prove by the expreſs Words of a General Approved Council, that what you term Old Popery was delivered as a Doctrine of Faith— all you ſay will avail nothing.</hi> I would be glad to know what the Vindicator would have ſaid in behalf of Tranſubſtantiation, ſo ſome ſuch Man as <hi>Rabanus Maurus,</hi> or <hi>Bertram,</hi> or <hi>Berengarius,</hi> if he had lived in their Times, and they ſhould have ſaid to him, (tho I think in my Conſcience none of 'em would have talked ſo inſipidly) <hi>Till you can prove by the expreſs Words of a General Approved Council, that what you term the Catholic Faith concerning Chriſt's Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence in the Euchariſt, was delivered as a Doctrine of Faith, all you ſay will avail nothing.</hi> Here I will not allow that the Vindicator ſhould bring in the <hi>Doctors</hi> and <hi>Saints</hi> of the Church, who might be pretended to bear Teſtimony to the Churches <hi>Senſe</hi> in this Point: For he has forecloſed himſelf as to this Relief, and that by giving the Defender a notable Reaſon, why all he can ſay will avail him nothing, if he brings not the expreſs Words of a Council. <hi>For,</hi> ſays he, <hi>you bring only the Sentiments of Private Men, which other Members of the ſame Church condemn.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="93" facs="tcp:60867:52"/>
            <p>I have urged this Matter further than I intended at firſt, for I meant not to preſs for Anſwers to the foregoing Queſtions with much Importunity. And now I ſay no more, than that I ſhall take it very kindly of the Vindicator, if he will pleaſe to admit theſe things into his Conſideration, and enlighten me with his Thoughts about them.</p>
            <p n="2">II. I proceed in the ſecond place to ſuppoſe a very ſtrange thing, for fear the Vindicator ſhould affirm it; and that is, That nothing is to be taken for the Senſe of the Church as to <hi>Doctrines of Faith,</hi> but what ſhe declares by her Voice in <hi>General Approved</hi> Councils. For if we take the Cauſe by this Handle, the Diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction between <hi>Old</hi> and <hi>New</hi> Popery will I believe go on as roundly as it did before: And ſome Inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence too will follow in the Cloſe, to trouble the Vindicator no leſs than this <hi>Odious</hi> Diſtinction between <hi>Old</hi> and <hi>New</hi> Popery.</p>
            <p>Becauſe I would lead him fairly to the Buſineſs, I ask him in the <hi>Firſt</hi> place, Whether his Church hath delivered <hi>her Senſe</hi> concerning thoſe two Points, which he mentions upon this occaſion, by <hi>her Voice</hi> in <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral</hi> and <hi>Approved</hi> Councils, or whether ſhe has not? The two Points are the Doctrine of the <hi>Invocation of Saints,</hi> and the Doctrine of <hi>Worſhipping Images.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If ſhe has not done it, then in the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> there can be no Doctrine concerning theſe two things, which can be called <hi>a Doctrine of Faith.</hi> The Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicator therefore will ſay, I hope, that ſhe has deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered her Senſe by her Voice.</p>
            <p>And ſo I ask him in the <hi>Second</hi> place, Whether by the Doctrine which the Church delivers, he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands only ſo many <hi>Words</hi> put together, and not ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:60867:53"/>the Senſe of thoſe Words, which <hi>the Voice</hi> of the Church uſes, that is, which her General and Approved Councils have put together to expreſs their Meaning by? This is a Queſtion which the Vindicator muſt needs underſtand, becauſe I do in effect but borrow it of his Friends: For the like Queſtion has been of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten put to us by them, and particularly by his good Friend the <hi>Repreſenter,</hi> and, it may be, by himſelf, <hi>viz.</hi> Whether by the Scriptures we underſtand the <hi>Words</hi> or the <hi>Senſe?</hi> So ſay I, by the Doctrines of Faith which the Vindicator ſays are delivered by the Voice of the Church in her General Councils, Does he mean the <hi>Senſe,</hi> or the <hi>Words</hi> only of her Councils? I will for once anſwer for him, That he means the <hi>Senſe,</hi> which is contained under the Words.</p>
            <p>I ask him therefore the <hi>Third</hi> time, Whether the Senſe of thoſe Words<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which his General Councils have put together,
<note place="margin">Pag. 6.</note> be not, as he ſays, <hi>what truly we ought to mean by Popery?</hi> If I may be bold to anſwer for him once more, he muſt needs grant it. For if the Churches <hi>Doctrine of Faith</hi> be the ſame with the <hi>Senſe</hi> of her General Councils; and if that which we ought to call <hi>Popery,</hi> and to mean by <hi>Popery,</hi> be the Churches Doctrine of Faith; it will go very hard if <hi>Popery</hi> be not the <hi>Senſe</hi> of her General Councils.</p>
            <p>And now the <hi>Odious</hi> Diſtinction clears up apace, in going this way to work. For if that part of Popery which is made by Doctrines of Faith, be neither more nor leſs than the <hi>Senſe</hi> of General Councils concerning ſuch Doctrines as we <hi>Proteſtants</hi> diſclaim, it follows preſently, that the Senſe of thoſe Councils is <hi>what we ought to call</hi> Popery. And therefore,</p>
            <p n="1">1. I humbly conceive, that if there be two Parties
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:60867:53"/>in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> that are not agreed what the <hi>Senſe</hi> of her General Councils is, it follows out of hand, that ſo far they are not agreed about <hi>Popery;</hi> and that for this very good Reaſon, Becauſe the <hi>Senſe</hi> of her General Councils, and the <hi>Faith</hi> part of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, according to him, is all one, and indeed but two Expreſſions of the ſame thing.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It follows alſo, That in <hi>what Senſe ſoever</hi> either of thoſe Parties takes the Words of the Churches Councils, that Senſe is, and muſt neceſſarily be that Parties Popery; becauſe the <hi>Senſe</hi> of her Councils be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Popery,</hi> that which is to one Party the <hi>Senſe</hi> of her Councils, muſt likewiſe be <hi>Popery</hi> to that Party.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If therefore one of thoſe Parties takes the Words of her Councils in one Senſe, and another takes the ſame Words in a contradictory Senſe; then becauſe the Senſe in which the former takes thoſe Words is the Popery <hi>of</hi> or <hi>to</hi> that Party, and the Senſe of the latter is its Popery; it unavoidably follows, that there are two pretended Poperies betwixt thoſe two Parties, which are inconſiſtent with one another.</p>
            <p n="4">4. If the Senſe of one of theſe Parties was that which prevailed without Controul ever ſince the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> till very lately, and the <hi>Senſe</hi> of the other Party is therefore but of yeſterday; then of theſe two Poperies, the former muſt needs be the <hi>Old</hi> Popery, and the latter the <hi>New</hi> Popery.</p>
            <p n="5">5. So much Reaſon as we have to believe the <hi>Old</hi> Popery to be the true Senſe of the Churches Councils, rather than the <hi>New</hi> one; ſo much reaſon alſo we have to believe, that the <hi>Old</hi> Popery is the <hi>True</hi> Popery, and the <hi>New</hi> to be but an Impoſture, or a Miſtake of thoſe of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church that have of late brought it up.</p>
            <pb n="98" facs="tcp:60867:54"/>
            <p n="6">6. And laſtly, If Proteſtants did not make thoſe different Senſes for them, but each Party in that Church made them for themſelves, then this Diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of an <hi>Old</hi> and a <hi>New</hi> Popery is no Miſrepreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Falſification, or Calumny of Proteſtants, but a Diſtinction grounded upon the Real Diſagreement of Papiſts about <hi>Popery. Quod erat demonſtrandum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I think that Men were never put to it as we are, to make ſolemn proof of things that are ſo evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that they need not to be proved at all.</p>
            <p>The Council of <hi>Trent</hi> determines, That we are to <hi>fly to the Prayers, the Help, and the Aſſiſtance of the Saints.</hi> If we would know the Councils Senſe in this Matter, the <hi>Old</hi> ones will tell us, that the meaning is, we ſhould have recourſe to them for <hi>other Aids</hi> beſides their <hi>Prayers.</hi> And as one would verily take this for the meaning from the Conſtruction of the Words themſelves; ſo the Terms of Invoking the Saints which were then uſed in their Offices, and ſtill are ſo, do manifeſtly favour that Interpretation. But our New Expoſitors come and tell us, that they <hi>require no other Aid and Aſſiſtance from the Saints than their Prayers;</hi> and the Vindicator intimates, that if they did, we ſhould have <hi>ſomething to ſay againſt the Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of what they practiſe.</hi> If Popery therefore be not ſo much the Words of the Council, in which I acknowledge they all agree, as the Senſe of the Council, in which they do not agree, how is it poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible but that here are two Poperies in this matter ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced amongſt themſelves, one againſt the other?</p>
            <p>Again, The Council of <hi>Trent</hi> affirms, That <hi>due Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Veneration is to be given to Images.</hi> And therefore what one Party in that Church takes to be that due Honour, is Popery to them, becauſe 'tis the
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:60867:54"/>Senſe of the Church to that Party. And what ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther believes to be ſo, is their Popery. And here I am ſure if we find a Harmony, 'tis made up all of Diſcords. Indeed one would have thought, that the Council, by <hi>Due Honour and Veneration,</hi> had meant that Worſhip which was at that time given to Images in the <hi>Roman</hi> Church; which their Offices required, and for which their moſt celebrated Writers had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended. And this way of coming to the Senſe of the Council, muſt lead a Man to the Popery of giving the ſame Honour to the Image, that is due to the Prototype, or at leaſt an Inferior Honor, by which the Image might be ſaid to be truly and properly wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped. For the former Senſe, Cardinal <hi>Capiſucchi</hi> does at this day earneſtly contend, and very fairly argues it againſt all Oppoſers, from the Words of the Council. But the Biſhop of <hi>Meaux,</hi> and the Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenter, and the Vindicator, are as croſs to that Senſe as downright Contradiction can make them: They ſay,
<note place="margin">See Second Def. p. 31, 32, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note>
               <q>That in preſence of Images reſpect is paid to the Perſons whom they repreſent; but Images themſelves are not to be worſhipped. No, God forbid; but only uſed to put us in mind of the Original.</q> Thus they <hi>explicate the Language, i. e.</hi> give us the Senſe of their Church <hi>in her Deciſions of Faith:</hi> But ſo, I dare ſay, as it was never explicated before.</p>
            <p>However, if theſe Gentlemen believe the <hi>Senſe</hi> of the Council to be as they ſay, I wonder how it comes to paſs, that the Vindicator ſhould not acknowledge it to be Popery. For he muſt not forget, that Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery is the Senſe of the Church, which ſhe delivers by her Voice in Councils, and therefore that the Senſe of the Councils Words it truly Popery: And conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, what He and His Party take to be their Senſe, they
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:60867:55"/>muſt, in ſpite of their Hearts, confeſs, to be their Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, unleſs they care not how inconſiſtently they talk. And then I would ask the Vindicator, whether it be poſſible to reconcile his and the Biſhops Sence with Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal <hi>Capiſucchi</hi>'s, and thoſe of his way.</p>
            <p>The Truth is, the Vindicator has given up the Cauſe; for by ſaying, that we <hi>bring only the private Sentiments of Men, which other Members of the ſame Church condemn,</hi> he confeſſes, that they do in theſe things <hi>condemn one another:</hi> Which perfectly acquits us from the charge of miſrepreſenting them, when we ſay, that there are two ſorts of Popery amongſt them; by which, we never meant any thing elſe, than that one Party of them, and that the greater, does ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly contend, that that is Popery, which the other utterly diſclaims, and does therefore ſet up another <hi>Senſe</hi> of their Councils, and their publick Offices op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to that of the former.</p>
            <p>As for his calling the Sentiments of the oppoſite Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, <hi>Private Sentiments.</hi> If he means that they keep their Perſuaſions to themſelves, and do not trouble the Church with them; He is to know, that as the Men are <hi>not private,</hi> but of great Note and Authority in the <hi>R.</hi> Church, and the number of their Followers far more conſiderable than of theirs who condemn them; ſo their Sentiments are <hi>not private</hi> neither, but as publick as Diſputing for them, and cenſuring and puniſhing their Oppoſers, can make them.</p>
            <p>But if I can underſtand him, by <hi>private Sentiments,</hi> he means, the Sentiments of Men out of Council; ſo that no meaſure is to be taken of the Doctrine of their Church, by what is delivered by ſuch Men, tho they be Biſhops or Cardinals, and their number never ſo great, and their Declarations never ſo publick and
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:60867:55"/>notorious, and their Cenſures never ſo ſharp againſt thoſe that oppoſe them; for ſtill they are but the <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate</hi> Sentiments of Men out of Council.</p>
            <p>Why then muſt the Repreſenters, or the Vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, or even his Lordſhip the Biſhop of <hi>Meaux</hi>'s Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments concerning the Doctrine of the Church, go for any other than the <hi>private Sentiments of Men?</hi> For their Expoſitions have been neither <hi>made</hi> nor <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved</hi> in General Councils. Muſt Cardinal <hi>Capiſucchi,</hi> the Archbiſhop of <hi>Bourdeaux,</hi> and Father <hi>Craſſet</hi> with his Holy Biſhops and Learned Doctors, nay, and with the Learned of all Nations, be ſaid to deliver only the <hi>Sentiments of private men;</hi> whileſt a few Teachers, that aroſe in this Age, whoſe Party is deſpicable, who labour under the marks of Inſincerity, whoſe Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine being profeſſed in good earneſt, is perſecuted by that Church, whoſe Faith it is ſaid to be; whilſt thoſe Men, I ſay, muſt be thought to deliver the True and Genuine Doctrine of the Church?</p>
            <p>But if neither the one ſide nor the other ſide delivers the Senſe of the Church, Who knows what the Senſe of the Church is, and how ſhall I come by it? The Vindicator directs me to the <hi>Expreſs Words of General and Approved Councils.</hi> But then, I muſt needs ask him, Who is to be Judge of the Senſe of thoſe expreſs Words? I ſee expreſs Words indeed, and I am very apt to think that I do underſtand the Senſe of plain and expreſs Words. But if I may be allowed to underſtand <hi>expreſs Words,</hi> why can I not as well underſtand ſuch Words in the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> as in their Councils? For the Words of the Scripture ſeem to me to be very expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly againſt many things that are held in the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> And here I have been told, that this is not the Senſe of the Scripture, but <hi>my private</hi> Senſe; that the
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:60867:56"/>Scripture is a <hi>Dead Letter,</hi> till the Churches Interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on gives it Life and <hi>Senſe;</hi> that private Judgment is Fallible, and therefore not to be relied upon; that the ſame places ſeem to be <hi>expreſs</hi> to one Man for this thing, and to another Man for that thing; that ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny private Heads as there are, ſo many Bibles there will be; that after all our aſſurance, that we under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand plain and expreſs Texts of Scripture, there is no certainty to be had, but by ſubmitting to Authority, and receiving Doctrines of Faith, not from the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but from the Church.</p>
            <p>Well, I ſubmit to the Church, and ask, Where, or by whom ſhe delivers her <hi>Sence</hi> concerning Doctrines of Faith? <hi>Anſ.</hi> By <hi>her Voice in her General and Approved Councils.</hi> But where is that Voice to be heard? <hi>Anſ. In the expreſs Words of thoſe Councils.</hi> I go therefore to thoſe Councils: God help them that can't. Here in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed I find <hi>expreſs Words,</hi> if a Man could but tell how to come to the Senſe of them; for I thought my ſelf very ſure of the meaning of <hi>expreſs</hi> Words of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: But it ſeems I was miſtaken then. What aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance have I that I am not miſtaken now? For <hi>expreſs</hi> Words, are but as expreſs Words in the Councils, as they are in the Scriptures. And if my Sence of ſuch Words in the Scripture, was but a private Sence before, my Sence alſo of ſuch Words in the Councils is no more now. And therefore if I muſt truſt to my own pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Sence, I ſhall be ſorely tempted to go back again, and to make as good a ſhift as I can, with my private Sence, and the Scriptures together, rather than follow thoſe who tell me my private Sence is not to be truſted, and yet leave me to it at laſt.</p>
            <p>For when all is done, the Churches <hi>Sence,</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to this Man, is a mere Notion of a thing that is
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:60867:56"/>no where to be found; for the ſeveral Sences of her Words in Council, are but the <hi>Sentiments of private Men;</hi> which this Man oppoſes to the Sence of the Church, to ſave his Church from two Poperies. For inſtance, if I go to Cardinal <hi>Capiſucchi</hi> and his Party, to ask them what the Churches <hi>Sence</hi> is, of that <hi>due Honour and Veneration that is to be given to Holy Images,</hi> they tell me, the very ſame that is given to the Perſons re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented by them. But what am I the nearer? for this is but the <hi>Sentiment</hi> of private Men. I go to ask the Biſhop of <hi>Meaux</hi> and his Party, and they cry, <hi>God forbid, the Church requires no ſuch thing.</hi> But I conceive his Sentiment is as private as the Cardinals; and ſo is every bodies elſe that I can ſpeak to; and, which is worſt of all, I muſt not judge between theſe different Parties, which of them ſpeaks the Churches Sence, becauſe I am that way Infallibly thrown upon my own <hi>Sentiments,</hi> which are as <hi>private</hi> as can be.</p>
            <p>In this State, there being no Council ſitting, I have no living Judge upon Earth to help me, and I am ſure I muſt not be a living Judge for my ſelf; ſo that I have no Oracle to go to, but a few <hi>Dead Letters,</hi> which cannot ſpeak; and I have no reaſon to expect, whilſt I am doubting, whether the Words mean <hi>Capiſucchi</hi>'s or <hi>De Meaux</hi>'s Sence, that the Letters ſhould diſappear, and other Letters riſe in the room of them, and make Words plain enough to end the Diſpute. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I think we muſt do as the Vindicator gives leave, and <hi>ſuſpend our Judgment,</hi> at leaſt, till the ſitting of the next <hi>General</hi> and <hi>Approved</hi> Council, that ſhall be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, to interpret the laſt. Tho I do not ſee how that could end the Controverſie; becauſe the Words of that Council too muſt be interpreted by <hi>private</hi> Sence, and ſo to the Worlds end; till Councils have found
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:60867:57"/>out a way to determine Controverſies of Faith, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any <hi>Words</hi> at all. There is, I confeſs, one way left to come to a certainty of the Churches Sence, if we had it, and but one; and that is, for every Body to be Infallible; for by the ſame reaſon that they would take us off from the Scriptures, we have not any ſecurity by Councils, unleſs we had an infallible Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit to interpret; and then, I fancy, there would be no need of Councils at all; for an Infallible way of interpreting the Scriptures, will excuſe any Mans de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendence upon Councils that has it.</p>
            <p>Now after theſe Men have vilified the private uſe of the Scriptures, and have in effect, made nothing of them, for this Child of the Church to come now at laſt, in his diſtreſs, and make as little of General Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils, is a juſt Infatuation upon him: Who does not ſee that to get off the <hi>two Poperies</hi> which are ſo notorious, he will allow nothing to be <hi>Popery</hi> but the very <hi>expreſs Words</hi> of their Councils? which indeed have a Sence, that this Man calls the <hi>Churches Sence;</hi> but then you are to ask no body what that Sence is: For whoever he is that you ask, he gives you but his own Sence, or his <hi>private Sentiment.</hi> And at this rate, I confeſs, it will be impoſſible to find out two Poperies in the Church; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Popery is nothing but the <hi>Churches</hi> Sence. But then you will not be able to find ſo much as <hi>One</hi> Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in the Church, and that, it may be, the Vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor never thought of. For whilſt every body gives his own Sence to the Words of the Council, as they ſay every one of us does to the Words of the Scripture, indeed no Man can be certain that the Churches Sence is not reached by any of the <hi>private Sentiments</hi> of Men; but who has had the good luck to reach it, the Lord knows; for 'tis a Happineſs, which no Man that has
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:60867:57"/>it, can certainly ſay that he has. And therefore, by that Trick, which ſerves him to keep <hi>two Poperies</hi> out of the Church, he has unawares thrown out <hi>all Popery,</hi> excepting that dead Popery that lies buried in the Words of <hi>General</hi> and <hi>approved</hi> Councils.</p>
            <p>Thus ſpeaking of that which we <hi>Term</hi> Old Popery, and his Parties condemning it, he ſays,
<note place="margin">Pag. 6.</note> 
               <hi>So long as there is ſuch a Diſpute betwixt them whom the Church acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges to be her Children, and ſhe does not determine it, any one may hold which ſide they pleaſe as an Opinion, or ſuſpend their Judgment: but neither ſide is truly what you ought to mean by Popery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that 'tis neither Popery to worſhip Images with the ſame Worſhip that is due to what they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent; nor is it Popery to worſhip them with a Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip that is not the ſame; nor is it Popery to worſhip them as it were not at all. And therefore the <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren</hi> of the Church may <hi>hold which ſide they pleaſe as an Opinion;</hi> they may with Cardinal <hi>Capiſucchi</hi> be of the opinion that M. <hi>de Meaux</hi>'s Doctrine concerning due Honour and Veneration <hi>ſavours of Hereſie,</hi> and they may with M. <hi>de Meaux</hi> be of the Opinion, that <hi>Capiſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chi</hi>'s Doctrine ſavours of Idolatry. And they that are of the former Opinion may yet with the Cardinal approve the Biſhops Expoſition; and they that are of the later Opinion, <hi>may</hi> with the Biſhop ſay, That <hi>the Cardinal in his Treatiſe about Images, had ſaid nothing in the whole that contradicteth the Biſhop.</hi> In ſhort, we may take Due <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Veneration,</hi> in this Senſe or in that Senſe, or in any Senſe wherein any of the Children of the Church underſtand it, or if you pleaſe, <hi>no Senſe</hi> whatſoever: For you may <hi>ſuſpend your Judgment.</hi> And if the Vindicator be in the right, that <hi>what he has ſaid in this caſe is applicable to all others;</hi>
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:60867:58"/>Proteſtants, without believing one Doctrine of Faith more than they do already, may be ſaid to have as much Doctrinal Popery as the Members of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church it ſelf.</p>
            <p>I would have the Vindicator think of theſe things, and before he ſends us again to the expreſs Words of his General Councils, to conſider how his Friends have uſed the Scriptures, and us for making them the Rule of our Faith.</p>
            <p>We do not pretend to find in expreſs Words of their General Councils, every thing which we call Old Popery; but we find it in the Profeſſion of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing Part even of the preſent <hi>Roman</hi> Church, and in its oppreſſing thoſe that ſeem in good earneſt to be of another mind. And as we may without blame call that <hi>Popery,</hi> or the Senſe of their Church, which them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves call ſo; ſo we cannot be reproved for ſaying, that their <hi>Popery</hi> ſeems to be the true and genuine Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, becauſe it agrees vaſtly better with the expreſs Words of their Councils, than the Popery of our mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern Expoſitors and Repreſenters. But yet for calling this <hi>Popery,</hi> the Vindicator calls the Defender a <hi>Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repreſenter;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 6, 7.</note> a <hi>Miſrepreſenter and a Calumniator too;</hi> a <hi>Miſrepreſenter, a Falſifier, and a Calumniator.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus he lays about him; without Fear or Wit, and hurts himſelf more than his Adverſary. For his bad Language does furniſh me with a Proof that there are <hi>Two Poperies</hi> amongſt them, which the dulleſt Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion will feel, and the fineſt ſhall not be able to diſtinguiſh away.</p>
            <p>To take the Vindicator's Inſtance once more. Here in <hi>England</hi> I make bold to ſay, that worſhipping Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and Crucifixes with the ſame Worſhip that is due to the Perſons repreſented, is Popery. And for this
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:60867:58"/>by an Authentic Papiſt I am called a Miſrepreſenter, a Falſifier, and a Calumniator too: Which are hard Words, and I would not willingly deſerve them. I would therefore know what is the ſincere Popery in this caſe; and I am told, That Images are not properly to be worſhipped, but the Perſons repreſented only, in <hi>preſence</hi> of their Images. I ſtand corrected, and deſire to know what Rule I am to go by in judging what Popery is in all other Doctrines, that I may not be miſtaken again as I was before. The Vindicator tells me, That what I can prove from the expreſs Words of the Churches Councils, and what they have Poſitively defined and declared, that is Popery as to Doctrines of Faith, and nothing elſe. Well, I am now furniſhed for a Journey into <hi>France,</hi> or <hi>Spain,</hi> or <hi>Italy,</hi> becauſe now I know what Popery is, as a Man ought to do that ventures into thoſe Parts. There, for inſtance, at <hi>Sevil,</hi> or at <hi>Bourdeaux,</hi> I am apt to talk as other fooliſh Men have done before me. <hi>Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifixes,</hi> ſay I, <hi>are upon no account whatſoever to be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured with Divine Worſhip. Images,</hi> ſay I, <hi>are not properly to be Worſhipped: No, God forbid. The Church requires it not,</hi> and ſo forth. But I ſoon find that this <hi>Engliſh Popery</hi> (for ſo I muſt now call it) does not agree with thoſe Climates, and that my Propoſitions are <hi>Heretical</hi> there, and ſince the Definition of the Council of <hi>Trent, intolerable.</hi> I pretend truly that I had my Popery from a Man that admits nothing for Popery but what is proved from the <hi>expreſs Words</hi> of Councils. They laugh at me, and aſſure me, that my Propoſitions are to be found in Councils, neither in expreſs Words, nor by any good Conſequence. I deſire to know if my Propoſitions be contrary to the <hi>expreſs Words</hi> of Councils. They tell me, that they
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:60867:59"/>are contrary to <hi>the Senſe</hi> of the Council of <hi>Trent;</hi> and I find, that unleſs I could ſhew where the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil does expreſly define againſt what they call <hi>Popery,</hi> I ſhall have but little comfort of inſiſting upon my <hi>Engliſh</hi> Rule, That nothing is Popery but what is expreſly defined in Council. For at <hi>Sevil</hi> I am forced to retract: my Propoſitions as Heretical, and at <hi>Bour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deaux</hi> I am Impriſoned; and becauſe I am not <hi>a Man of Renown,</hi> my Lord the Biſhop of <hi>Meaux</hi> will not break with his Friend the Archbiſhop for ſo ſmall a Matter as the Ruine of a <hi>Man of no Renown.</hi> And this I get by learning Popery from the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cator of the <hi>French</hi> Expoſitor. Now if this be not as clear a Demonſtration of two Poperies as any Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in the World needs to have, a Man muſt be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken of his Reaſon, and bereft of his Senſes. For if I ſay this thing <hi>is Popery</hi> here in <hi>England,</hi> I am a <hi>Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repreſenter,</hi> a <hi>Falſifier,</hi> and a <hi>Calumniator too.</hi> If I go into a warmer Sun, and ſay in the ſimplicity of my Heart, concerning the very ſame thing, that it <hi>is not Popery,</hi> there I am <hi>a Miſrepreſenter, a Falſifier, and a Calumniator too,</hi> for ſaying ſo: And, which is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what worſe, if I do but hold my own, they will not only ſay that I am a <hi>Miſrepreſenter,</hi> but they will uſe me like one too, or rather like an <hi>Heretic.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if on the other ſide a Man has but <hi>apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> enough to underſtand when one thing contradicts another, as for example, that to ſay of a certain Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine concerning <hi>Image-Worſhip,</hi> That it is Popery, is a Contradiction to ſaying of the very ſame Doctrine, That it is not Popery, and that the contrary is Popery: And if, on the other ſide, he has <hi>ſenſe</hi> enough to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand when he is rail'd at by thoſe that ſay 'tis not Popery, for ſaying that it is; and worſe than railed
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:60867:59"/>at by thoſe that ſay 'tis Popery, for ſaying that 'tis not: I will give the Vindicator leave to write a Book as big as <hi>Aquinas</hi> his <hi>Summs,</hi> and as full of Subtilty, to prove to the ſame Man, or to any Man elſe, that for all this there are not <hi>Two Poperies</hi> among Papiſts.</p>
            <p>This of Image-Worſhip is the Caſe about which the Vindicator called the Defender all to naught; and concludes with this remarkable Saying: <hi>What I have ſaid in this Caſe, is applicable to all others.</hi> With all my heart, for ſo ſay I too; <hi>What I have ſaid in this Caſe, is applicable to all others; viz.</hi> where we pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend this Diſtinction to hold between Old and New Popery.</p>
            <p>I ſhould now leave this Point, but that he ſtill in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts with an unparallell'd Confidence, that the Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der is a falſe Tranſlator of that Paſſage in the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> which concerns <hi>Reliques.</hi> I ſhall therefore once more go our Fallible way to work, to vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate his Tranſlation, and thereby to ſhew from the <hi>expreſs Words</hi> of the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> that the Old Popery was to <hi>ſeek the Aid of Reliques.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Council having eſtabliſhed the Invocation of Saints,
<note place="margin">Seſſ 6.</note> proceeded alſo to eſtabliſh the Veneration of Reliques, in theſe Words. <q>That the Holy Bodies of the Holy Martyrs, and of others who live with Chriſt, which were the Living Members of Chriſt, and the Temple of the Holy Ghoſt, and to be raiſed up by him to Eternal Life, and glorified, are to be venerated by the Faithful; by which many Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits are from God beſtowed upon Men.</q>
               <note place="margin">Ita ut affirmantes San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorum Reliquiis, venerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem atque honorem non deberi, vel eas aliaque ſacra monumenta à fidelibus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>utiliter honorari; atque EOR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>M opis impetrandae causâ Sanctorum memorias fruſtra frequentari, omnino damnandos eſſe.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>So that they who af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm Veneration and Honour not to be due to the Reliques of the
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:60867:60"/>Saints, or that thoſe and other Sacred Monuments are unprofitably honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the Faithful; and that for the obtaining of THEIR help, the Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the Saints are in vain frequented, are to be condemned.</q>
            </p>
            <p>This is a Literal Tranſlation; and I ſay, That by <hi>THEIR Help</hi> we are to underſtand the Help of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques</hi> and <hi>other Monuments;</hi> not as the Vindicator would have it, of the Saints. To put ſome Colour upon his own Tranſlation, he inverted the Order of the Words as the Defender accuſed him, and he has ſaid nothing to it. But <hi>Their Help</hi> muſt be the Help of <hi>Reliques</hi> and <hi>Monuments,</hi> becauſe otherwiſe the Conſtruction of the <hi>Latin</hi> is Falſe, and againſt Rule. For had the Council meant what the Vindicator ſays, the Words muſt have run thus.</p>
            <p>Or that thoſe and other Sacred Monuments are unprofitably honoured;
<note place="margin">Vel eas, aliaque ſacra mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numenta inutiliter honorari atque SANCTOR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>M opis impetrandae causâ, EO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>R<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>M memorias fruſtra frequentari.</note> and that for the obtaining of the Help of the <hi>Saints, Their</hi> Memories are in vain frequented.</p>
            <p>The Relative <hi>Eorum</hi> had this way been determined to the Saints; and ſo it had been placed, if that had been the meaning; becauſe otherwiſe <hi>Eorum</hi> would, according to the Rules of <hi>Latin</hi> Conſtruction, fall to the ſhare of <hi>Monumenta;</hi> and this tho <hi>Eorum</hi> does by chance agree in Number and Gender with <hi>Sanctorum</hi> that comes afterward; but which comes out of place
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:60867:60"/>there, for <hi>Eorum</hi> to be referred to it, becauſe this Relative had a very good Antecedent of its own be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. This therefore I ſay, That he who Tranſlates a <hi>Latin</hi> Sentence according to true <hi>Latin</hi> Conſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is no Falſe Tranſlator, but a True one; eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly if that Sentence be part of a Work where the <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin</hi> is every where elſe very good, and that Senſe which the Conſtruction makes, agrees with all that is in connexion. And, 1. it agrees very well with the mention of <hi>thoſe many Benefits</hi> which <hi>Reliques</hi> are ſaid to be the Means of. And, 2. It holds with the Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between the Matter of this Period, and that of the foregoing one, much better than the Vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor's Senſe does. For he would have the Help of the Saints to be mentioned here: But let him obſerve, that this was abundantly taken care for in the Proviſion that went immediately before; and therefore if it were Indifferent, as it is not, which way the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction ſhould be carried according to the uſe of <hi>Latin,</hi> this ſhould carry it for ours, that here the Council was engaged in a new Matter, not for the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation</hi> of <hi>Saints,</hi> and the Benefits of that, which are provided for before; but for the <hi>Veneration</hi> of their <hi>Reliques,</hi> and the Benefits that come that way, which is the Buſineſs of this Period. And now the Vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor may conſider, to whom of right the Character of a <hi>Falſe Tranſlator belongs,</hi> of a <hi>Falſifier,</hi> and <hi>a Calumni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator too.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Certainly Controverſies about Religion were never diſgraced by ſuch mean Bickerings as theſe; but who can help it, that has to do with ſuch Men as this Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicator and his Friend the Repreſenter?</p>
            <p>So much for knowing the Senſe of the Church by her Voice in her General and Approved Councils.</p>
            <pb n="110" facs="tcp:60867:61"/>
            <p>Again, We are to know what the Church delivers as a <hi>neceſſary Practice,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 6.</note> 
               <hi>by her univerſally practiſing ſuch things as neceſſary.</hi> I ask therefore,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Did not the Church intend her Public Offices for Rules of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal</hi> Practice? and are they not therefore one Means by which we are to judge of ſuch Practice?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Whether thoſe things are not <hi>neceſſary</hi> to be done in the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, which her Public Offices require?</p>
            <p n="3">3. Whether ſhe does not practice thoſe things <hi>as neceſſary,</hi> which ſhe practiſes in conformity to her own Public. Offices? or, Whether it be <hi>indifferent</hi> for the Children of the Church to obſerve her Rules, or to refuſe to obſerve them?</p>
            <p>The Vindicator underſtood himſelf to be liable to theſe Queſtions; and therefore when he comes to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply this Means of knowing the Churches Senſe in ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Practices, he adds a new Limitation. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nleſs,</hi> ſays he, <hi>you can prove,—That what you term</hi> Old Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery <hi>was delivered as a Practice neceſſary TO SALVA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TION, all you ſay will avail you nothing.</hi> For the Church is to anſwer for nothing which ſhe requires not <hi>as neceſſary to Salvation.</hi> And tho <hi>ſhe obliges all her Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren</hi> to worſhip the <hi>Wood</hi> on <hi>Good-Friday,</hi> and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demns thoſe that refuſe, as Schiſmatics,</hi> as <hi>Imber<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> knows to his Coſt; yet 'tis not the Churches <hi>Senſe</hi> that they ſhould do ſo, becauſe the Rubric does not add that this is <hi>Neceſſary to Salvation.</hi> So that if the Church had commanded us to worſhip <hi>Moloch,</hi> that had not been <hi>Popery</hi> or the Churches <hi>Senſe,</hi> unleſs ſhe had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted that Reaſon for her Command, That 'tis <hi>neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to Salvation</hi> to worſhip <hi>Moloch.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="111" facs="tcp:60867:61"/>
            <p>In a word, The General Practice of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> in the <hi>Service of the Virgin,</hi> the <hi>Invocation of Saints,</hi> and the <hi>Worſhip of Images,</hi> is notorious to the World. And no Man that knows the authorized <hi>Practice,</hi> can doubt of the <hi>Senſe</hi> of the Church, nor be ignorant that in theſe things the Biſhop of <hi>Meaux</hi> has delivered not the Churches Senſe, but his own, if indeed it be his own. The Defender produced an Author of the <hi>Roman</hi> Communion, who concluded that the <hi>true and only Means to free their Religion from the Exceptions of Heretics, was to ſhew that it does not tolerate any thing but what is Good, and that the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lic Worſhip, the Cuſtoms and Doctrines Authorized in it, are Juſt and Holy.</hi> This Author had good Reaſon for what he ſaid, eſpecially againſt the Biſhop of <hi>Meaux,</hi> who <hi>imputed to the</hi> Pagan <hi>Religion thoſe Abuſes which were publicly committed amongſt them,</hi> and <hi>laughed</hi> at the <hi>Expoſitions</hi> of the <hi>Philoſophers,</hi> that would put a good Senſe upon their Abominable Worſhips. The Vindicator ſays, he <hi>admits the Parallel,</hi> but he <hi>is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that it will never make any thing for us, till we can ſhew that the Church does or did make uſe of Racks and Gibbets, and all ſorts of Tortures, to oblige People to believe and practiſe thoſe things which we call Old Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, as the Heathens did to make them worſhip Idols.</hi> That is to ſay, He does not admit the Parallel, tho he ſays he does admit it. For the Biſhop of <hi>Meaux</hi> was brought in charging Paganiſm with a Barbarous and Idolatrous Worſhip, upon the account of their Notorious and Authorized Practices, without regard to their Cruelties upon thoſe that refuſed to comply with them. And therefore if the <hi>Parallel be admitted,</hi> we may conclude an Old Popery from a like general Practice, without enquiring whether <hi>Racks</hi> and <hi>Gibbets,</hi>
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:60867:62"/>and <hi>all ſorts of Tortures</hi> were uſed to enforce it upon the people.</p>
            <p>But the Vindicator has required a wiſe condition to make the Parallel hold; for he ſays in effect, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſtianity appeared againſt Heatheniſm; and till the <hi>Pagans</hi> had ſome people to <hi>hang</hi> and to <hi>torture, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganiſm</hi> could not be charged with a Corrupt and I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatrous Worſhip. And yet if this were neceſſary to be added, <hi>Old Popery</hi> has not been behind hand with the <hi>uſe of Racks and Gibbets and all ſorts of Tortures;</hi> to ſpeak all in a word, it has had, and to this day it has an <hi>Inquiſition</hi> to uphold it.</p>
            <p>As for what he ſays that the Defender muſt <hi>ſhew,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 7.</note> 
               <hi>that the Church allows ſuch wicked Practices as correſpond to his Authors example of Killing and Robbing, and are as dangerous to the Church, as thoſe are to a State.</hi> I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, that the Queſtion is not here, how dangerous thoſe Doctrines and Practices are, which we call <hi>Old Popery;</hi> but whether indeed they are to be charged upon the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> And the Similitude was brought to ſhew, That it is to as little purpoſe to defend the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> againſt our exceptions, by pretending that no deciſion of Council can be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced requiring that Service and Worſhip, which is univerſally given to Saints and Images, as to acquit a City where they rob and kill without contradiction, by ſaying, that there is no Law commanding Men to rob and murther one another.</p>
            <p>As for the danger of thoſe Doctrines and Practices, which we call <hi>Old Popery,</hi> 'tis another Queſtion, in which I am pretty confident, that <hi>Good Man</hi> the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenter,</hi> is bound to appear. He and the Vindicator therefore ſhall agree about it, at their leiſure. I ſhall do my part to bring them fairly together, and ſo
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:60867:62"/>let them compound the matter betwixt them as well as they can.</p>
            <p>The Vindicator felt himſelf born down with thoſe clear Teſtimonies of an <hi>Old Popery,</hi> which the Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der plied him with; and by what appears now, he ſtruggles at laſt with all his might, to make this ſame Popery, if ſo we muſt call it, to be not the Popery <hi>of</hi> the Church, but a Popery rather <hi>in</hi> the Church; and becauſe 'tis of ſo large a Spread, and is manifeſtly upheld by the Authority of the Great Ones; therefore ſome good Words were now to be given it, to ſave the Reputation of the Church; which elſe, will be in great danger of the Similitude of a City that permits <hi>to Rob and Kill without contradiction;</hi> or rather of a City, that rewards Robbers, and puniſhes Honeſt men.</p>
            <p>Wherefore ſays the Vindicator, <hi>Every thing,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 7.</note> 
               <hi>I hope that any one fancies to be ill, is not therefore to be repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</hi> And is it come to this at laſt? We had been in good hands, I ſee, if we had come into the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> upon the Repreſenters Terms. For was it not the <hi>Repreſenter,</hi> that ſaid, <hi>He would as ſoon be a T<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RK as the</hi> Anſwerers <hi>Papiſt?</hi> Now the Anſwerers Papiſt was the <hi>Old Papiſt:</hi> And therefore it was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably and boldly ſaid, That he would as ſoon be a <hi>Turk</hi> as <hi>Our</hi> Papiſt. For one would at leaſt conclude from thence, that the Expounding and Repreſenting Party would have ſtood ſtoutly by us, if we had come in rejecting all that <hi>Popery,</hi> as we uſed to call it, which the Repreſenter had ſo bravely rejected. But if we had taken the Bait, had we not been finely angled up? For what ſays our Repreſenter's other ſelf, the Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cator? Why truly, <hi>Every thing, he hopes, that any one Fancies to be ill, is not therefore to be reproved.</hi> It ſeems then, that the Repreſenter did but <hi>fancy</hi> thoſe things
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:60867:63"/>to be <hi>ill,</hi> which (not he in his miſrepreſenting ſide, but) the Anſwerer charged upon them as Popery: Or, ſhall we ſay, that theſe Men underſtand one another, and that he did not <hi>fanſie</hi> them to be ill, but for the preſent thought good to ſay however that they were monſtrous ill things; and that he would as ſoon be a <hi>Turk</hi> as the Anſwerers <hi>Papiſt?</hi> But I rather think, they did not lay their Heads together upon this Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but that in the deſperate eſtate, to which the Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicator's Cauſe was reduced, by the clear Teſtimonies of ſuch a Popery amongſt them, as the Repreſenter re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects with deteſtation, he found himſelf obliged, for the credit of his Church, and perhaps for his own ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to remit of his Rigour; or rather to take off his Diſguiſe a little, without asking the Repreſenter's leave; and ſo <hi>he hopes that every thing that any one fanſies to be ill, is not therefore to be reproved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the Repreſenter has the leſs reaſon to be angry with our Vindicator, becauſe this Gentleman has made as bold with himſelf, as with his Friend. The Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cator too once <hi>fanſied,</hi> that it was an <hi>ill</hi> thing to <hi>Worſhip the Image of our Saviour or the Holy Croſs with Divine Worſhip, upon any account whatſoever.</hi> But Cardinal <hi>Capiſucchi</hi> came in the way; and ſo <hi>every thing</hi> that the Vindicator himſelf <hi>fanſied to be ill, is not therefore to be reproved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay, he was not content to let the <hi>Old</hi> Popery get up again, but he has been pleaſed to ſink the <hi>New</hi> one as much. For tho Cardinal <hi>Capiſucchi</hi> ſays ſo and ſo, <hi>yet ſeeing others of the ſame Communion reject this, and are NOT CENS<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RED BY THE CH<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RCH; it plainly follows that</hi> his <hi>is not the neceſſary Doctrine of the Church.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 7.</note> 
               <hi>And what he ſays in this caſe is applicable to all others.</hi> Alas for New Popery! for it declines apace;
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:60867:63"/>we had thought it had been ſhewn us for the <hi>True, Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, Standing Sence</hi> of the Church. And now the moſt that can be ſaid for it, is, that it is <hi>not cenſured by the Church.</hi> It ſeems then, that theſe Expounders and Repreſenters, are but a <hi>Tolerated Party:</hi> One ſtep more backwards, makes them not to be ſo much as <hi>Tolerated,</hi> and the next news we ſhall hear, is, that they are <hi>Intolerable.</hi> But, by the way, what Church does the Vindicator mean, by ſaying that he and his, are <hi>not cenſured by the Church?</hi> I fanſie he means, the Inviſible Church which cannot now be ſeen, becauſe no Council is ſitting. The Fathers that ſate at <hi>Trent,</hi> do not ſtart out of their Graves to declare theſe Gentlemen <hi>Heretically</hi> inclined; and the <hi>Books</hi> of the Council do not riſe up and fly in their Faces. For if we mind what the Authority of the now <hi>Living,</hi> and <hi>Viſible</hi> Church declares in this caſe, we ſee that they who reject this <hi>Old Popery,</hi> as we call it, <hi>are cenſured by the Church:</hi> and, to mention <hi>Imbert</hi> no more, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of <hi>Aegidius Magiſtralis,</hi> Canon of <hi>Sevil</hi> in <hi>Spain,</hi> is a Conviction to the Vindicator of ſomething that I will not name. For he was forced to abjure theſe two Propoſitions as <hi>Heretical.</hi> 1. <hi>That the Images of Saints are not to be adored with the ſame Adoration with which the Prototypes are adored.</hi> 2. <hi>That the Croſs is to be worſhipped only with an Inferiour Adoration.</hi> This ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Inſtance being produced by the Defender out of <hi>Capiſucchi,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pref. P. XIV. XV.</note> who left it for a <hi>Caution</hi> and a <hi>Conviction</hi> to ſuch Men, as in good earneſt maintain our Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cators Doctrine; for the Vindicator to mention <hi>Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſucchi</hi>'s Doctrine, and to ſay in the ſame breath, that they who reject it <hi>are not cenſured by the Church,</hi> is of a piece with his Sincerity every where elſe. Well, but let that paſs, and let us conſider what will come of this, if it be true, <hi>that they are not cenſured by the Church.</hi>
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:60867:64"/>Really this is but a ſmall encouragement to take Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery upon the <hi>Repreſenter's</hi> Terms: For that which is <hi>not now cenſured</hi> by the Church, <hi>may</hi> in good time be <hi>cenſured</hi> by the Church. Perhaps you will ſay there is no reaſon to fear it: But in my mind there is; for, as I ſaid before, the Credit of this <hi>New Popery</hi> has ſunk extremely in a Month; for in truth the Vindicator has degraded it from being <hi>Popery,</hi> as we obſerved ſome time ſince. Now if it be not ſo much as <hi>Popery,</hi> it may in a little time grow to be <hi>Hereſie,</hi> and then the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of the Church will follow as faſt as can be: In the mean time, it is not <hi>Popery:</hi> And ſo fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel to the Repreſenter's Undertakings, which are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrown beyond all recovery; unleſs he faces about, and recovers his Credit, by beating the Vindicator out of the Field with his own Hand.</p>
            <p>The Repreſenter at firſt gave us a two-fold Character of Popery: One was of <hi>That Popery which the Papiſts own and profeſs,</hi> as appears in the Title Page of his Firſt Part. In his very firſt Article of <hi>Praying to Images,</hi> the <hi>Popery</hi> which <hi>the Papiſts own and profeſs</hi> amounts to this, That <hi>properly</hi> they do not ſo much as <hi>Honour I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages,</hi> but only <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Saints.</hi> This is the <hi>Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> of the Repreſenting ſide.</p>
            <p>What now ſays the Vindicator? He very honeſtly acknowledges that there is a <hi>private Sentiment</hi> in the Church againſt this, that will have the <hi>Image of Chriſt worſhipped with the ſame Worſhip as Chriſt himſelf;</hi> and what does he conclude upon it? Why, that <hi>any one may hold which ſide they pleaſe as an Opinion, or ſuſpend their Judgment, but neither ſide is truly what you ought to mean by Popery.</hi> And therefore I conceive that if neither ſide be Popery, the Repreſenters ſide is not Popery, but a private Opinion, which the Church has not yet <hi>cenſured</hi> as the Vindicator ſays.</p>
            <pb n="117" facs="tcp:60867:64"/>
            <p>Now what the Vindicator <hi>ſaid in this Caſe, is appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable to all others;</hi> where the Anſwerer plainly ſhewed, that the Eminent and Leading Men of the <hi>R.</hi> Church were of a different <hi>Sentiment</hi> from the Repreſenter. Whereas therefore the Repreſenter either promiſed or threatned great matters in his Introduction: <hi>I'll endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour,</hi> ſays he, <hi>to ſeparate theſe Calumnies and Scandals from what is REALLY THE FAITH AND DOCTRINE OF THE CH<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RCH. I'll take off the Black and Dirt which has been thrown upon her, and ſet her forth in her GEN<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>INE Complexion.</hi>—I'll <hi>Repreſent a Papiſt whoſe Faith and Exerciſe of his Religion is according to the Direction and Command of the Church:</hi> The Vindicator has on the other hand knocked him down at one blow: For, ſays he, <hi>So long as the Church determines not the Diſpute, any one may hold which ſide they pleaſe as an opinion, but neither ſide is truly what you ought to mean by Popery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This ſhews that I was not much out of the way, when I noted the great hazard of theſe Expounding and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenting deſigns. The truth is, it was ſo nice a work, that in prudence they ought to have commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it to one hand, and the Repreſenter ſhould have been the Vindicator. For while they are two, and and each of them driven to ſtraits, one of them being preſſed on one ſide, and the other on another ſide, the danger was great, that each of them would ſhift for himſelf a ſeveral way, and be expoſed to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches of one another.</p>
            <p>Thus it happened, that the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> being preſſed by his Adverſaries, for not having fairly <hi>Repreſented</hi> Popery, was fain at laſt to make a Rule to know the Churches Senſe by, which might ſerve his turn; and what ſhould that be, but the <hi>Currant paſſing of his Book
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:60867:65"/>amongſt Catholics:</hi> for this, he thinks, was enough to ſhew, that the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of it was <hi>Authentic.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the <hi>Vindicator</hi> being preſſed with the Oppoſition that is made in the <hi>Roman</hi> Communion, to the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the <hi>Expoſition,</hi> and perceiving that <hi>Currant paſſing</hi> would not ſerve his turn, he, I ſay, comes out a Month after the <hi>Repreſenter,</hi> and will not allow any thing to make Doctrine <hi>Authentic,</hi> under the <hi>expreſs Words of a General Approved Council;</hi> and he has ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly undone the poor Repreſenter's Rule of <hi>Currant paſſing,</hi> which he thought was enough to ſhew that his Doctrine was <hi>Authentic.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay, the unfortunate Vindicator has blown up the <hi>Expoſition</hi> of the Biſhop of <hi>Meaux,</hi> as well as the <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters</hi> of the Repreſenter; which indeed could not be avoided, becauſe one muſt neceſſarily follow the Fate of the other. For the Biſhop's <hi>Expoſition</hi> was ſolemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pretended to be, <hi>An Expoſition of the Doctrine of the Catholic Church in Matters of Controverſie;</hi> that is to ſay, An Expoſition of <hi>Popery.</hi> But the Biſhop has ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded many things for the Doctrine of the <hi>Catholic</hi> Church, which <hi>other Members of the ſame Church con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn;</hi> and ſo long as the Diſpute remains undeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, <hi>neither Side is truly what you ought to call Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery.</hi> And therefore the Biſhop ſhould have called his Book <hi>An Expoſition of his own Private Sentiment con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Doctrine of the Catholic Church:</hi> Thus, I ſay, he ſhould have called it, or elſe he ſhould have found out another Vindicator.</p>
            <p>Nay, becauſe the greateſt Grace that his Doctrine ſeems now to have from the Church, is, That <hi>it is not cenſured by the Church:</hi> The Title ſhould have been a little more wary, by running thus: <hi>An Expoſition of the Biſhop's Private Sentiment, which the Church has not
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:60867:65"/>yet cenſured, concerning the Doctrine of the Catholic Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But becauſe in truth the Living Church has begun to cenſure his Doctrine, and they who have cenſured it, are not cenſured for it: The Title ſhould have been yet more warily contrived, thus: <hi>An Expoſition of the Biſhop's Private Sentiment, which Sentiment is not contrary to the expreſs Words of a General Approved Council.</hi> Then perhaps the Vindicator might have done ſomething in diſcharge of the Duty of a <hi>Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cator.</hi> But as the caſe ſtands, he ought henceforward to change his Name, and to write himſelf the <hi>Betray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> of the Biſhop of <hi>Meaux</hi>'s Expoſition, but by no means the <hi>Vindicator</hi> of it.</p>
            <p>Which himſelf ſo well underſtood, that he thought fit to <hi>paſs over all the Letter</hi> of the Defender to the Biſhop; and he gives this ſubſtantial Reaſon for it, Becauſe the Letter <hi>concerns not him,</hi> the Vindicator, <hi>nor the Doctrine of the Catholic Church which</hi> he <hi>is to vindicate.</hi> In good time! But the Letter ſorely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned the <hi>Biſhop,</hi> and the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of his <hi>Expoſition;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 8.</note> and therefore if it does <hi>not concern</hi> the Vindicator, you are not to wonder at it, becauſe there have been great Changes of late, and now the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of the <hi>Biſhop's Expoſition</hi> is one thing, and the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of the <hi>Catholic Church</hi> is another.</p>
            <p>I may without breach of Modeſty ſay, that hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to I have given the Vindicator a <hi>Full</hi> Reply. And I believe the Reader would be well ſatisfied that I ſhould drop him here, and leave his following Cavils to be confuted by any one that will take the pains to compare him and the Defender together. But then this would be a Pretence for another Book, and for ſome boaſting that he is not anſwered. A little there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:60867:66"/>muſt be ſaid to what remains.
<note place="margin">Pag. 8.</note> And,</p>
            <p n="1">1. By <hi>many of the Roman Caſuiſts allowing the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famation of an Adverſary by falſe Accuſations,</hi> as the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender ſaid in his <hi>Table,</hi> it is ſo plain by the Book, that he meant no more than that they maintained it to be <hi>but a Venial Sin,</hi> that the Vindicator himſelf has not queſtioned it; and therefore it was a mere Cavil to tax the Defender of <hi>Falſifying</hi> in this buſineſs; tho to incourage the Vindicator to do well another time, thus much he is to be commended for, that he limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his Accuſation to the expreſſion of <hi>Allowing,</hi> which he found in the <hi>Table. This, Sir, as you here word it, is a Falſe Imputation.</hi> Even where he does ill, I am glad that he does no worſe. But to ſpeak to the thing, They that make one of the baſeſt things in nature to be but a <hi>Venial Sin,</hi> cannot rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably be otherwiſe underſtood, than that they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to make it eaſie for their own Party to commit it: And tho they flouriſh never ſo fairly with that Rule, that <hi>No Evil is to be done that Good may come of it;</hi> yet there are ſo many little ways amongſt them of clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves from Venial Sins, that when ſo foul a Wickedneſs is made <hi>but Venial,</hi> it can be with no other deſign than to <hi>encourage</hi> men to it; and I think I may put it to the Vindicator, whether an <hi>Encouragement</hi> to ſin, be not equivalent to an <hi>Allowance</hi> of it. He grants the Pope condemned theſe Propoſitions, and ſeems to make ſome advantage of it, as if they were now ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver more to be told of them; becauſe the <hi>Supreme Paſtor</hi> has condemned them. But before he inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ates any ſuch Concluſions again, I would deſire him to inquire of <hi>F. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>C.</hi> what became of the Popes Brief to that purpoſe, in <hi>France;</hi> tho I believe there are ſome Fathers nearer hand that can inform him, if he knows it not already.</p>
            <pb n="121" facs="tcp:60867:66"/>
            <p>As for his endeavour to clear himſelf of denying what his Adverſary proved upon this occaſion,
<note place="margin">Pag. 8.</note> let him believe that he is come well off if he can: I will not purſue him as if it was hard to get him at an Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage.</p>
            <p n="2">2.
<note place="margin">Pag. 9. Def. Pag. 54, 55.</note> He ſays the <hi>Defender far exceeds him</hi> in giving <hi>Obliging Titles,</hi> otherwiſe called Hard Words. The Defender put thoſe together which he complained of, and they are a pretty Company. The Vindicator refers us to the Defence from Pag. 49 to 54. to ſhew how he has been uſed: I have read over thoſe Pages, and I find the Defender there <hi>preparing himſelf to encounter Rudeneſs and Incivility</hi> Pag. 49. <hi>eſteeming it <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nchriſtian to return his Adverſaries Revilings,</hi> Pag. 50. ſhewing in him the marks of a <hi>Calumniating Spirit,</hi> and that he is an <hi>unfit Witneſs to be credited againſt</hi> an Adverſary, Pag. 51, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> It ſeems he ſhould have ſaid that the Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicator was a very Civil, Moderate, Fair-ſpoken and Honeſt Gentleman, that had abuſed no body. If we do not commend theſe Men, as much as they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend themſelves, we muſt be thought to rail at them, as much as they do at us. For my own part, I have not <hi>Complemented</hi> the Vindicator, but I have ſpared him, and he ought to thank me for it; tho I do not much care whether he does or no, unleſs withal he intends to deſerve well for the time to come.</p>
            <p n="3">3. To his Cavil at the Defenders arguing that the Bp. of <hi>Meaux</hi>'s <hi>We ſuppoſe,</hi> or as the Vindicator ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders him, <hi>We believe,</hi> or as the <hi>French</hi> may be rendred, <hi>We eſteem,</hi> is <hi>no Argument of the truth of that Doctrine,</hi> which he ſo propounds: I reply, that the Defender did not thereupon infer, that the Biſhop had no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Argument to produce. By the way,
<note place="margin">Pag. 3.</note> I tell the Vindicator, that he cannot produce a better for that
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:60867:67"/>Doctrine that was in queſtion.
<note place="margin">Def. p. 57.</note> But for him to ſay, That the Defender <hi>ſees he cannot now deny that that was a Falſification,</hi> tho in Truth he would not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low it ſo much as to be a <hi>Miſtake,</hi> is to give us more and more reaſon to conclude that we muſt have done with theſe Men; for why ſhould a Man under reſtraint, go on to argue with another that feels none?</p>
            <p>To his other Cavil, that the Defender brings in the Biſhop <q>obſerving that St. <hi>Paul concluded that</hi> Chriſt <hi>himſelf ought not to be any more offered,</hi> without put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in the following Words, <hi>up to death for us.</hi>
               </q> I reply, that the Defender by <hi>Offering,</hi> meant <hi>offering to death,</hi> as he ſaid in his laſt Defence, and that without ſuch a Suppoſition <hi>his Argument was loſt.</hi> But of this the Vindicator would take no notice. I add, that there was no need of repeating thoſe Words that were o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, becauſe <hi>Chriſt</hi> was ſpoken of before as a <hi>Victim offered for ſin.</hi> Nor was there any need of ſaying this, but that I do in my Conſcience believe, that we have to do with ſuch a Repreſenter and a Vindicator, as are not this day to be matched within the Lines of Communication: If we go any further, I think I know of <hi>One</hi> that will ſet 'em hard.</p>
            <p n="4">4. For what concerns the Tranſlation of the Biſhops Letter, it was certainly but juſt in the Defender to anſwer Mr. <hi>de Meaux</hi>'s Senſe, and not his Tranſlators Blunders. But now for that wiſe Remark which the Vindicator has made upon that Paſſage, <hi>Pag.</hi> 11. he had done much more prudently to have conſidered what the Defender told him, That really he is not Maſter enough of the <hi>French</hi> Language to pretend to turn <hi>Critick</hi> in it, than to have given the World ſo evident a Demonſtration of it. Every one knows that is at all ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with that Tongue, that <hi>Cartons</hi> do not ſignifie
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:60867:67"/>in general <hi>any Leaves,</hi> but ſuch Leaves as are put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the room of others that are taken out of a Book; and therefore to add <hi>Cartons</hi> to a Book, is as the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender truly rendred it; to <hi>take out ſome Leaves and put in others in the room of them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. The Defender named thoſe Accuſations of the Vindicator againſt him, which he could not know to be true, and gave ſome Reaſons for ſaying ſo. But the Vindicator charging the Defender with the like, has neither given one Reaſon, or ſo much as one Inſtance.</p>
            <p>As for this Mans accuſing the Defender, of things which he <hi>knew to be evidently Falſe;</hi> the Defender in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanced in the Vindicators charging him with <hi>Falſifying Cajetan</hi> upon the Queſtion of <hi>Extreme <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction;</hi> tho it was moſt evident, that he had not falſified <hi>Cajetan,</hi> as he ſhewed in his Second Defence. Upon this the Vindicator declares in <hi>the Preſence of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag 10.</note> 
               <hi>— the Aven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of all wilful Crimes, That he never accuſed his Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary of any thing, but what he thought (nay had proved) him evidently guilty of: And he thinks he has now ſatisfied the World, that in that very inſtance, the Defender is a Falſiſier.</hi> And for this he refers in the Margin to his <hi>Letter to the Author of the Diſcourſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Extreme <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction.</hi> Well, the firſt uſe I make of this, is to Adore the Mercy and Patience of the Great God to whom this Man has appealed: I lay no ſtreſs at preſent upon the <hi>obvious</hi> right in this matter; but as far as I can recollect, he could not but have ſeen that Authors Anſwer to his Letter, before this <hi>Full An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer</hi> of his came out of the Preſs. And then, the Lord have mercy upon him. One thing I am ſure of, that he either wants that Conſcience or that Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding which are required to ſwearing in Truth and
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:60867:68"/>Judgment, who can after ſuch a Conviction, declare in the Preſence of Almighty God, that he has proved the Defender a Falſifier of <hi>Cajetan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6.
<note place="margin">Pag. 10.</note> As to his <hi>Scandalous Reflections</hi> upon the Church of <hi>England,</hi> he refers us for a proof of whatever he has ſaid, to a late Book called <hi>Good Advice to the Pulpits;</hi> which if it does prove thoſe things againſt us, which it pretends to do, does not yet juſtifie one quarter of that Reviling which he has diſcharged a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us. But whereas he ſays, that Book <hi>alone is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to make our Party aſhamed,</hi> I muſt tell him that his Boaſt is a little unſeaſonable, ſince his Party may have in a little time ſome cauſe to be aſhamed of the Book; and the Vindicator in particular, for having boaſted of it. I have a ſtrong Fanſie that the <hi>Good Advice</hi> is the <hi>Repreſenter's</hi> own: But the Vindicator's good Words of it, will not, I gueſs, make amends for undoing the Repreſenter in his main Chance.</p>
            <p n="7">7. For that Parallel which the Defender required to the account of things in Q. <hi>Elizabeths</hi> time, for which Dr. <hi>Heylin</hi> is quoted; this Man ſays no more than to this purpoſe, That if it were not for ſome <hi>hot-headed Spirits,</hi> theſe <hi>brangles about Religion</hi> might be ended. Which is as much as to ſay, that he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuated ſomething, which his Superiours have forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den him to own. It ſeems that it was to be inſinuated, but not ſpoken plainly. But becauſe he forbears I ſhall do ſo too, and refer my ſelf to the World, if he has not now made <hi>Nonſence</hi> of the Application of <hi>Hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin</hi>'s Account.</p>
            <p n="8">8. As to his being a Spy upon the Defender, his Vindication of himſelf, is the very Maſter-piece of his Anſwer: For no Man that cloſely attends to his Words, can tell whether he denies or confeſſes it; tho to a
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:60867:68"/>Superficial Reader he ſeems to deny it. His Words are elaborately put together, and tho I am in very great haſte, yet I muſt needs let the Reader ſee them. <hi>If I reflected upon your preaching, it was from meer report</hi> (but he might be at Church, when he did not reflect upon the Defenders preaching) <hi>for I aſſure you, Sir, what you were told of my being ſometimes a part of your Auditory, is like many other Stories which you abound with in all your Writings, I ſuppoſe too from hear-ſay.</hi> But if the Defender were not told of it, but ſaw him at Church, then this comes not within the Caſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he had it not then from <hi>Hear-ſay,</hi> but from <hi>Eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight.</hi> Again, if the Defender were told of it, then indeed he had it from <hi>Hear-ſay,</hi> but he might hear the Truth for all that. The Vindicator was afraid of Proof, and I adviſe him to be ſo ſtill. That which follows is juſt ſuch another pleaſant Strain; it concerns the <hi>Sunday Night Conferences;</hi> but the Reader ſhall go for that himſelf, as he likes the other.</p>
            <p>But whereas upon this occaſion of the Defenders Preaching, he bids him ask his Conſcience, <hi>Whether they who acknowledge only One God whom they muſt adore can be guilty of ſuch a Horrid Crime, as to give Divine Worſhip to Saints?</hi> I have asked the Defender about it, who has alſo asked his Conſcience, and in the name of his Conſcience, he ſays, That they <hi>may be guilty of that Horrid Crime.</hi> And more then that, he intends to give theſe Men ſuch Reaſons for his Concluſion, as he is in his Conſcience perſuaded, cannot be fairly anſwered. In the mean time, I will give the Vindicator a Queſtion for his Queſtion, and deſire him to put it to his own Conſcience, <q>Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a Woman who acknowledges only one Husband,
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:60867:69"/>to whom ſhe muſt pay Conjugal Duty, can be guil-of ſuch a horrid Crime, as to give her Husband's Bed to another?</q> And then let him uſe a little Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience in the Application.</p>
            <p n="9">9. For what next follows, That he would not be thought to have abuſed the Defender's <hi>Auditory;</hi> that the Defender had better give up the Cauſe; that he gave ill Language and juſtified it; that he believes every <hi>idle Report</hi> of the Biſhop of <hi>Meaux,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 11, 12.</note> rather than his <hi>Vindication;</hi> and his explaining of the Word <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries;</hi> this ſhall all paſs off quietly.</p>
            <p n="10">10. And ſo ſhould his next Reflexion too, but that he is ſo warm upon it, that he muſt not be neglected. The Defender had affirmed thoſe Expreſſions of St. <hi>Germane,</hi> St. <hi>Anſelm,</hi> and the reſt of 'em, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Virgin, which <hi>Craſſet</hi> had tranſcribed, to be <hi>horrid Blaſphemies.</hi> This the Vindicator could not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure. The Defender therefore tranſcribed them out of <hi>Craſſet,</hi> and left the Reader to judge. What now ſays the Vindicator? Why truly he knew not well what to ſay: To confeſs plainly that they were <hi>Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies,</hi> would be to vindicate the Defender: To de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny it plainly, was yet a little too ſoon; for tho New Popery was drawing on, it had not yet breathed its laſt. He took a middle Courſe, and thus informs the Defender.
<note place="margin">Pag. 12.</note> 
               <hi>Had you only ſaid that Father</hi> Craſſet <hi>had collected ſuch Paſſages from thoſe great Saints, as if ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in that ſtrict and dogmatical ſenſe he brought them for, might be called</hi> Blaſphemies, <hi>that Father muſt only have anſwered for them.</hi> This Man has a notable Gift of Speaking, and ſaying nothing, which does him great ſervice at a pinch. He does not ſay, That if thoſe Paſſages were taken in that <hi>ſtrict</hi> and <hi>dogmatical ſenſe</hi> for which <hi>Craſſet</hi> brought them, then they might
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:60867:69"/>be called <hi>Blaſphemies;</hi> for this had been to bring Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Craſſet</hi> upon his back, with all thoſe great Saints, which <hi>Craſſet</hi> had already raiſed up againſt <hi>Widenfelt.</hi> And yet he does not ſay, That if the Defender <hi>had ſaid</hi> what he ſuppoſes for him, that Father <hi>Craſſet</hi> could have brought himſelf off: No, he anſwers more wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, That <hi>that Father muſt only have anſwered for them;</hi> which, it may be, he could, and it may be, he could not. Now here he ſhould have ended: For <hi>Craſſet</hi> may take himſelf to be ſacrificed in what follows. <hi>But to lay them to thoſe Holy Saints Charges, to call them Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious Men, their Expreſſions horrid Blaſphemies, — is what truly pious Ears cannot hear without Indignation.</hi> For Father <hi>Craſſet</hi> is in an ill caſe, if to lay the Holy Saints Expreſſions in <hi>Craſſet</hi>'s ſenſe, to the charge of the Holy Saints, be what <hi>truly pious Ears cannot hear without Indignation.</hi> But I beg the Vindicator's Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don; for now I ſee how <hi>Craſſet</hi> may be brought off again, or rather the Vindicator. For perhaps that <hi>which pious Ears cannot hear,</hi> is not every Particular by it ſelf, but altogether; <hi>i. e. pious Ears</hi> may hear thoſe Paſſages laid to the charges of the Saints, even in <hi>Craſſet</hi>'s ſenſe; but that therefore thoſe Saints ſhould be called <hi>Superſtitious</hi> Men, and their Expreſſions <hi>Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid Blaſphemies,</hi> as they were, not by <hi>Craſſet,</hi> but by the <hi>Defender;</hi> this is what <hi>truly pious Ears cannot hear without Indignation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now after all this dexterity, he has not offered to ſhew that thoſe Paſſages which the Defender produced are not <hi>horrid Blaſphemies,</hi> or that they are capable of a good ſenſe. If the Reader has forgot them, he may go to the Defender for them, <hi>p.</hi> 89, 90, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and then he will be ſatisfied that all this ſhuffling comes to no more than this; that the Vindicator cannot bear any
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:60867:70"/>thing that reflects diſhononourably upon his <hi>Great</hi> and <hi>Holy Saints;</hi> but his <hi>pious Ears</hi> can hear Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions from them that do <hi>blaſphemouſly</hi> reflect upon <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God,</hi> without any <hi>Indignation</hi> at all.</p>
            <p n="11">11. The Defender produced thoſe <hi>Prayers</hi> and <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies</hi> in the <hi>Conſecration of a Croſs,</hi> which to him ſeemed to be <hi>Magical Incantations rather than Prayers.</hi> The Vindicator, to be even with him, ſays, That we <hi>uſe the like Prayers and Ceremonies in the Conſecration of Churches and Chappels.</hi> Now if we do, then I for my part will ſay, That our Prayers upon that Occaſion look more like <hi>Magical Incantations</hi> than <hi>Prayers.</hi> But why did not the Vindicator produce the <hi>like Prayers</hi> to thoſe which the Defender produced? Will any Man think that his good Nature would not ſuffer him to ſhame us ſo grievouſly? Or does the Vindicator think that he is of ſuch Credit, that his Word muſt be taken for any thing he ſays? He refers indeed to <hi>Sparrow</hi>'s Collection of Canons, <hi>p.</hi> 375. But why not a few Lines tranſcribed from thence, to match the Defender's particular Allegations? Even becauſe the Place would not afford them. I grant, that we ſet Perſons and Places too apart for the Service of our Maker, by Prayer and Ceremony. But do we pray that the <hi>Stones of the Church</hi> may be <hi>a ſaving Remedy to Mankind,</hi> as they do that the <hi>Wood of the Croſs</hi> may be ſo? Do we pretend to derive any Virtue upon them, which is afterwards to be derived from them; or that by the Holineſs of our Churches we may <hi>be redeemed from Sin,</hi> as they hope to be by <hi>the Merits</hi> of a Conſecrated <hi>Croſs;</hi> for ſo they pray at the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecration of it? This, and the like, is that which ſeems to be <hi>Magical Incantation:</hi> But for which he cannot find an appearance of a Parallel amongſt us,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:60867:70"/>any more than he could for that ſort of Conjuring, which they call <hi>Exorciſing,</hi> and for which he has ſaid never a word; and it had not been the worſe for him, if he had ſaid as little for <hi>the pious and ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant Ceremonies of</hi> his <hi>Church</hi> in the Conſecration of <hi>Croſſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="12">12. He ſays, The <hi>Guide in Controverſie</hi> remains un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anſwered. To which I ſhall not think it enough to ſay what he does to the Catalogue of our unanſwer'd Books, That <hi>he ſhould have told us whether 'tis worth anſwering in particular or no, when all that is ſaid in it, is obviated in many Treatiſes;</hi> tho I am very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident that this is the very Truth. But I ſhall add, 1. That ſome Parts of the <hi>Guide in Controverſie</hi> have been anſwered, and the very Foundations of it over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown, in Dr. <hi>Stilling fleet</hi>'s <hi>Second Diſcourſe in Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the Proteſtant Grounds of Faith, &amp;c. in anſwer to the Guide in Controverſies by R. H.</hi> Imprimatur Sam. Parker. April 15. 1673. Again, the Fourth Diſcourſe in the Second Edition ſet forth 1673, is anſwered in <hi>The Difference between the Proteſtant and Socinian Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods,</hi> publiſhed about a Year ſince. And the Fifth Diſcourſe in Vindication of the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> was anſwered in the Second Part of the <hi>Neceſſity of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation.</hi> To which we have had no Return. And we think our ſelves to be upon equal Terms at leaſt with our Adverſaries, as to this very Book. But, 2. For what wants a particular Anſwer, I am apt to think that this unſeaſonable Boaſt of the Vindicator will prove an Occaſion of depriving his Party even of that little thing they have to ſay in this kind; and therefore they will tell him, I doubt, that he men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned it a little too ſoon. For what he ſays, <hi>That they may be attacked as the other Diſcourſes of the ſame
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:60867:71"/>Author lately publiſhed at</hi> Oxford, <hi>with the like Misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune:</hi> I reply, That hitherto the Anſwers have had the fortune to remain without any Returns; which if it be a <hi>Misfortune</hi> to the Authors, 'tis for this only Reaſon that I can think of, That the oftner our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries write in the way of Replies and Anſwers, the more they diſcover their own Nakedneſs, as I am pretty ſure the Repreſenter and the Vindicator have done for their parts.</p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:60867:71"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
